hi my dear students hello everyone if I
am Audible and visible properly please
please let me know in the comment
section hey budies are you getting my
voice
yes or no come on let me know in the
comment
section and buddies please be
active and today we are going to do a
yes hi good afternoon s how are you so
it's a yes okay great great
great
hi good afternoon to all my dear
students so we are live sharp at 12 and
uh I don't know how much time will it
take but we will complete whole syllabus
of zoology all the different chapters of
zoology of your class 12th we are going
to complete today yes ready
everyone no buddies it's a Maha Marathon
now what do I mean by these Maha
Marathon I know you guys are apping for
your board examination isn't it and your
board examination is here right how many
days are left after all one week and now
in this one week we will complete we
have to complete the full full syllabus
now I have a strategy for you now this
is specifically again I'm saying for the
board examination yes this is not
related to the previous session which we
had so this is yes one week is left and
the today we are are going to uh prepare
for it what we are going to do is today
we will complete our zoology part so
once you will you are done with the
zoology part after that you will be
having five days five to six days where
you can do your own revision so I will
be completing everything yes I am going
to start with the human reproduction
reproductive Health then we will be
talking about the evolution
biotechnology human health and diseases
every chapter each and everything we
will be dealing okay so it's it is a
good thing that uh we are preparing as
you know uh for the board examination we
will do great and what we are expecting
how many marks do you really
expect yes
definitely it's a English Channel so I
cannot talk in Hindi
Rahul 70 70 very nice so after after
this session as we will complete each
and every part each and everything so
yes your target 70 will be completed but
you have to be with me in this session
from the first minute to the last minute
H right so first of all everybody
promise me that you're going to watch
this video
full 100 out of 100 it's a 70 Theory
thank you so much so 70 out of 70 we are
targeting today and everything I today
dealing with with the zoology and
zoology we will be completing yes so
first minute to last minute isn't it
great so what all things I need from
your side so first thing is are you
having your ncrt with you if yes that is
good take out your ncrt class 12
ncrt definitely samya definitely I will
be taking I will be teaching you
everything which is important for your
board examination again I'm mentioning
so please first of all all you all
should have your ncrt take out a
notebook any notebook you should have
your pencil you should have your pen
with
you tomorrow that will be a session
there will be session of botney soon you
will get to know okay JP San okay yes
ready ncrt you should have your ncrt
with
you it will it will definitely take some
hours 6 7 8 but we will read read
everything we'll study
everything see uh nav I won't say the
ncrt the concepts are there but it will
be a theory examination where you have
to write suppose it's a five marker so
as per the five marker things are not
clearly mentioned in ncrt so that is the
reason hello Namaste thank you so much
so first of all share with your school
friends and call them here and let's
enjoy this session let's start this
Maham marathon and starting with the
first chapter which is a human
reproduction so let's start so this is
how we will be proceeding human
reproduction reproductive Health
Evolution biotechnology two chapter
principle and processes then
biotechnology application human health
and diseases yeah all these chapters we
will be doing D dad and
D Samia definitely out don't don't be
worried just be with me in this session
and get ready with your you know the
notes I mean to say a blank notebook and
try uh writing down whenever I'll say
this diagram is important just draw that
diagram also simultaneously okay okay
and yes buddies you will get this PDF
whatever I'll write on the board you
will get this PDF now you will be having
6 days after uh today you'll be having
six days in that time period you can go
through these notes you can take out a
print out whatever you want you can just
go through them ready everyone yes let's
start the session Lear okay so first
chapter which we are going to start is a
human reproduction you all know super
important chapter and from this chapter
you can directly expect five marker
majority every year you can expect a
direct five marker from this topic human
reproduction that can come from U
Genesis or spermatogenesis or menal
cycle these are the most important thing
how to write when it is a when a five
marker type question comes we'll be
discussing everything okay
so let's start so introduction first
I'll be giving you introduction and
slowly we will be proceeding okay
human
reproduction okay tell me in humans
sexual reproduction occur or asexual
reproduction human sexual reproduction
occur sexual
reproduction
right sexual reproduction and if I talk
about a male male produces
sperms male produces sperm process of
formation of sperm is termed as
spermatogenesis
sperato
Genesis
clear sperms are there now let's talk
about the female female produces
egg production of the egg is termed as o
Genesis U
Genesis in total these two names they
are termed as
gametogenesis
gito Genesis
is so U Genesis is also gametogenesis
spermatogenesis is also gametogenesis
how can I say this because here these
are the gametes and both these gametes
they are
n right they are heid now what happens
next is now there is a Next Step due to
which there is a formation of a
zygote zygote the process by which
zygote formation occur is termed as
fertilization this is
fertilization right then what happens
next buddies then there is
development
development right baby will be developed
and in that particular period if I talk
about that period so that period again
I'm saying that is a 40 weeks it takes
40 weeks or the 9 month for the
development ultimately there is
paration partur means giving birth to a
baby students get confused between
paration and uh M uh micturation so that
is something else that is expulsion of
urine this is paration now listen very
carefully first male produces sperm
female produces egg right because of the
insemination procedure here what happens
is
insemination in
semination sperms will be introduced
into the female reproductive tract then
there will be formation of a zygote
right there will be formation of a
zygote now zygote will develop zygote
will develop now this development is 40
weeks you can say this is also 9 months
both are
sa 9 months or 40
weeks clear this is a gation period what
do we call this word gestation
period gestation
period and because of the various
hormone action there will be partur
isn't it clear everyone one second guys
one second something is not visible to
me
second one
second
okay okay now it everything is
fine okay so this is human reproduction
spermatogenesis U Genesis so what all
things are there let's have a look there
is a
gametogenesis now suppose this question
comes in your paper as a one marker
right Define gametogenesis how will you
remind gametogenesis that is the
formation of
gamuts formation of
gametes see now the biggest mistake
which everyone does I have written over
here formation of gamut the reason is
here I am teaching you right and it's a
marathon session and you know I have to
teach everything so I cannot give a full
definition so what are you going to
write because it will be a theory paper
you'll be judged on the basis of what
you have written on that paper you're
going to write down gametogenesis it is
the process of formation of a gamut
complete sentence you have to write down
if you will write like this you will not
get complete marks okay now formation of
gamuts they are of two type when we talk
about female it is the U
Genesis and when we talk about a male it
is the spermato
Genesis
perat
Genesis clear now moving on to the next
is
insemination now insemination what is
insemination who is genital track
reproductive track yes same same same
someb now tell me tell me tell me tell
me insemination so insemination means
deposition
of you're going to again I'm saying
you're going to write the whole
definition deposition of
sperms
in female
reproductive
track clear female reproductive track
done done done buddies next is
fertilization that means Fusion
of
male
and
female
yamit next implantation very important
word what is implantation very nice good
buddies good job good job doing good now
next is implantation what is
implantation that means how can you
explain implantation implantation means
whenever we have a zygote zygote comes
to a stage which you will learn later on
that is a blastos so blastos engrave
itself into the uterine wall yes
attachment of blastos to the uterine
wall very nice good
job
attachment
of
plastoy
to uterine
wall blasty now you'll say ma'am what is
blastocyst BET blasty is what blastocyst
is one of the stages Whenever there is
an embryo development this implant
itself and whenever this implantation
occur in many female there is
implantation bleeding in many cases it's
not that visible in many cases it is
visible whenever there's an implantation
some blood comes out right so gestation
so what do you mean by gestation on
gestation how time period of development
of embryo in
uterus gestation
period
embryo
development
in
uterus right
partur
that means now you're going to write
down again I'm saying the full
definition giving
birth
to
fully
developed
fetus when the baby is fully developed
in that case we call this as a bation
one second buddies I have to switch on
the okay clear yes quick birth yes
pation okay D done hope these points are
clear now guys let's move on on to the
next one now buddies we are going to
start with one by one so first of all we
are going to start with the male
reproductive system right so let's start
with a male reproductive
system okay so let's
start mail
reproductive
system male reproductive system so first
of all we are going to discuss the male
reproductive
system clear so in the male reproductive
system you know there are various
structures present so along with the
various structures here are ducts some
accessory ducts yeah one second one
second Buddies
so what all things are part of male
reproductive
system first the
primary
reproductive organ
Le
whereas
accessory
structures in accessory structures we
are having
glands and
ducts
mom
definitely can't
focus okay okay okay
so ma'am definitely full cabus will be
covered in neat 50 days challenge yes
everything will be covered okay so here
we have is a primary reproductive organ
so what is the primary reproductive
organ in case of male what is that that
is the what is that that is the test
right so there is
tesus
along with that some other structures
are also there we will be discussing
some glands are present some glands are
like prostate gland is there there is a
semal vcle semal vcle and there is one
more gland which is a cers gland is
present there secretions they are
important for overall development of
gamuts yes now next one we are having is
the other structure okay now let's
start first we are going to start with
the test now testes are situated outside
the abdominal cavity within a pouch
which is termed as scrotum
right yes so testes are situated outside
the abdominal cavity testes they are
present in a sack now these sacks they
are termed as scotle
sack scotle sack
why they are present outside because
they maintain a temperature of a body
less than 2 to 2.5 de C which is
important for the process of sperm
development right now the scrotum helps
in maintaining the low temperature of
testes 2 to 2.5 de lower than the normal
internal temperature necessary for the
spermatogenesis now whenever a baby is
there whenever a male baby uh you know a
kid is there so in that case when a
child develops at the time of birth the
tesus they descend into the scrotum many
cases test they unable to descend into
the scrotum they remain inside in the
abdominal cavity that condition is
termed as
cryptorchidism that is that condition is
termed as cryptorchidism so with the
help of a surgical way so tesus will be
descended into the scrotum because when
tesus will remain inside the body in the
abdominal cavity there will be Pro there
will be you know the spermatogenesis
proper sperm formation will not be able
to occur right now in adult each test is
oval in shape each test is oval in shape
shape is oval now next is with a length
of around 4 to 5 so they are having the
length of around 4 to 5 cm see we are
just discussing important points because
it will be a theory paper so we have to
write down everything that is the reason
I am giving you all the points now width
is about 2 to 3 cm so their width is
around 2 to 3 cm with the help of cords
they are
attached with the help of the cords they
are attached so that I'm not discussing
here now the test is covered with a
dense covering here outermost covering
is quite dense so that is the reason so
they are having a different covering yes
inguinal Canal is there gobul is there
which helps in holding the test clear
now next is they're having a dense
covering around it now next is each
testes has about 250 compartment called
testicular lobules now let's understand
this let's understand this okay now here
can you see can you see this is a very
important diagram previous diagram again
I'm saying no need to remember but this
diagram is super important you have to
draw this diagram once in your notebook
why this is important because here
question can comes relate come related
to the duct like what kind of duct is
present what is the flow of a sperm from
where does it travel Etc and Etc now
let's start now if I talk about the
testes so this is how a test is I'm just
making a this a one one side one okay
okay this is outermost covering tuna
alenia is there in fact three layers are
there not mentioned your in your
ncrt C here 250 compartments are present
they have compartments like this just
like that of a kidney here also
testicular lobules are present what do
we call
this
testic lobules
see I'll show you everything I will show
you see here come here what we have
discussed so far each testes has
compartment termed as testicular lobules
how many 250 testicular lobules are
present how many
250 testicular lobules are
present now in testicular lobules
seminiferous tubules are present here
here tube like structure 2 to three
seminiferous Tu tube tube again I'm
saying what are I'm labeling
seminiferous
tubules sem
mineras tules here I'm writing tules are
present now these seminiferous tubules
are the places where there is sperm
synthesis okay now similarly over here
also it will be
present here also so it will be present
so they are present like
this they can be one they can be two or
they can be three now this point is
clear done now listen here very
carefully now another diagram which is
there in your ncrt is this and many
student that they get confused and they
say k ma'am this is a seminiferous Tibu
and what you are drawing is a
seminiferous tubules like a tube what is
the difference so this is actually
whenever you take a tube and whenever
you dissect it what you will get is the
round structure so what are these These
are the seminiferous tubules and in the
seminiferous tubules the sperms are
present in the various stages of
development sperms are present in
various stages of development done clear
everyone okay okay so let's start so
what comes after the seminiferous
tubules so in the seminiferous tubules
sperms formation occur isn't it clear
now from here the sperm enter into a
network of
tibule what is that come on tell
me what is that come on what's the name
of
that what's the name of
that come on tell me tell me R test is
absolutely right that is a r test T So
this I'm labeling as R
testis after that sperm goes into small
ducts which are termed as come on write
down the
name come on write down the name what is
that vas differentia yes so next comes
the vas
differentia so here
come the vas efferentia so this I'm
labeling as
Vasa
differentia now these things are not
clearly mentioned in this diagram but
again I'm saying you can see testic
lobules out of this testicular lobules
the r tesus comes out R testis say sperm
will go into the Vasa inferentia some
network of tubes you can see over here
then the sperm will enter into
epididymis so it is having a structure
like this epididymis epididymis is
present from the upper part of the test
to the lower part means it is the one
which spread on the One Direction of a
test this is termed as
epididymis clear epid diis the reason
why I'm having both these images on your
screen is I can you have to draw this
diagram but I'm explaining you
everything over here so that you can
have a clear comparison see now what
happens is now here now now the here the
sperm will enter all the way into the
another duct this duct is tered as vast
difference Vasa difference or vast
difference clear now can I explain you
some other
thing clear is this point clear now
listen very carefully there are many
cases where the vast difference is
absent so what do you think are they
able to produce their own baby can they
have their own baby if both the vast
difference is absent if both the vast
difference is
absent tell me tell me they can have
their own babies how so no no vast
difference can be abset that is is
termed as congenital bilateral absence
of vast difference that is cbavd
congenital bilateral absence of vast
difference and when there is absence of
vast difference they can have their own
babies also by with the help of a
surgical procedure sperm they take out
from the testicular lobules sperms will
be taken out and then the fertilization
they can do it externally that means
with the help of an IVF procedure they
can have their own babies right so this
yes this can also happen vast difference
can be absent so that means in the the
their body sperms are being synthesized
but they are not coming
out can clear now the vast difference
now come back to this diagram buddies
here testicular luse next is R testes
then vas differentia then the epididymis
see epididymis is like
this right it has three different part
no need to remember that because this is
not mentioned in the book now next we
are having is a vast difference can you
see this vast difference this is a vast
difference coming over here this is on
the one side another side also another
uh these are coming these are also the
same thing will happen on the another
side also now here what happens is guys
again I'm saying this diagram is
important and this diagram should be
there in your
notebook now here now first there are
different glands they will open over
here first gland name is a semal vcle
second is the prostate gland and third
is a bulbo ureal gland they have their
own
secretion clear now ultimately sperm
coming over here urine can also come
over here right are you getting this
point sperm travel all the way over here
all the way they will be having
secretion of a semal vcle the prostate
the bulbo ureal gland and what are their
secretion that I'll let you know now we
in case of male there is a common
opening common thing right because that
carries the urine coming from the
urinary Blader so they are having a
common thing which is termed as urra and
this is also termed as urinogenital
duct this is
urino
genital
duct urinogenital duct so it carries
urine also it carries a sperm also clear
now next one here what happens is now
sperm comes out this is termed as Ural
me like from here the sperms come out
here you will see the P penis is present
the covering is termed as a for skin the
swollen portion over here that is termed
as a gland
spenis done now now now now listen very
carefully now let's talk about the
glands right simultaneously we will be
discussing everything okay now first
thing is let's talk about the gland
first gland is prostate gland second
gland is a seminal vicle the next is the
bulbo ureal the cers gland now out of
all these three gland which of the
following is unpaired one very important
question what is that that is the
prostate is
unpaired prostate is unpaired rest semal
vicle bulbo urethal they are paired this
is
unpaired first thing you have to start
with a let's start with semal vcle this
is one pair present on both the sides
situated behind the urinary blader
provide secrete fructose prosta gland in
vitamin C citric acid and
ocol clear yes so this is the one now
fructose why fructose is important
fructose gives energy for the developing
sperm right so this is you know this is
a carbohydrate so this will provide the
energy prostag glands they will be
important for the motility later on they
are important for the motility which you
will learn I'll tell you how okay now
next thing is bulbo next let's talk
about the prostate because after semal
there will be position of a prostate it
is a chestn shape Chestnut shape
unpaired milky
appearance calcium ion it secrete
calcium ion protic enzyme citric acid
semal plasmine are there so you know the
whsh is because of that milky appearance
is because of the secretion by the
prostate gland which is
unpaired it is having citric acid it is
having the semal plasmine which makes it
thick you know whenever it comes out of
the body it becomes thick the reason is
because of the secretion of a prostrate
gland now next one is a bulbo ureal
gland the last one this is again one
pair it secrete mucus it helps in
lubrication palbo urethal another name
is cers gland everyone will learn this
okay clear everyone now let's move on
further
so right duct whilea part is done right
duct I have explained you now here now
let's talk about the tesus in detail so
this is a cross-section cross-section of
What Not testicular lobule this is a
cross-section of a semi iferous tibule
clear so this is a TS of
seminiferous
tibule seminiferous tubule so those
tubes you
remember 1 2 3 they can be pres they
will are present in testicular lules I'm
talking about those so here you will see
the sperms are present in various stages
of
development if you look at this diagram
you have your ncrt open if this diagram
is not clearly visible to you you can
open your ncrt in that you will see
outer cells are rounded in
shape and towards the center you will
find the sperms are present because
outer side the
spermatogonia are
present
spermogonia
SP atonia in the center sperms are
present spermatozoa are present so this
is how they develop from Outer to
Inner outer to Inner clear now again
this is an important diagram first
diagram was the male reproductive system
diagram here from male reproductive
system question can come related to the
gland where is this gland present is it
paired what are the secretion Etc and
Etc now from this topic question can
come transfer section of uh draw the
transfer section of sem tribute super
duper
important yes some tanu samak
everyone what is your next exam biolog
what is your next exam
buddies what's the name of your next
exam that's a physical education
exam what the for that the my students
they are always ready H isn't it
it so dedicate this dat to
biology
okay let's
start now let's do a quick reading of
the duct male accessory duct including
the r testes vasen idamis and the VAS
Defence okay clear now can you tell me
no it's not tough it will be easy don't
worry can you tell me the function of
epididymis here what is the function of
epididymis what is the function of aamus
who's going to tell
me what do you want me to repeat dream
doctor what should I
repeat yes it stores sperms other than
that it helps in providing the motility
also to the sperm before this sperms are
not motile motility they attain in the
epididymus okay now next one last line
what was the last line I just talked
about the this one buddy okay okay now
next is sanifer tubules of the re testes
open into vast differential theor test
everything is there why why notes are
there on your screen because it will be
a theory paper you will be writing
everything for this
paper now V differentia leave the tesus
open into epidemis located along with
the posterior surface of each tesus
epidemis lead to vast Defence that
Ascend to the abdominal Loop over the
urinary
bladder okay now
buddies everyone right down in comment
section the flow of sperm starting from
the sem feris tubules come on write down
in comment section sperm moves from
seminiferous tibule to dash two dash two
dash two dash everything right
now come
on this is for cbsc this is for your
board this is for come on write down
write down starting from the semer
tubule you have to start with the
seminiferous tubule like this semer
tubule very nice Raj sem to reest to
vast differentia very nice epidemis and
vast difference very nice and after that
vast difference the semal vcle will uh
flow will you know secretion will enter
then there will be ejaculatory duct
there will be prostate cers gland
ultimately into the urinogenital duct
and from the uh further it comes
out okay clear
very nice good job good job clear now
let's proceed
further this also we have done now let's
talk about the penis the penis is a male
external genitalia figure is given at
the back the madeup of special tissue
that helps in erection of penis to
facilitate the insemination the enlarged
end of penis is termed as glance penis
is covered by by lose fold of skin which
is termed as four skin done clear good
job good job Shan Monga yes to urra very
nice
okay now let's move on to the sperm
sperm so next topic now let's talk about
the sperm then I'll be talking about the
process of spermatogenesis microscopic
structure if I let's come back to this
diagram let's understand with the help
of this diagram okay again everyone you
have your notebook draw this diagram
draw the diagram structure of sperm here
okay f for say let's draw the diagram of
sperms in your notebook everyone start
drawing you are watching this session so
make a full advantage of it you were
revising everything and after that like
in between the session whenever I told
tell you guys that you have to draw a
diagram do that it will be a great help
for you because ultimately when you will
be drawing the diagram in your board
paper that will be like second time or
the third time time you're drawing so
you'll be able to draw within a very
less duration of time so here if I talk
about the sperm sperm is having
Following part first part is termed as
head second part is the neck then there
is a middle
piece middle
piece
middle
piece and ultimately there is a tail
what is this this is a tail
done head neck middle piece tail so if
you look at the body body is covered by
the plasma membrane the body is covered
by the plasma whole body is covered by
the plasma
membrane clear now next one is the
acrosome acrosome here acrosome acrosome
yes absolutely right acrosome is derived
from GGI
body there derived from GGY
body and this is the one which is filled
with acrosomal
enzyme acrosomal
enzyme right these acrosomal enzymes are
zalin
these acrosomal enzyme are
honas acrosomal enzyme are Corona
penetrating
enzyme
enzymes three
enzymes clear now next one after that
you will find the nucle cleus having the
chromosomal material here the chromosome
here they are having n n that means they
are
hloy they are
hloy right so in the head part you will
find the acrosome is there the nucleus
is there right then there is a neck neck
neck may you will find PC now this is
not pryanka chobra here you will find
here the proximal
Centrio
proximal
Centrio and
DC distal
cental cental is
there proximal cental and distal cental
from this Centrio the flagala
arise okay so next is a middle piece in
the middle piece you will find
mitochondria is there which is the
energy used for the swim and then there
is a tail which helps in the
movement Right movement of
sperm clear is this point
clear no no no no no head um the neck
mitochondria is not present in the
middle piece region this one region the
mitochondria the spiral shaped
mitochondria is
present clear clear
okay yes it is present in in the body
now moving on to the
next one
second
now
okay one second so yes moving on to the
next let's talk about spermatogenesis
let's complete the spermatogenesis you
want to complete the spermatogenesis
now okay so let's complete the
spermatogenesis right now here first of
all we will complete this spermato
Genesis so so what is a spermatogenesis
spermatogenesis is formation of
sperm formation of
sperm
from
sperm Mother
cell mother's cell or
spermatogonia
spermatogonia clear point clear now
there are listen here then I like
explain you the ncrt diagram now there
are
spermatogonia
spermatogonia now these spermatogonia
they are arranged in the periphery of
the sanus tubu clear done now here
spermatogonia lots of spermatogonia are
present right they undergo the process
of
mitosis they undergo the process of M
mitosis with the help of mitosis what
they form is primary
spite right spermatogonia are
2N so what will be the ploy of primary
come on write down in the comment
section come on come on yes that's an
equational division but write down in
the comment section by the time let me
drink water come
on
come
on if this is 2N what will be the pyy of
the primary spermato site 2N yes
absolutely right so this will also be 2N
done now this primary now what
the student do in the paper they make
this silly mistake key they start the
meosis in the spermatogonia no
spermatogonia first of all divide and
mature and what they form is primary
so primary will undergo
the process of meosis so meosis occurs
in two step meosis one and what they
form is secondary
secondary
spermato
site right secondary will be n
isn't it
yes or no yes this will be n now this
will undergo
the spermed
formation formatted now this is by the
meosis 2 everybody start writing the
reason is more you will write more it
will be helpful for you again I'm saying
buddies start write also simultaneously
it's it's a good revision thing for you
see when I was in class 12th I was not
having this opportunity of watching some
Marathon sessions some classes where
everything is there in a one shot but
you you guys are seriously very lucky
that you are getting everything it just
that you just have to sit and
study yes okay so spermatic so here
these are n and these will also be n now
one primary will form two
secondary spermato site will form to
will form the four secondary spermed
this is a reductional Division and this
is a equational division clear done now
these spermed they will
differentiate they will differentiate
and they will form the mature sperms
only differentiation is there so this
will also be n
differentiate per met Genesis formation
of sperm from a Meto from a mother cell
spermatogonia next is process process
sperms are formed now here the pro
formation of sperms from spermed this is
termed as
spermiogenesis what is this this is the
spermiogenesis
pero oh
oh
spermiogenesis okay so spermatogonia
primary secondary
spermatites and the sperm this is the
spermiogenesis and this is the
spermatogenesis now head of the sperms
they are present in the ctoi cells okay
I have to explain C cells also that is
also left I'll explain you
so head of
spur are associate ated
with C
cells and their
release is called as
permeation is termed as
permeation
clear everybody tell me tell me tell me
is this point clear any doubt to anyone
amongst please let me know come on come
on come on come
on come
on do it
fast
yes
come on come on come on spermatids to
spermatozoid spermiogenesis very nice
very nice
everyone okay now if this question comes
in your paper you have to draw this a
diagram this very nice neat and clean
diagram of flow chart in fact and you
have to explain everything
okay
okay okay now one more thing is left
let's discuss
this so one more thing CI cells CI cells
are present
here which provide nutritions to
nutrition to the developing
sperms here outside in the interstitial
space some special cells are present
which are termed as interstitial cells
or ladc cells these are the leic
cells or
interal
cells and what is the function of leic
cells LC cells secret hormone
testosterone what does it secrete
testosterone and testosterone is the one
which is responsible for the secondary
sexual characteristics in case of
male
clear now now let's talk about this
diagram but say let's complete this
where is the diagram here so this is a
closer view of the seminiferous tibule
you will see here spermatogonia are
present which form the primary
which form the secondary and
ultimately spermatites are formed and in
the Lum in the center they form the
sperms you will see sometimes their head
they are associated with the CI cells
their head is associated with CI cells
because they gain nutrition from there
and their release is termed as
spermiation so three words we have
learned so far spermatogenesis
spermiogenesis and spermiation so you
should know the difference between these
three okay now let's talk about hormonal
control
hormonal control of of
spermatogenesis now this topic you all
must have done in the class 11th also
the chemical coordination and
integration chapter same thing I am
repeating here nothing new the same
thing I'm repeating here here let's
start with the
hypothalamus yes hypothalamus is a
structure which controls the
spermatogenesis hypothalamus secretes a
hormone which is
GnRH this GNR goes to anterior
pitutary and anterior pituitary in this
respect they secrete to hormone one is
the
FSH and second one is LH FS is I'm
writing the full form for you buddies
follicular stimul
ating
stimulating
hormone and this is leutinizing
hormone leutinizing hormon see it will
be too important for you for for the
board examinations again I'm saying FSH
now FSH will go to the ctoi
cell C holy cells it will produce
factors produce
factors important for
spermatogenesis detail not
given which are important for the
spermatogenesis so ultimately they
provide nutrient
right now next one is a lutenizing
hormone lutenizing hormone they help in
providing the what do they do they
secrete
Androgen they secrete
Androgen and androgen is the
testosterone clear this is the
then why are you studying here you can
go you can go in case you don't want to
study then go so no one is telling you
to come here uh see we are not forcing
you question hypop yes zamb that was a
hypop fisal bort circulation
right okay clear is this point clear to
all my
bodies basically ctoi cells produce
factor which are important for the sper
Genesis and specifically buddies if I
say specifically for the spermiogenesis
is May the main process
spermiogenesis spermiogenesis
spermiogenesis may it plays a role
specifically if I say clear so
spermiogenesis spermed so sperm
conversion conversion mate is
important okay okay then done done now
let's move towards the female
reproductive system
female reproductive system okay so let's
start with the female reproductive
system buddies any doubt till now yes or
no come on let me
know
female
reproductive
system
so in female reproductive system what
all structures are present come on tell
me female reproductive system the
ovaries are there female accessory gland
cervix
ovaries female accessory
glands accessory glands are
there there is
cervix cervix is also a part and other
than that the external
genitalia
external
genitalia these are the different part
clear ovaries you all know the are the
these are the one which are responsible
for the formation of egg first let's
start with this external genitalia first
I'll be explaining you the external
genitalia then we will be proceeding
further right so external
genitalia now external genitalia the
diagram here the things are not clear
properly so here different parts are
there let's have a look
so
okay so there is a kushy structure here
which is termed as the mo
pubis Kush structure is the mo pubis
which is covered with here full of it's
a Kush fatty next one is I'm labeling it
here that is the labia
maora
maora inner lip is termed as liia
minora minora
clear
here just like that of a gland spanis
females they have
clitoris Cloris is there right here
ureal
meatus one second
second urra opening urethal meatus is
there and vaginal oriface is
there so this is the
ureal
oriface and this is the
vaginal
opening is
present clear so so there is a mons
pubis again I'm explaining there is a
mons pubis there is a labia majora laia
minora urethal ores vaginal opening they
are present clear now now
now around the urra par Ural glands are
present some glands some glands right
around urra par ureal glands are
present par
ureal
gland par ureal gland their secretion
helps in neutralizing the
urine other than that what's the name of
the next gland Bartholin gland some very
nice next is Bartholin gland
present barolin gland and Bartholin
gland is present
around
vaginal
opening opening and what does it secrete
it secrete
mucus what does it secrete it secrete
mucus which helps in
lubrication okay clear is this point
clear to all of you
buddies right now ovaries are there
cervix you know cervix is a part next is
a external genitalia mons fubis there is
a Mia maora inside labia manora mon
pubis Majora minora at the junction
there is a clutoris center paroral gland
there is a vaginal opening here there
will be anal opening look at this
diagram here also things are given but
not properly here you will see labia
maora is given labia maora and minora
they are labeled over here vaginal ores
is given urra is also opening over here
there's a pubic symphisis urinary
bladder Addus there will be rectum
cervix Etc
right okay yes yes what's the doubt
what's the doubt tell me doubt doubt
down don't spam guys don't spam okay so
what's the doubt what what doubt you
have okay now let's proceed by the time
uh let's proceed towards this right if
you have any doubt you can write down in
the comment
section
now this is a diagrammatic
representation this is not an external
genitalia this is a diagrammatic
representation of the female
reproductive system internally right so
here different structures are present
the first structure is the uterus guys
can you see this
structure this structure this is a
uterus what is this this is a uterus is
it labeled
here I'll label this this is our
uterus here the three layers of uterus
are present
uh no bet it's an English Channel so I
have to lubric uh mucus is the one which
helps in the lubrication basically so
that easy insemination can occur
okay okay okay who asked this question
bike bike
Walla okay so let's start so here uterus
three coverings are present first
covering is the outermost covering which
is a perimeter perimetrium which is
present towards the outer side then in
the middle there is a myometrium
myometrium is made up of smooth
muscles smooth muscles and these smooth
muscles rigorous contraction helps in
Easy birth of a baby okay then the inner
layer which is endometrium which show
periodic shedding the inner layer shed
it always shed monthly shedding what
does it show it show monthly
shedding and because of the monthly
shedding we experience female experience
menal
cycle clear cyclic changes is because of
the endometrium right so this is so they
form a cavity over here cavity this is a
uterine cavity labeled here this is a
uterine fundus part the thicker part is
a fundus part so two hand like structure
as I've discussed earlier some ducts are
also present some hand-like structure
they arise and these hand like structure
they are the fallopian tube fallopian
tube one fallopian tube
two right now these fallopian tube has
different part it is having isus ampula
and infantum three different part is
there okay now who's going to tell me
where does the fertilization occur very
important question fertilization occur
in
fertilization occur
dash where does fertilization occur
ampula very nice just me it occurs in
ampula it occurs in
ampula right ampul at this region so
here you will see here ovaries are
attached ovaries are not directly
attached to the uterine wall many
student when they make this diagram they
say ma'am they attached over here no
they're not attached to the uterine wall
in fact they are here in the cavity
they're present in the cavity right so
here ovaries they release egg eggs will
be captured by infundibulum infundibulum
is having a finger like finger like
projections if you will see it's the
finger like projections are like this
and if you will see here there is a hole
present hole hole hole which is tered as
ampula so egg once it is released from
the ovary they will come over here in
this osteum so once they will enter over
here they will reach at the ampula
region they will wait for the ampula
they will wait for the sperm to come if
copulation will occur sperm will be
released into the vagina from sperm
sperm Will Travel Travel Travel it will
come here in the ampula and in the
ampula it will undergo the
fertilization right so where does the
fertilization occur correct answer is it
occurs in the ampula region where does
it occur in the ampula region done
clear that's a ampula
ampula ampula it's a pipe now so it has
to enter in a pipe how will they enter
into the
pipe yes
why all not population because the egg
has a life egg is released in a
particular time period it is released
that I'll show you menal cycle K day 14
per it is released and add the day 14 to
it is having a life of around 24 hours
so 24 hours May it will die so that is
the reason all copulation will not lead
to
pregnancy is that it clear egg will be
released once in a month at the day 14
it will be viable just for 24
hours
okay now next is here let's proceed
towards the towards here now these two
points are clear now here you will see
the cervix is present cervix this was
the part cervix is present cervix and
vagina is present cervix and vagina they
form a cervical Canal so they form a
canal over here through which the sperm
enter
okay clear
everyone okay
so let's proceed now let's look at the
structure of a ovary where is the
structure of a ovary
yeah ovary ovary how many ovaries do we
have we have two ovaries in case of
birds there is a single
ovary right in case of bird there is a
single ovary why because that's an
adaptation to flight here in case of
female two ovaries are present now if
you will look over here here a thin
membrane thin covering is present thin
covering germal epithelium thin covering
is present thin covering is present
clear here the eggs are present in
various stages of development yes the
shape is alond like here the blood
vessel nerve Supply everything is there
which provide nutrition
here you will find the follicles are
there in various stages of development
primary follicle will be present the
secondary follicle will be present
secondary there will be tery follicles
also there will be gfriend that means
graffian follicle also so graffian
follicle is a follicle which is a mature
follicle which is a mature follicle
through which the eggs they will release
Here the mature egg they will come out
whatever is Left Behind that is termed
as this see what they releases a egg a
worm they releases whatever is Left
Behind that is termed as Corpus lutetium
which is a temporary endocrine gland
what is this this is a
temporary endocrine
gland temporary endocrine gland clear
what does it secrete it secrete
progesterone and and
estrogen clear now here this yellow
color body is converted into a white
body which is termed as Corpus
alons Corpus
alons which is just like a scar white
body clear so eggs are there in the
various stages of development we have a
pair of
ovaries clear now here one more thing is
labeled that is a entrum entrum is the
empty space so they have this cavity
which is the entrum so as they develop
tery follicle start showing the
formation of antrum which is completely
formed when we talk about the graffian
follicle
clear okay
now let's move
further okay okay okay now buddies let's
do
the this one the U Genesis okay let's do
U Genesis F say
Okay
gametogenesis o
Genesis o Genesis so just like that of a
sperm spermatogenesis where there's a
formation of sperm o Genesis this is the
formation
of of
egg or
oite
from egg Mother
cell egg Mother cell egg Mother cell
which is also to termed as
ugia or
gonium clear oite now o Genesis is a
stepbystep procedure but this is not a
continuous process this is a
discontinuous
process discontinous
process when does it start it start
before
birth before birth spermatogenesis
starts at puberty and it never ends but
here if I talk about
this it
end at
menus now what do you mean by menus
menus is a play you know at particular
time period when there is no menal cycle
when menal cycle stops it stops
clear
now it occurs in two different step
one let's start here first I'll be
explaining you this this I'll explain
you this CH one which is there in your
ncrt then I'll explain you the follicles
also
see millions of ugia now whatever I'm
discussing here that is related to your
uh ncrt millions of ugia are present
when a child is there in the mother's
swm how many
ugia
clear ugona how many millions they are
present when I was four month gestation
when just imagine when my mother was
pregnant and I was there in her wom and
I was just 4 month old that gestation
while four-month-old not after birth
whilea four four-month-old in that
particular time in my ovaries the eggs
that means ugia were present in
millions and they keep on dividing they
keep on dividing right they keep on
dividing clear now listen very carefully
so they divide and what they form is
primary oite when during the fetal life
during the fetal
life yes
clear so primary oite right so it this
primary oite the primary oite now this
primary oite start dividing right it
undergo the miotic division completed
prior to
ovulation ugas are there ugas they will
divide and they will form the primary
oite now this primary oite they will
start dividing they will start dividing
and prior to the
ovulation they stop see I I'll explain
you here so let's start
right so let's start with U
Genesis
ugona what are these
honia ugia billions of ugas are there
now these ugia they divide by
mitosis and they differentiate
also differentiate
also clear
and what do they form
is primary
oite primary
oite clear now they will divide further
C they will start the process of meosis
one meosis one they will start the
earlier it was mitosis now it is meosis
now now meosis
one it will halt at it will start meosis
but it will halt it will stop and where
does it stop it stop at prophase right
it will stop at proas
one
tipline
stage
right so this is before birth this is
primary oite only these are what these
are the primary oite so they have
started they have started the procedure
but they have not divided so again we
call it as primary
oite we call it as primary
oite
right clear
now now in this primary usid stage now
what happens is this is a fetal life now
what will happen this is again I'm
writing this is the fetal life when
child is there in mother's
form up now what will happen baby
born baby I was born baby born
one right these primary oite they will
remain like
this primary oite will remain like this
they are already
arrested at proac
one arrested at proas one ditin
stage clear right they will wait
they will not complete the division they
will wait so at menal
cycle menal cycle the first menal cycle
that is a mear now this primary oite
will divide now let's have a look
primary
oite
oite this was the primary oite now this
Prim primary oite will divide and it
will form the secondary
oite it will form the secondary
oite right as they divide the division
is unequal division is unequal the
another one is very small the smaller
one is termed as the first polar
body first polar body
body what is this this is a first polar
body which is of no use because this is
a result of a unequal division now what
happens is secondary oite will this one
will divide further because it is a
result here they have completed the
meosis
one here they have completed the meosis
one meosis one is done so definitely it
will be n okay it will be 2 N now they
will divide further now before dividing
again listen very carefully it will
remain like this but it it will start
meosis
to meosis 2 but again it will arrest
at metaphase
2 metaphase 2 not metaphase 1 metaphase
2 so this is a process first arrest was
here when the child was there in the
mother's swarm ditin stage prophase one
second arrest was at this stage that is
at the metaphase any doubt okay okay
I'll repeat
this generative cells vegetative cells
here we are discussing zoology and no
not
botney yeah tell me I'll repeat this
again see now do not focus here first
listen to me listen to me I'm giving you
my example when I was was there in my
mother's SW right I was just a four
month four month gestation period honia
millions of ugas they start developing
now these ugia which was there in my
ovaries they start dividing they form
the primary oite how do the primary oite
formation occur by a mitosis now this
primary oite started the process of
meosis they started so so when does me
when does o Genesis start o Genesis
start when a child is there in the
mother's womb so proace one started so
as the proace one started it is halted
at the ditin stage okay so now they are
halted at a ditin stage now these
primary oite stuck in the Diplo te stage
they will remain like this and I was
born I was 12 to 13 years old they
remain like this their number reduces
your ncrt says their number reduces that
is termed as arraia the death of these
oite some oite die out of those Millions
only 60 to 80,000 per OV was there in
the
ovary was there in each ovary right so
60 to 80,000 number now primary oite
they were waiting so when I got my first
menal cycle listen very carefully I'm
taking my example example so when I
started my first menal cycle I was
around 13 years old I don't remember now
so that primary oite started the process
of meosis
1 it was already started but now they
have completed they completed the
process of meosis one whenever there is
a first division one cell formed the two
cell this here this was a unequal
division unequal division means one was
a smaller cells other was a bigger cell
smaller cell is termed as a first polar
body the bigger cell is a secondary oite
now secondary oite will start dividing
secondary oite will form the will
undergo the meosis 2 but meosis 2 as he
had started the meosis 2 it will be
stuck it will complete the prophase 2
but it will be stuck at the metaphase
2 now what will happen I'll come here
and I'll show
you now this is the mature this is this
is a secondary oite now our graffian
follicle will release that secondary
oite secondary oite arrested at
metaphase 2 it is released now come
here as it is
released it will come over here from the
infundibulum it will wait for the wait
at the Ula waiting at the Ula population
happened firms are here now sperms they
will travel travel they will come to the
ampula now sperms will be responsible
for conversion of the secondary oite
into oted or aom that means it will
complete the meosis 2 so when sperm will
come then only it will complete the
meosis 2 otherwise it will not complete
the meosis
to
White done no meal cycle is the toughest
no it's not tough It's easiest I'll show
you how
done everyone clear so this point is
clear CH tell me if it is clear yes or
no come
on say tell me then we will start the
next topic that is a menal cycle come
on done
everyone come on come on come on JY say
come on tell
me
Al be S white done great great great
good job buddy simultaneously hope
you're writing also AB how many diagrams
you have done you have drawn the diagram
of uh sperm in your
notebook duct the male male diagram hope
that is also clear we have drawn the
structure of OV that is also again I'm
saying this chapter is important now
you'll say ma'am every chapter is
important but this chapter for five
markers they are important okay that is
the reason this is the first chapter I
am starting and this will take some time
to complete because I am trying to
explain you everything CH suppose a
topic comes related to U Genesis now how
you're going to write down first you're
going to Define what is a u Genesis when
does it start when does it end and then
then you will make a chart you're not
going to write the stories you're going
to make the chart that one cell divided
into two second cell third cell uh
everything and everything okay
clear no it will not be a great it will
not be a issue I have given you a
solution this is how you can draw okay
do not focus here okay from now onwards
buddies if during the revision you will
not focus on these two diagram you will
focus on this diagram everything I've
explained you all the points and this
one this one see o Genesis o Genesis is
done that's it I've explained you
everything okay okay my dear buddies yes
no come on tell me ad come on Sleeping
Beauties get
up
yes enjoying enjoying everyone if yes
then F say give me thumbs up in the
comment section if you are enjoying this
session see almost more than 50% of this
chapter we have already done the one of
the biggest chapter of class
12th done so drink some water and then
we will start with the menal cycle
everybody drink some water good good
good thank you so
much very nice good good good
okay very nice very nice very
nice okay so let's start buddies let's
start with the with the with the with
the topic number two which is a menal
cycle
okay menal
cycle now suppose a question comes in
your paper Define menstral cycle write
down the different stages of menstral
cycle CH what is a menal cycle menal
cycle occurs in two different ways now
you'll be like n n this definition we
haven't studied ma'am in school we have
another definition I'll explain you in a
beautiful way there is one process which
occur in
OV there is a process which occur in the
uterus this is the first time I am 100%
sure like my way uh this is a f like you
will be teaching this is very complete
different I am teaching you because if
you know the concept then you can write
anything in your your paper okay and
once you're done with this paper please
let me know ma'am yes paper was good
fine yes everything went well or not to
discuss so ovary so first thing ovary so
ovary during the menal cycle what
happens in OV is the development of
follicle there is development of
follicle follicle
follicles means primary
follicle develop into the secondary one
secondary develop into the ter one ter
develop into a girlfriend that is a
graffian follicle okay which is
happening in this chart H continuous
talking continuous students they are
talking to each other very wrong moving
on to the next is the uterus in the
uterus also some changes occur there
there is
formation and
breakdown
and
of
endometrium right and these processes
whatever I have mentioned over here
these processes they are under
the influence
of
hormones now you'll be like ma'am no
this definition we haven't studied in
school now I'll tell you see special
cycle it is that cycle which occurs in
uterus as well as
OV this is that cycle where there is
development of follicle in ovary and
formation and breakdown of endometrium
in the
uterus the two parallel process occurs
and both these process they are under
the control of various
hormone
done characteristic
feature
so when does it start when do cycle
start when it is at puberty
12 to 14 years of age nowadays it is
starting early because of adulteration
because of the food which we
eat
right now start is termed as
minarch and when does it
stop it stop when a female is almost 50
years of age
50 55 48 like this this is termed as
menopause it start it ends like this
mean Arch and menop pass done
okay we are teaching we are studying
menal cycle okay now listen very
carefully very very very very very very
very very
carefully there are various stages of of
meal cycle in the ovary there are
various step first step
is molecular
phas second step is the ovulation
phase third step is the luteal phase
total duration of this is almost 28
days right 1 to 13 14 day 13 days
follicular development occur 14th
day this occur 15 to 28
today the Lal face
occur right point
clear now let's talk about uterus uterus
may be there are stages now you'll say
yes we haven't talked about it a uterus
way there is the first phase that is the
menstrual flow
phase flow phase second phase is the
proliferative
phase proliferative
phase third phase is the last one that
is the secretory
phase these are the faces which occur in
uterus these are the faces which occur
in the ovary clearly I'm explaining you
everything clear now the first thing
see at the day one at the day one let's
start with the day
one day one GNR comes from the
hypothalamus GNR goes
to better better better take now GN R
gnrs come and DNR goes to the anterior
pitutary interior pitutary release the
hormone the follicular stimulating
hormone the first step I'm first let's
do with respect to this okay now FSH
level
increases FSH level increases as there
is increase in the FSH level follicles
develop molecular stimulating hormone
lead to the release of lead to the
formation of follicles primary secondary
tertiary
Gul graan follicle clear primary
secondary tertiary and the graphion
follicles FSH comes FSH comes from
anterior pit do not forget now this
comes from anterior pit right FSH
increases FSH increases because
progesterone
reduces and estrogen
reduces how that I'll tell you later on
okay now as the follicles
develop as the follicles develop
developing follicles releases estrogen
so they will release estrogen
okay they will release
estrogen see you will see here estrogen
level
increases developing follicle releases
estrogen Point Clear
this is the development because of this
estrogen level increases now what
happens next is here as FSH increases
over here LH also increases now LH
increases developing follicles FSH
increases now L increases LH increases
estrogen also increases because of
sudden increase in estrogen L surge
occur what happens is LH surge see what
is this l
search LH surch because of LH searge the
graphion follicle kicks out the
secondary oite and secondary oite is
that oite which is stuck at the
metaphase
2 okay which is stuck at the metaphase 2
now how to write in a paper that also
I'll explain you L surge now what we
have is L surge occur now we have is
ovulation occur ovulation is this one
ovulation done done done let's have a
look follicular phase occur because of
the increased level of
FSH developing follicle will release
estrogen estrogen increases due to which
LH also increases L surge occur due to
which the ovulation occur at the day 14
everyone is everything
clear now the next thing next thing next
thing next thing what happens is
whatever is left behind bachaa
everything which is Left Behind is
termed as Corpus
litium and as I have discussed earlier
the Corpus lium is a temporary endocrine
gland what does it release progesterone
and estrogen it releases progesteron and
estrogen so this releases progesterone
and
estrogen clear next phase is termed as
lual phase Lal means Corpus litium is
there see now what is happening
progesterone level increases this first
there is a downfall in the estrogen then
estrogen level also increases because of
the Corpus lithium done this point is
clear everyone now Corpus litium it is
termed as a temporary because it has a
life now the Corpus lithium will be
coent gone we will get the Corpus aluts
this is a wide
scar Corpus elans white
body
Albus this point this point is
clear right this point is is clear now
let's move on to the uterus let's look
at the steps that happens in the uterus
so in the uterus different stages are
there okay the first is the menal flow
phase first the menal flow phase
initially for some period of time 3 to 5
days menal flow occurs menual flow means
release of blood from a female track it
comes out tissues also comes out why
does it occur occur because of the
downfall of progesterone and downfall of
estrogen the Menses of the menual flow
occur clear now as the follicles develop
as the follicle develop they releases
estrogen as estrogen comes estrogen
helps in the formation of the
endometrium this is endometrium so
endometrium formation occur they will
form the endometrium yes this is served
as proliferative phase proliferative
phase done now endometrium develops
develops develops Corpus litium start
releasing the progesterone now this will
be responsible for the glandular nature
of the endometrium so glandular nature
of endometrium is because of the Corpus
litium that is the
progesterone
okay tell me buddies clear
right so two different process occur
simultaneously hormones they are same
okay so how you're going to write down
in a paper you are going to write down
first first you will explain what is a
menual cycle menal cycle is a cyclic
changes that occurs in ovaries and
uterus in the ovaries there is
development of follicle and the
ovulation and in the uterus there is a
formation and breakdown of endometrium
everything is under the influence of
hormone Mo I am explaining you
everything okay now what are the
different step first step is a menual
flow phase where are you going to
explain in this way menual flow phase
second is proliferative Phase third one
is a secret secrety means secretive
nature so that means the glandular
nature of endometrium here it is
folicular ovulation and the Lal this is
how if you learn everything you will not
forget now tell me whether this topic is
easy easiest or
difficult I don't know by which way you
have studied but this is super easy I'm
telling you this is super super duper
easy
topic Lal is secretary phase yes the
last phase Lal is secretary absolutely
right both are I'm not see do not be
confused some lual phase is a corpus
lium formation that occur OV May and
here security they are parallel faces I
won't say they were they're not
interchangeable
words they're not interchangeable words
here these faces secretary face occur
here here right they are the parel faces
do not be confused okay tell
me any doubt anyone everyone come on
come on come
on okay Lal phase duration Lal phase 15
to 28 days
okay CH let's start
okay now let's talk about the next topic
which is the which is the memory
glands then yes the next cycle begins
yes because Corpus luum has a life the
progesterone level reduces estrogen
level reduces when these two go now the
endometrium will
fall
okay okie doie clear everyone CH come on
any doubt otherwise we have to start
with the next topic which is the menal
cycle can we
start huh okay so memory glands are what
memory glands you all know these are the
paired structures develop in case of
female glandular tissue
and the size
varies as per the fat
content okay now next is glandular
tissue of each breast is divided into 15
to 20 memory
lobes memory loes are there up everybody
please Focus here otion can come in any
form so you should know what are the
memory Loops so these are are I am
drawing are the memory
Loops
memory memory Lo clear is this point
clear now they contain cluster of cells
this may you will find the cluster of
cells are
present look at this look at this
aluli where there is milk
formation what is this
Alvi Alvi May what happens milk
formation so there is a milk formation
right this Alvi they open into the
memory
tubules memory tubules tubules Alvi
memory tubules so alv these are not the
lungs alali these are something else
okay present in breast alali opening
into memory tibul everything it is clear
now now look at here different tubules
they join and they form a
common memory
duct what they form is the memory
duct hope this point is clear
right now this memory duct further lot
of memory duct they open now let's come
to thisp diagram okay guys can you see
here
alviz can you see here alviz actually
different memory loes are there and in
memory loes I I'll I'll make this
diagram better
okay the lobes memory lobes memory lobes
May alval are there alali they open into
duct you will see here duct ducts are
there can you see duct now these ducts
they are coming from each and every Alvi
duct has a swollen swollen swollen area
which is termed as ampula ampula ampula
opens into a lactiferous duct ultimately
the milk come out comes out through the
N blackish portion brownish portion that
is termed as arola so what is the flow
of uh milk so it is like
alvioli Alvi right Alvi see yeah we have
drawn the structure Alvi Alvi right
Alvi then into memory
tubules memory
tibul memory tubules to memory
duct duct now duct has a swollen portion
so it is like
Alvi these are
the
tibes tibule one more tibule
coming one more tibule
coming they will form duct the these are
the duct now this duct they swell
up which is the ampula memory
ampula ultimately opens into the
lactiferous
duct lactiferous do and then open to
outside right this is the open to
outside through the
nipple development of breath breast is
because of
astrogenesis an
because of this happens now the next
thing
is if I talk about the formation of
milk formation of milk in the breast is
because of
prolactine now the next one next one is
the ejection of milk
ejection of milk so ejection of milk is
because of
oxytocin why milk is important milk is
important for the overall development of
a baby first milk is termed as
chrum
postr po now next is which is rich in IG
antibod
IG
IG it is
colostrum right cestrum rich in
IG done
here okay now let's proceed see how
beautifully we are completing our notes
of also you will get these notes and it
will be a great help for you buddies in
your uh revision which you have to
do now after some
time okay yes okay now let's start the
process of fertilization fertilization
very important where does fertilization
occur fertilization occur in the ampula
region in the ampula there is uh sperm
and the Egg they both of them they
fertilize together okay
okay
first
steps
or
fertilizer steps of
fertilization first step of
fertilization
is
insemination first there will be
insemination right deposition of sperm
into the female
reproductive then
then see what happens is whenever the
sperms they are deposited into the
female reproductive tract sperm has to
move and the for the movement of sperm
they undergo certain reaction that is
termed as
capacity
of
sperms right this is important for the
movement of
SP I'll not explain this in DET that is
it is not given in your of
SP mement of
sperms that sperms will move and how
will the sperm see actually what happens
is the the head of the sperm there will
be some albumins attached those albines
they will be released which sperm they
will be able to move towards the egg
clear so that is important for the
movement of sperm now the next step is
the acrosomal
reaction BM will reach to the egg there
will be acrosomal reaction acrosomal
reaction mean what happens
is around the
egg there will be some layers
present no I'll
explain
okay some enzymes are released
enzymes these enzymes are yalu
Ron there will be
Corona penetrating
enzyme penetrating
penetra and
zonal zal H on days is the C now what
happens in whenever eggs come over here
first enzyme is hyaluron days you will
see here the follicular cells cells
around the egg they are termed as
follicular cells what are these buddies
can you see these are the follicular
cells here now these follicular cells
they will be attached by the hialuronic
acid hyaluronic you remember you
attended the previous session talked
about some you know outside the cell the
intercellular spaces ground substances
present which we call it as hialuronic
acid so here also honic acid is present
so whenever sperm comes first thing is
they release hyaluronidase which helps
in the digestion of hyaluronic acid
present around the follicular cells done
so next layer you can see here that is a
cells of Corona radiator Corona radiat
cells are there Corona radiator cells
will be digested by the corona
penetrating enzyme done here third thing
is Zona license internal to this there
is a Zona peluca layer Zona peluca layer
Zona peluca layer will be digested by
the Zona lysin now what will happen
happen yes now what will happen let's
have a look acrosomal enzyme now what
will happen see Next
Step prevention of
polyspermy
first entry
of
sperm new
nucleus and
proximal
Centrio in
egg see what happens is first
insemination will occur then there will
be capacit capacitation in the cervix
region then there will be acrosomal
reaction every layer will be digested
then there will be entry of the sperm
nule and the proximal cental proximal
cental will be important for the first
division of the egg now what will happen
next is the prevention of
polyspermy of polyspermy it will not
allow further sperm to enter as one
sperm is
entered now this is termed as cortical
reaction not given in detail cortical
reaction cortical reaction clear now
what will
happen egg
completes meosis
2 egg completes meosis
2 completes meosis 2 how does egg
complete meosis 2 because sperm comes
with anas promoting factors and it will
degenerate the metaphase promoting
Factor now this is the one yes
definitely cortical reaction or acros
reaction is different cortical reaction
may I'll explain you what happens is in
the perit line space can you see this
not for the cbsc in fact because one
student is asking that is a reason I'm
explaining there will be cortical
granules they will accumulate over here
it's like a gate around the egg which
will not allow further egg further
sperms to enter if one sperm is entered
there will be cortical reaction poly
sperm because we don't want any other
sperm to enter already one nucleus is
entered one in fact nucleus and along
with that the PC that is a proximal
cental is also entered clear
done
okay
okay H yes
okay H let's proceed further now let's
talk about this now what happens is this
stage now there will be fertilization
after the fertilization there will be
formation of a zygote sorry this is a
egg this is a
egg this one indicates the
fertilization this is a
fertilization fertilization this is the
C see here what happens is after the
zygote there's a one cell State see if
you'll see here there's an egg release
over here fertilization fertilization
occurs here which region is this this is
a ampula
region
ampula okay now there will be two cell
stage and they are migrating as well as
they are developing there will be two
cell stage there will be four cell stage
there will be 8 to 16 cell stage there
will be 8 to 16 cell stage now 8 to 16
cell stage is termed as
morula this is termed as morula solid
mass of boss of ball of cell that is a
morula malur like now this will further
develop into this structure which will
further develop into this structure
which is termed as blastocyst so what is
a blastocyst blastocyst has an outermost
layer which is termed as
trophoblast trophoblast or tropo
aoom troa
Toom which along with the uterine wve it
will form the placenta and it is having
the ICM Inner Cell
Mass
Inner Cell Mass so Inner Cell mass will
form the baby whole baby formation will
be because of the ICM trophoblast of the
tropho acto will form the
this clear yes so here there will be C
development like this okay so here we
call this as a cleavage we don't call
this as mitosis the reason we call do
not call this as mitosis because here if
you'll see the SI size of the zygote and
size of a two cells eight cell stage the
size is same only the cell divides right
cell do not increase in
size okay buddies now trophoblast again
I'm saying a with the uterine wall they
form the
placenta so so this is how the baby look
like so tropho blast or the tropo ooom
they form the placenta along with the
uterus wall uterus wall so they form the
placental V placental V and the uterine
uh tissues they are like this they are
closely attached to each other this is
the structure which is attached to the
baby which is termed as a umblical cord
this is a baby or the embryo developed
there is a yok saac which is not that
developed not required this is a cavity
of the uterus this is a plug of mucus
mucus plug is attached here and the baby
is there in the amniotic fluid okay
amniotic fluid
so now guys let's move on to the
development in human being after 1 month
of pregnancy first structure which is
formed is dgd that is the heart you know
whenever a female expecting female if
she is a 1 month one month 15 days
pregnant she goes to a doctor doctor
first check the pregnancy with the help
of a HCG either by a blood or the urine
test if HCG that is a human cionic
gonadotropin only secreted at the time
of pregnancy is there in the mother's
blood or the mother's urine that means
it she is positive for the she's having
a positive pregnancy now that is one
test now the second test is ultrasound
which female should go through to know
whether the implantation is at the
proper position or not so the first test
that another test that is I told you
that is a ultrasound it gives it in that
case Doctor listen to the heart sound
also so first structure which is formed
is the heart that is even at the end of
one month when a fe one month baby one
month baby when she got to know her
first menal cycle is not there because
after 28 days only she will get to know
whether she is pregnant or not in case
she missed the menal cycle so that means
chances that she can be a she can be
pregnant so that is the reason she goes
to a doctor the first sign of growing
fetus may be noticed by listening to the
heart sound carefully through the
stethoscope with the help of stethoscope
also with the help of a ultrasound
machine also they can be
H
okay by the end of the second month
pregnancy fetus develops Limbs and the
digits all these the data whatever I'm
discussing is there in your ncrt so
please focus at the end of 12 weeks that
is a first trimester three trimesters
are there first trimester I am seeing
most of the organ formation occur for
example limbs external organs are welld
developed first movement fifth month at
the end of the first movement at the end
of fifth month movement appearance of
here on the head is usually seen so
movement fifth month if I talk about the
heart sound heart sound at the end of
first month
now by the end of 24th week at the end
of second trimester body is covered with
a fine here eyelid separate eyelashes
formation occur at the end of the N9
month of pregnancy the fetus is fully
developed and it is ready for the
delivery okay progesterone is an
hormone progesterone is in hormone
female May what's the
issue
okay okay now let's talk about the
partur so signal for
partur
for
partur comes from fully
developed fully
developed
fetus plus
placenta
okay now at the 40th week near the 40th
week the baby you know the baby has a
less space and baby is developing so
they will create a signal along with the
placenta due to which it lead to mild
uterine
contraction female will feel mild
uterine contraction because of some
prostag
glanding
contractions signal will go to the
hypothalamus hypothalamus with the help
of posterior
pitutary posterior
pitutary will release a hormone which is
oxy
oxytocin which is the one which is
responsible for strong uterine
contraction uterine
contraction then more and more uterine
contraction will occur see here what
happens is positive reflex if a baby is
there and baby is trying to push a baby
is producing some mild contraction
oxytocin will come and oxytocin will
cause stronger contraction of the uterus
right initially the uterus May though
these uh you know the contraction
duration will be more with time the
contraction duration becomes less right
and because of the strong uterine
contraction baby birth occurs that is a
pation that is
the partur pation will occur right baby
will be
born zygote is deployed then male and
female gamuts are hloy some of they
heid they're
heid okay now let's talk about lactation
lactation
lactation as I've
discussed formation of
milk formation of milk is because
of the
prolactin prolactin where does prolactin
comes prolactins comes from anterior
pitutary it comes from anterior pitutary
where does it come it comes from
anterior pitu clear so because of this
there will be formation of milk now as
the baby suckles so at the time of
delivery let's say at the time of
delivery there will be
oxytocin oxytocin come and oxytocin
because of oxytocin there will be
ejection of
milk ejection
of milk now more a baby suckles more a
baby suck it goes to a signal goes to a
brain there will be more formation of
milk just after a baby is
born in many cases female doesn't get
the milk in that case she's always
recommended by doctors that she should
uh let she should let the child suckle
more a baby sucks the milk try to suck
the milk more the you know the
hypothalamus uh sorry the anterior pit
they start releasing the
prolactin right
clear okay buies clear
yes yes anterior pitutary this prolactin
comes from anterior
pitutary
okay one
[Music]
second so with this buddies we have
completed one chapter chapter which is
the human reproduction see everything
each and every topic we have completed
now we have to move towards the next
chapter Which chapter do you want to
start now reproductive Health can we CH
start the chapter reproductive Health
now which chapter you want to start come
on stop spamming
guys come
on okay come on stop spamming and tell
me which chapter you want to
start human reproductive Health can we
start the reproductive Health
chapter okay so are you done with the
first chapter is that
clear yes good good kitu oh biot bi
technology will do in the end so so many
students they said ke n n we'll not do
questions here because it's not uh it's
not s it's not s here because it will be
a theory paper everything I have
discussed the detail Theory and
everything but uh it will not be easy
for me to discuss question also
okay
okay some let's
start reproductive Health reproductive
Health
okay so what do we mean by reproductive
Health reproductive Health like overall
health means we should be fit not only
uh you know physically there is an
absence of disease but we should say ke
we should be mentally fit we should be
socially fit that is important similarly
wh gave the definition that reproductive
Health means one should be fit the
reproductive organ should work properly
in fact there should not be any kind of
of social any kind of mental pressure
should be there right so you all know
there was a time when maternal mortality
rate was really very high there was a
time when infant mortality rate was very
high can you tell me the
reason can you tell me the reason why
why because of the poor development
because of the because earlier the
female used to give birth at home only
untrained profession
like people were there who used to take
care of mother and when a child is born
that is a new life for a female also in
the term key the female will definitely
undergo lot of changes in her body
she'll be facing lot of blood uh loss
from the body yes there was a lack of
awareness very nice just me so that was
one of the reason now reproductive
Health right so with time with time we
developed so many things I would like to
discuss one
thing so let's start from the beginning
leave
it
reproductive
Health reproductive health so according
to wh that is a world Health
Organization reproductive Health
means needs to be fit the person needs
to be
fit
physically
socially what else what do you think the
person should be fit by what way
right
mentally right this is what the def
definition of wh was clear so in that
respect because of the poor you know
awareness there was no awareness there
was awareness was very
less was very less so government of
India was first country who started rep
reproductive and Child Health Care
Program when was it started come on let
me know in the comment section
reproductive and
Child healthc
Care
Program started reproductive and Child
Health Care
Program come on tell me
yes when was it started come on tell me
1951 1951 it was started okay yes prabas
absolutely right good so in the 1951 we
started that is just to create awareness
and how was awareness created awareness
was created with the use of the print
media with the help of a social media uh
with the help of radio Etc awareness was
created people were told about the STD
people were told about the contraceptive
pills people were told about the hygiene
how they can maintain hygiene of a
private part people were uh told
regarding the uh you know the the child
care when a baby is born how to take
care of that kid when a mother uh
delivers a baby how to take care of that
mother that's it so with time what we
faced was the population explosion that
was one of the reason because of the
huge population here not only um in the
world in fact in India also you know the
you know there's a biggest problem today
we have is a good
population many time we feel that as
compared to other
countries this comes in everyone mind ke
why we are not that U you know we don't
have those things which are there in
other countries the one of the reason is
population it's really very difficult to
manage this much population here
we see when we have a small population
it's easy to manage but when we have a
huge population it's very difficult to
manage so one of the reason was the
population explosion the world
population which was around 2 billion
this is just a data given in ncrt so
that data I'm reading here 2 billion
1900 May rocketed to 6 billion by 2000 a
similar Trend was observed in India to
our population which was approximately
350 million at the time of our
independence were close to 1 billion
Mark by 2000 and cross 1 billion in May
to 2,000 that means every sixth person
in the world is Indian right it is
actually a big issue but if you'll
thinking n why we are why do if you go
to any foreign country I recently
visited one uh
country everything was so fine
everything was so uh uh you know
organized it's not because the
population is less and actually I
realized here it's we always blame our
government that government is not doing
this government is not doing that but
seriously buddies one should really
think about it to manage this much
population it's very a difficult uh
thing H yes so literacy rate is also uh
not that
good okay let's start so reason for
population exp population explosion the
rapid decline in the death rate with
time you know hospitals came and the
Serv Services also came and there was a
decline in the birth rate uh sorry the
death rate maternal mortality rate also
reduced and the infant mortality reduce
was all was also reduced contribution of
reproductive and child health program
was marginal effects of population
explosion poverty unemployment energy
crisis overcrowding in cities and
increasing in the crime rate these are
some very uh basic thing the
reproductive and Child Health Care
Program here came up with an idea that
we should aware people regarding this
hamar
they promote small families here in
India if you have a small families
government always promote those in fact
uh there are uh many school here who
give preference to those families those
kid here in um I'll tell you I'm from
Delhi and recently I was uh reading of a
newspaper where the couple they are
struggling to get their child admission
in the nursery itself is a big deal here
I don't know about your state it's a big
deal here the one of the reason
is uh number of you know the population
is really very high another thing is
here in India uh here in Delhi I don't
know about the other
state U if you have a single child so
and that to a girl
child in fact the schools they give
priority they give some points it's
there right so governments takes lot of
step to control the population One Step
which they started was
right second thing is one child Norm so
they always promote a one child Norm
statutory raising of the marriageable
age of a female to 18 years and the male
to 21 years though still in many state
early marriages are there incentive
given to couple having the small
families even in India those who are
having a small families and they are
having a girl child government provide
some fund right U there is one yena I'm
aware of it suya Sami yena so where you
have to deposit some amount in your
child account of girl child account and
government also provide that similarly
there is another yogena by which uh
government provide books uh you know the
all the expenses related to education to
a girl child so so many things
government has started they're working
definitely in this direction because
ultimately the first thing is we have to
control the population with this
population definitely we cannot grow we
cannot we cannot see development
now another uh awareness which was
created in our country was related to
the contraceptive people were not aware
of the contraceptive so contraceptive
particular part is there in your cabus
and that to in detail because you being
biology student so you should know about
it okay so these are the contraceptives
so what are these contraceptive
contraceptives are the birth control
methods birth control methods
do you know which is the prevalent which
is the most mostly people U which
contraceptive method people use a lot
here in
India can you tell me what's that that's
a copper tea that's a copper tea yes
that's a intrauterine devices not the
barrier method no not the that is the
intrauterine devices here in India but
if I talk because here people men's they
have this mentality that they do not
want to use any
barrier yes but in outside if I talk
about the outside India they use uh you
know the barrier method such as condoms
Etc so what are these what are these
contraceptive devices contraceptives are
the birth control methods there are
various birth control methods uh
available in the market that I'll be
discussing in detail now regulation of
contraception by preventive methods or
devices to limit the number of Offspring
is termed as a birth
control now
what are the different characteristic of
a ideal contraceptive it should be user
friendly easily available nor or least
side effect no way to interfere with the
sexual drive okay so now let's talk
about the methods of contraception so
first let's talk about the natural
method natural method of
contraception so in natural method of
contraception we have a is lactational
amoria
lactational
amoria lactational amoria means when a
female is
lecta Right female is
lecta when a female
lactating
then there is no menstrual cycle when
there is no menstrual cycle so there
will be no
ovulation no ovulation that means in
this particular time if if if
insemination occur then there will be no
pregnancy though this particular method
is you know it's not the case it only
occur in it is only possible when a
female is highly lactating because when
prolactin level is high that particular
time no menal cycle no menal flow occur
because it suppress the gonard dropin
FSH and LH right no menal cycle why
because of increase in the prolactine
hormone and due to which there is
decrease in the FSH and
LH so in this particular time period
there is no meal cycle this is
lactational
amoria now moving on to the next
periodic
abstinence periodic abstinence you all
know ovulation occur
at ovulation occur at when does
ovulation occur ovulation occur at day
14 right clear now egg has a life of
egg has a life of around
24 24 hours right so it means no
quas quitus means
intercourse
from
day 11 to
17 If egg is there in female body so
that means there will be pregnancy if if
no insemination at that time when there
is egg in the body so there will not be
any pregnancy periodic abstinence
periodic periodic it's also termed as
calendar method this is also termed
as calendar
method by looking at the calendar yes
earlier people used to track their uh
menal cycle by this way now the third
one is quite a
interruptus quas
interruptus qu us interrupt us that
means do
not
deposit
FBS in female reproductive tract so that
means during quitus female abstain the
male abstain him abstain himself and do
not deposit the sperm in the female
reproductive track in fact the deposit
outside
okay okay guys clear yes good job after
day 16 17 this is a tentative time now
out of this method if I talk about the
natural method so natural method C there
is no side effect because nothing we are
using from outside no side effect but
this is not very
effective not very effective so one one
people are doing is people they just
study their own body isn't it what do
are the people doing they are just
studying their own body isn't it are
they using anything from outside no
right so this is a natural
method or this is also termed as that is
the TR traditional method right now
moving on to the next is barrier
method these are something which use
from outside barrier
method barrier method barrier that means
some barrier is there that means we have
a
barrier and because of this barrier the
female
gamut
is not able to meet the male
gamet that barrier we have created
clear okay now here let's talk about the
different barrier method first let's
talk about for the male for the male we
have just one that is
condom which is made up of latex or
rubber right
which is disposable and this prevent the
STD also right and now this one next one
for the
female for the female we have is
following we have is
diaphragm we have is
walls and we have a cervical caps
right these are the one which female
uses they are condom it's like this they
have a
cap something like this and this is how
a diaphragm look like which female use
on the cervix uh so that the sperm
should not enter yes this protuct from
the STD so these are the barrier method
the condom diaphragm and the w s right
cervical caps they see they resembles
diaphragm only and they are smaller and
more
rigid and this uh one should prescribe
this by the doctor because it depends
upon the female Sur size the cervix size
because one has to place over the cervix
sometime this is also used with the
spermicidal Creeps in the jelly so
whenever sperm will come in come in
contact with it the sperms they will die
yes they are disposable they canot be
they cannot be reused
again right but out of this if I say uh
the vaults are the one which can be used
again so these are
reusable these are the
reusable they can be reused again female
she can use this again after washing she
can easily use this
again
okay okay similarly in the female also
female case may see in the female case
also the female condoms are
available female condoms are also there
and female condoms are available by the
trade name of
fidom
fidom done now let's move on to the next
one that is
the intrauterine
devices intra uterine
devices intrauterine devices
iuds so name itself indicate these are
the iods which one person has to use in
their uterus so what is that one person
that definitely that's a female so that
is used by
female used by female and she plac it it
in the uterus so there are three type of
intra uterine devices first one is
non-medicated nonmedicated
iuds come on write down in comment
section the different type of
non-medicated
iuds yes and what are their function
that also I'll let you know second one
is a copper releasing
IUD copper releasing
iuds
and third one is a hormone releasing
IUD hormone releasing
iuds non-medicated
iuds
yes yes yes yes so come on write down so
these are the non-medicated one is a
lippes loop very nice
buddies lippes Loop good job copper
releasing is the copper
T copper
7 multiload
375 multiload
375 the next one is a hormone releasing
is
LNG
20 and
prester okay
come on is this point
clear right now let's talk about their
function first first is written here
lippes Loop
sperm
phagocytosis whenever sperm will come in
contact with it sperm will die because
of
this sperm FOC yosis this will cause
sperm
phagocytosis
phagocytosis and decrease fertilizing
capacity of
SPM decrease fertilizing capacity of
sperm
of sperms now the next One progesta S
and this this um this this will release
definitely some hormone and because they
release a hormone so they
make uh
cervix in hostile for
sperm
for
sperm and
unsuitable for
implantation for
implantation unsuitable for
implantation right
yes okay everyone
D come
on so now moving on to the next let's
talk about the oral
contraceptive
oral
contraceptives oral contraceptives so
oral contraceptives they are of further
type so contra contraceptives let's say
contraceptive then I'll be talking about
the oral contraceptive and injectables
so oral contraceptive may we are having
is the
pills right we have is the pills pills
are the basically they're made up of the
progesterone and
estrogen so progest synthetic
progesterone and estrogen due to which
it will not allow
ovulation no
ovulation
and
implantation it will not allow ovulation
and implantation to
occur there will not be ovulation there
will not be implantation there are mini
pill and combined pill also available in
the market have you heard of the sahal
sah are a type of it here no sorry not
sah so here um uh what's the name of
that uh I
forgot what's the name of this medicine
I just forgot yeah sah is nonsteroidal
yes there some of that right but uh it
just skipped from my
mind it is available in the market oh I
forgot CH uh so there will be no
ovulation and no implantation so um we
have to take this someone has to take
medicine
daily daily for 21
days for 21 days so one one has to take
daily then the they do not have to take
then after that what will happen as the
progesterone estrogen level will come
down as they will come down there will
be menstral cycle right so it was very
difficult starting from
a ah
no what was the name of that medicine
are tell me now n n lto that is not done
principal and processes n there's not an
i pill there not an i pill I pill is
emergency contraceptive
s croman is in
sah s croman just just skipped from my
mind H whatever it was so uh 21 days say
we have to take this daily uh within the
first 5 days one has to start right
pills are there similarly one more
medicine is available in the market by
the name of
sahili so we are so proud Sahel is
developed by
cdri Central drug Research
Institute drug Research
Institute cdri which is in
lakau central drug Research Institute
which is in lakau and uh this is having
this so they uh it's like once in a week
so one one person has to take this once
in
week right this is
nonsteroidal this is
nonsteroidal they they have sent chroman
as you have told me so let's discuss it
has sent
chroman
sent chroman and sent chroman it blocks
the estrogen
receptor the
estrogen
receptor it blocks the
astrogenesis basic mechanism is they
will inhibit ovulation and they will
inhibit the implantation this is a oral
contraceptive similarly injectables are
also available in the
market injectables are also there so
injectables they are also U you know
dimpa there are many available in the
market and these injectables they are in
the form of injection which contain the
progesterone and estrogen so that's it
okay so with this guys we have completed
the methods of
contraception intra utrine devices
natural barrier Etc now we have to talk
about the surgical
methods
surgical
methods the surgical methods are also
there first is the tubic
toi and second is the
vasectomy
homy and
vasectomy homy done by
female so they
doctors
cut and
tie fallopian
tube Fallopian
tubes on both
sides
so so right these are the Fallopian
tubes so doctors they just make a cut
over here and they just tie this again
so they'll tie this again so uh it's
like they Block it's like a road and
it's that road where the sperm one side
the sperm is coming and another side the
egg is coming so they will block that
road and ultimately what will happen
there will not be any uh pregnancy now
tell me and many students they come to
me and they say ma'am in this case there
will not be menal Cy ccle what do you
think come
on will they be menal cycle in this yes
there will be menal cycle definitely why
not there will be menal cycle only gamut
cut yes cut the fallopian tube but here
menal cycle will be there female will
undergo the same menal cycle vasectomy
vasectomy we do in case of male where
cut and tie
the
vas
Defence on both
sides both sides right these two methods
surgical methods they are
non-reversible
nonreversible these are non-reversible
method one cannot reverse this this is
non-reversible both these methods okay
once done that means done done done done
that means there will be no
pregnancy
okay AA guys now I have to discuss this
amasis also with you what is amnios
nasis yes gamut formation will
occur a now you'll say in vask toi those
who have done the vask to me uh so that
means in that case there will not be uh
sper formation there will be some sperm
formation only the sperm will not come
out so either a in a couple either a
female can go through the tubectomy or a
male can go through the vasectomy right
in case they do not
want do not want any baby amnios
synthases amniocentesis so amniocentesis
is the procedure by which any
chromosomal disability if it is there in
the baby that can be detected easily
that can be detected right how in this
case what happens is when a child child
is there in the mother's swarm right 18
to 20 week gestation
at 18
to 20
weeks of
gestation right suppose in a family in a
family chances key there are diseases or
some gen genetic diseases are there in a
family and couple wants to know whether
their child will be suffering from that
thing or not so in that case they can go
for amniocentesis so amasis is a
procedure which is done under the
ultrasound machine so this is ultrasound
uh you know image so this is how it is
done and with the help of a syringe as
you can see this is a baby and with the
help of a
syringe some fluid amniotic fluid will
be taken out right gestation 16 to 18 um
like this week it depends like how much
how enough amount of of amniotic fluid
should be there in the mother's SW right
so 4 to 6 mL of amniotic
fluid amniotic fluid we take
out we take out with the help of a
ultrasound transducer and by using a
syinge either the syringe can be trans
abdominal or can be trans vaginal
right right now the fluid will be taken
out and then what will happen the
embryo
cells will be
collected will be
collected now what we'll do we will
check for the
chromosomal
abnormalities
we will check for chromosomal any
genetic
disorder or any genetic
disorders we just can be analyzed they
can be easily analyzed that's it we will
culture those cells and easily we can
check out right now what all disease can
we carry hemophilia yes hemophilia can
be analyzed isn't it Down syndrome prom
of chomosome under 21 can be detected
Turner syndrome if it is there the
client client felter syndrome whether it
is there in the baby or not can be
detected and when in normal cases me
people do not go for
amasis why people do not go for amasis
the reason is it's not required but when
they feel in the pedigree this disease
is there and they do not want that their
child should have this dis disease in
that case they can go for an entosis now
we are very sharp we are very
intelligent now we are using this
amniocentesis procedure for the sex
determination because chromosomes are
there so with the help of chromosome
analysis we can get to know whether XX
is there or XY is there XY is there Oho
by it's a boy very nice if it is a
female then female fitti side right so
that is illegal now AMD syntaxis for
checking the sex is illegal in our
country but in other countries it is
legal yes is that so so see it's a
medical procedure used in prenatal
diagnosis of chromosome amoli fetal
infection and sex determination but for
sex determination it is not used okay so
this is ultrasound transducer baby
Position will be checked and with the
help of a fine nle the amniotic fluid
will be taken out this is a trans
abdominal like this a trans vaginal can
also be
done yes we cannot detect the Clift
pallet oh yes okay okay okay let's move
on next now whates let's move on to the
next topic which is
the medical termination of
pregnancy female f female is there in
mother's SW now what will people do
people will go for a female feticide in
our country not here everywhere but in
some states the sex ratio is badly
affected number of female to that of
male is really very very very less why
because they feel now why that you all
know people feel female is a burden
female will this will that Etc and Etc
okay so people can go for a uh so MTP
here in India is
legalized medical termination of
pregnancy or abortion in India is
legalized this is not legalized for this
reason we have more uh people we have
the population is really very very high
it is for the other reason right so MTP
was not M MTP is not a method of
contraception again I'm saying okay
intentional or voluntary termination of
pregnancy is called medical termination
of pregnancy medical termination of
pregnancy is also termed as abortion
these are the lines from your ncrt okay
mtps are used to get rid of unwanted
pregnancies for example in case of rape
right in case people want to do not want
a baby so in that case they can go for
an MTP pregnancy which could be harmful
fatal to mother and the fetus or both
suppose in the suppose um you know
ectopic pregnancy is there can anyone
tell me what is ectopic
pregnancy that will be uh in the next
session the bota session that will be
tomorrow so we will teach this chapter
CH come on tell me what is ectopic
pregnancy come on what is ectopic
pregnancy come on tell me come on come
on when a baby is in fallopian tube when
baby is anywhere but not in uterus
anywhere but not in uterus so that is
termed as ectopic pregnancy yes
pregnancy anywhere in other than uterus
that is termed as ectopic pregnancy not
only in fop
okay so in that case what will happen
why why did I tell you ke U after
getting a positive test on that strip
one should go for ultrasound the reason
is to get to know whe whether ectopic
pregnancy is there or not if ectopic
pregnancy is this this is fatal for a
mother as well as baby in that case one
has to go through the MTP they have to
abort that baby now mtps are safe up to
12 weeks the first trimester of the of
the baby we have legalized MTP in 1971
reproductive and child healthare program
was started in
1951 MTP is legalized in India here it
was legalized in
1971 40 to 55 million mtps are done in
year throughout world which is 1/5th of
the total pregnancy when one uh you know
first trimester is there there will be
one medical practitioner and that
medical practitioner will be uh with the
help of various methods there are
various methods like diretion and cute
rages U introduction of prostag glin or
by the surgical procedur depending upon
at which stage the baby is one can go
for an MTP so that is always that will
be prescribed by doctor only and one
should not again I'm saying I'm saying
this on public
platform no one should buy these MTB
drugs directly from a medical store
without prescription no guys it's really
harmful and it can be fatal to a mother
okay now significance it helps in
getting rid of unwanted pregnancy such
pregnancies which can be harmful and
this is significant role in decreasing
the human population though it is not
made for decreasing the population in
many cases what doctors do is Doctor
cuts the baby within the uterus into
small small pieces and then with the
help of a vacuum they take out each and
every part so that is also one of the
part if this could have been a normal
session I would have explained you the
different type also but it's okay though
it's not a part but it's very good to
study these also okay now it is being
misused to abort even the normal female
fetus female feticide majority are
performed illegally by unqualified quack
which can be fatal it raise emotional
ethical religious and social
issues okay guys now we have to move
towards the next topic which is the
STD right now let's start the next topic
which is the STD okay so guys let's
start
STD what are STDs STDs are the sexually
transmitted
disease
sexually
transmitted diseases
sexually transmitted diseases are also
termed as veneral
diseases most of the most of these
diseases there is most of the diseases
the reproductive tract is being affected
so it is also termed as pelvic
inflammatory
diseases
P inflammatory
diseases sexually transmitted diseases
vendal diseases pelvic inflammatory
diseases this is also termed as
reproductive tract
infection
reproductive
track
infection these are the different
names sexually transmitted diseases
veneral diseases pelvic inflammatory
diseases reproductive tract infections
RTI clear so how does it spread it you
know we all know about HIV right we all
know about HIV in around 1981 this first
case came and this first came uh so so
I'll tell you a story in 1981 so so
there were group of people so those
group of people they were uh uh you they
were taking some intravenous drugs so it
was like some party was going on and one
one of them he was taking that drug and
with that same syringe other also they
started sharing it after some time it
was realized all of them they were
getting the Toxoplasma infection they
were getting the tuberculosis they were
getting other infections also uh so many
people they came to this idea because
they were into drugs they they used to
take drugs that is the reason their
immune system is low with time doctors
they did deep study in this and they
realized it is because of the HIV HIV is
that virus which spread through the
sexual it spread uh it's an STD which
spread through the sexual contact and it
also it doesn't mean that it only spread
through the sexual contact it spread
through the other ways also and because
they were taking the same nles so with
that it's spread to one person to
another it was really very U the you
know it's you know the HIV today we do
not have any cure for HIV isn't it we
can only increase the life of a person
but today cure is not possible but these
STDs not only spread through a sexual
contact they spread through other
contact also sharing the needles or the
surgical instrument contaminated with
the infective blood suppose you go to a
dentist and vess to everyone all doctors
they follow this suppose the instruments
they are not clear are not uh you know
properly washed in that case the chances
that yes it can spread so all the
surgical instrument should be uh
properly sterilized transfusion of
contaminated blood suppose one person is
suffering from any sexually STD it can
spread from one person to another okay
now next is STDs can also be transmitted
from an infected mother to fetus if a
mother is suffering baby can also suffer
fetus disease which are transmitted
through the sexual intercourse with the
infected person are called sexually
transmitt diseases venal diseases or
reproductive tract infection but all are
not reproductive tra infection for
example in case of AIDS HIV May
reproductive track infection doesn't
occur examples are goria ceris genital
herpes genital warts hepatitis AIDS
clamidia are sexually transmitted
diseases do you want to know the ctive
agent name it's not there in cabus but
still I'm telling you yes placenta say
spread now gonor is neria gonor
bacterial disease syphilis the tripona
palum genital herpes herpes simplex
virus human Poma virus hepatitis virus
uh HIV clamidia romaus these are the
diseases out of this which one is
non-curable which one is non-curable
come on tell me genital herpes
non-curable hepatitis non-curable and
AIDS is non-curable rest all are curable
so what are the different uh symptoms
basically the discharge from the uh you
know the reproductive tract discharge
can be a liquid discharge or discharge
can be cheesy discharge foul smell
coming out some wats are there some
blood is coming out unusual blood is
coming out no syphilis is curable but
when it migrate tery stage but when it
migrate to the brain neuros syphilis it
is non curable so at initial stages all
these all diseases except the three
which I've told you they are
curable okay okay buddies okay buddy
buddies now how can this is treated
avoid sex with the unknown person and
any point of time again I'm saying on a
public platform it's also this chapter
is there in your cabus to create
awareness one of the reason is guys at
any point of time you feel that you are
facing some problem in the reproductive
track anything if it it is relate it's
outside some discharge is there please
feel free to contact to your doctors you
should go to them you should discuss
with them you should discuss with your
friends you can take your friends also
to the doctor you can discuss with your
parents also so they can be a your good
good guide so do not uh hide this in
fact share this because ultimately after
some time disease uh cure becomes
difficult yes clear okay so avoid sex
with known person or the multiple person
condoms condoms are the only barrier
method by which only method of
contraception will prevent the STDs if
early symptoms like eching fluid
discharge slide pain swelling occur
genital region one must consult a doctor
again I'm saying yes okay yes my future
biologist if left untreated can lead to
pelvic inflammatory diseases abortion
still birth ectopic pregnancy es
infertility even cancer of a
reproductive tract okay yes buddi
clear
okay now now let's move on to the next
topic assisted reproductive technology
so with that we will be able to complete
this chapter
also yes three hours two chapters done
ectopic pregnancy Pras ectopic one
second ectopic pregnancy means ectopic
pregnancy that pregnancy where there is
implantation other than
uterus okay now I'm talking about
this okay so just give me a water water
break let's take a break for 2 minutes
everyone drink some water everybody you
know now water is important so drink
some
water
someone is saying ma'am coffee per you
you can come here and you can
join he Shahid you can come here and you
can
join by I'm continuously speaking from
last 3 hours have some
heart okay so good
good get more than get more than 70
marks in the class 12th and let's have a
coffee together isn't
it t let's
start it's hot outside you must drink
cool yes it's really very hot
outside so you guys are from which
place
I mean to say which state which
city oh biar Patna oh wow Shahid I'm
also from Delhi
Maharashtra oh
good Gujarat oh oh very
nice Kota oh very nice Ranchi New Delhi
very nice Rohit I'm also from New
Delhi
he
aabad Punjab very
nice
Punjab rit in in sometime Rohit will
give uh his address
also Rohit do not share your address
here no unti in that case enough amount
of amniotic fluid is not there so it's
very difficult at an earlier stage one
can go for cionic Willa sampling
CVS cionic V sampling may we take out at
the 10 to 12 week if early detection we
want then in that case is cionic Villa
sampling great let's start let's start
this
topic let's
start let's start this topic assisted
reproductive technology assisted
reproductive technology is the WAN it's
like it's like a thing which is
important for those who suffer from
infertility
infertility infertility means unable to
reproduce unable to
reproduce even
after even after 2
years of
unprotected
Fus right that is
infertility now this infertility a tell
me they are different they different a
tell me infertility infertility tell me
one thing uh what is the m couple me in
majority couple here uh what's the major
infertility occurs in male or female
what do you
think major reason for infertility is
male M normally 60% in male it there an
infertility 40% female May infertility
yes sterility is the one which cannot be
cured infertility can be cured there are
various things like in the case of
female so I'll discuss here it's not
there in cabus but still discuss female
May what can happen is female May there
can be the uh you know the some fibroids
are there in the uterus there are
chances key there's a tuberculosis of
Fallopian tube Fallopian tubes are
blocked so many reasons are there
menstrual cycle is not occurring
properly there there are reasons in male
there can be Aus spermia zeros sperm uh
sperm motility is not there the sperm
shape is not proper or there is no sperm
in the semon so many reasons are there
right in that case one can go for
assisted reproductive Technologies the
art techniques
right so let's discuss
a
r
assisted
reproductive
techno
logies assisted reproductive
Technologies are those Technologies
which are actually ban for those couple
uh who are suffering from infertility
specifically
uh either in male or female right in
this case one word that comes in
everyone's mind is the test tube
baby test tube
baby but this word test tube baby itself
is a misn noral so let's start let's
start discussing so here in assisted
reproductive technology from a female
body we take out
egg right from a male we take out
sperm
sperm what we do we collect
them we collect them then we fertilize
in
lab fertilize in laboratory condition
right when we fertilize them in
laboratory condition then we
implant the
blastocyst in
uterus this is what we call test tube
baby up female say we collected egg male
say we collected sperm we fertilized
them in lab and then we transplant it
back into the female body this we call
it as as testu
baby right this we call it as test tube
baby now tell me anywhere did I use the
word test tube no right but that is the
reason this word is a misn noral test
tube word is used because they are the
babies who are produced in the lab so
they are like a normal babies only
they're not something different they are
not like aliens they are normal babies
only so this is the overall procedure so
I'll explain tasa this procedure in
detail because nowadays every third to
fourth person couple they are suffering
from MDES because of the late marriages
because of the poor hygiene practices
and the most important reason is the
adulteration the food which we take so
from the female egg is collected how can
we collect the egg so it is like
normally a female produces one egg in a
month by continuous injection of FSH
follicular stimulating hormone not only
one follicle in fact 28 29 follicles
develop in female 28 29 follicle and
every day whenever she takes injection
female Co the the doctors they actually
look uh they keep a close eye on
her ovaries like how many eggs they are
developing right ultimately at the
retrieval day they retrieve egg from a
female right many times they are able to
get seven 8 9 10 eggs many times they
can get a one or two
egg from the male the sperms they are
collected right there are various ways
if female is you know if male is fine B
is not suffering from anything in that
case there is there are normal ways of
collecting sperms which you all know but
when sperms are not there in the semon
what sperms are there in the test is by
Tisa there are various methods by a
vacuum aspiration or other methods
surgical methods the sperms they are
being taken out from the testest sperms
will be collected now what will happen
egg and sperm they will
be they will be allowed to meet they
will be allowed to fertilize so for the
fertilization we use use one procedure
which is
ixie that is intracytoplasmic sperm
injection intra
cytoplasmic sperm injection so it is
like we hold a
egg we hold a egg and we give a
injection of
a sperm like this intracytoplasmic sperm
injection then we when then we prepare a
blastocyst in the lab and then we
implant this into the baby sorry mother
BB CH now let's talk about the different
type of
Arts right assisted reproductive
technology so assisted reproductive
Technologies they are of various type
first is in
Vivo
fertilization
in Vivo
fertilization and second thing is
invitro
fertilization in Vivo fertilization and
invo
fertilization right Ino fertilization
that means these are the methods by
which
fertilization we do in the body of
female
in female
body Fertilization in female body and
today I'll giving you all the cheats
also so
first gift first method is gift gift who
likes gift who likes gift girls like
gift girls like to gift right so gift is
done in case of female in case of female
who are not able to produce egg so this
is
done in female who cannot produce
egg
cannot produce
eggs those who are not able to produce
egg we give them gift so what is a gift
yeah write down the full form of gift in
the comment section write down the full
form of gift
gamet
intra
fallopian
transfer clear gift right now in that
case what do we do we
collect egg eggs from
donor
right then those who want to be a mother
we transfer the in fact doctor transfer
the
egg in fallopian
tube who fallopian tube the mother
fallopian tube Who Wants To Be A Mother
so this is a gift gift is for the female
done in female who cannot produce eggs
right now the next procedure this is the
first one let's talk about the next one
that is the artificial
insemination
or
intra uterine
IUI insemination
now suppose now this is done in case of
a female or sorry a male whose sperm
count is less right in that case we
collect sperm from female sperm for male
and then we extract good sperm healthy
sperm M motile sperm into the female
body right so
here BS
collected
from
male then
artificially
introduced in
female at
ovulation
time ovulation
time now this is done also in that case
when we need a sperm donor when we need
a sperm Doner yeah this is gift so here
in fertilization is happening where is
fertilization see egg is there in
fallopian tube egg is there so
Fertilization in fallopian tube sperm we
are introducing here right so this is
also artificial examination now let's
talk about the invivo
fertilization invitro fertilization so
in invitro fertilization first we are
having is gift sorry
zift zft so what is zift
zygote
intra
fallopian
transfer zygote intrafallopian transfer
zygote intrafallopian transfer so here
what do we we do is we take egg from
female right from female we collect egg
right clear we from the male we collect
sperms
collected then fertilize we will get a
zygote and zygote we will transfer to
uterus
sorry fallopian
tube
fallopian
tube right here we are transferring the
zygote here what is there fertilization
is occuring in the lab initro initro
means Fertilization in the
lab okay
clear y you guys talk a lot I don't know
what do you eat so next
one now next is what is the next one
zygote is done Embryo
transfer Embryo
transfer ET right
or intra uterine transfer iut should I
write the full
form
intra
uterine
transfer
intrauterine transfer okay now
intrauterine transfer May what do we do
see we take again female say egg egg
retrieval male say we will collect
sperms we will fertilize them in the lab
we will get a
zygote and zygote say we will make a
embryo more than eight cell stage
eight cell
stage we will transfer this into the
uterus of female May transfer yes that
is the reason so here we will transfer
this into the fallopian tube zygote or
up to 8 cell
stage up to 8 cell stage we will
transfer into the fopen tube more than
eight cell stage we are going to
transfer into the uterus
huh it s it blast same same same same
same same same same same same AR
yeah okay see how good your revision is
going
on enjoying everyone
yes yes
Buddies
so art is that technique for this we
have special technician embryologist are
there who take care of embryon it's
really very difficult job they remain in
laboratory until unless a baby is fully
developed and then they freeze it also
it's is it is having a you know it's
a it will it's a great help to those who
cannot have their own baby and it's
important for U yeah right INF fertility
treatment
okay
clear
okay let's
start so guys with this we have
completed this chapter also reproductive
Health now we have to start another
chapter which is evolution shall we
start or do you want a break come on
tell
me shall we start or do you want a
break you want a break or shall we start
come on tell
me no
break okay then I guess then we can
start the chapter Evolution no
break okay
let's
start hey it's okay now let's start this
chapter and uh I'll give you break at 4
okay at 4 we will take a
break okay so let's start
Evolution so what is evolution and what
are we going to study in this chapter
now evolution is all about evolving the
life forms which exist today humans dogs
elephant some fishes animals whosoever
are there on the Earth's surface they
were not like they were not same if I
talk about a millions of years back and
if I talk about how these organisms they
came on the Earth's surface that itself
is a big thing and we don't have a time
machine to go back to that particular
time era to get to know what individual
used to exist at that time so we have
some evidences and with the help of
evidences we can get to know that these
species used to exist at that time but
if you look at those organism and if you
look at these organism which exist today
there's huge
difference yes because with time they
were exposed to different environmental
condition they
developed and now we have different
organisms all
today every thing comes under the
science which is evolutionary biology so
let's start so what is an evolution
Evolution or evolutionary biology it's a
branch of science with time you can
after 12th you can pursue your career
also in this now branch of science for
the study of origin of Life evolution of
different life form of Earth is called
as bio Evolution or evolutionary biology
by
Mir yes
no
let's start first first we have to talk
about the origin of life
now before starting how life evolved on
the Earth's surface let's first talk
about how Universe started forming we
all know about the theory the most uh
important theory that is The Big Bang
Theory so big bang name itself indicate
that there was a huge explosion and
because of that huge explosion today we
have stars we have Galaxy
and in the Milky Way galaxies we have is
a earth now it states that the Universe
originated around 20 billions years ago
and that to by a huge explosion a huge
bum blast happened and because of the
this huge B bum blast today we have is
the Earth so Universe originated very
important data around 20 billions years
back by a huge explosion now next is
Earth Earth Earth Milky Way galaxy may
we have is the earth 4.5 billions years
ago so with time when the explosion
happened the smaller smaller one they
joined together and the smaller means to
say uh uh the Earth the other stars the
galaxies they started organizing
themselves and if I talk about the Earth
Earth started forming in the
4.5 billions years ago right and if I
talk about the life this is the this
this is the universe formed at 20
billions years ago this is a 4.5 and if
I talk about the life life is formed
around 500 Millions years ago
life the first Universe then Earth and
then we have is a life earlier
atmosphere let's look at the earlier
atmosphere all these are the lines from
the uh ncrt only there was no atmosphere
on the early Earth water Vapors was
there temperature was really very high
and it is considered the temperature was
all around 800 C so whatever water was
there water was in the form of water
vapor methane was there carbon dioxide
was there NH3 was releasing from the
molten Mass cover the surface at that
time lot of volcanic activities was
there and because of the volcanic
activities Earth was covered with a
molten mass and that were releasing
these gases of carbon dioxide methane
ammonia and water vapor was was present
present UV rays as there was
no you know ozone was not there so as
ozone was not there UV ray from the Sun
broke up the water UV ray they were
directly coming from the uh you know
from the outside from the Sun directly
into the Earth surface due to which
whatever water vapor was present they
were bro broken up into the H2 and O2 H2
H2 being lighter H2 will go up oxygen
now this oxygen combined with H3 it
combine with CH4 and it forms the water
carbon dioxide
Etc so they form the water okay because
of this water because water Vapors was
there were there in the environment and
these water vapor they condens and that
lead to the cloud formation so rain
happened and Rain happened for years for
the millions of years rain happened and
because of those you know the clouds and
because of that rain today we have is a
oceans today we have that sea with
us then the ozone layer started forming
right as it cooled the water vapor fell
as a rain to form the
oceans okay
clear no this is not Oparin and Harden
Theory unti this is just the origin of
life this is a just first second
paragraph of your ncrt we will go
towards the opin andalin also then there
was an ozone formation then there was a
rainfall okay life appeared almost 500
Millions years ago written over here
also okay buddies clear so this was a
primitive atmosphere this was the
Primitive atmosphere now moving on to
the next is now we have to discuss the
origin of life that was origin of
universe now origin of life in the
origin of life we have various theories
the first theory is the theory of
special creation so special some special
person came and special person they
formed the Earth and who is that special
person that is a God so this was given
by the father Sor is he said God created
everyone on one day they created sand on
another day they created plants on
another day they created Birds Etc now
Cosmos zoic Theory Cosmic theory is also
termed as panspermia
Theory panspermia Theory and this
panspermia Theory is given by RoR they
say that unit of life or Spore they were
transferred they were transferred or
they came from any other planet
including Earth so they came from any
other planet so this was a theory given
in Cosmic proposed by RoR next is theory
of the spontaneous generation
spontaneous spontaneous means suddenly
life comes from the um you know
non-living substances is what they say
autogenesis a biogenesis autogenesis
supported by the ancient Greek
philosopher tales and exender xenop
Plateau edicol aristal Etc it state that
ignore this
line it state that life came of the
decaying rotting matter Like Straw mud
Etc clear so they said k n life does
life came from um you know the dead
substances this is what they said they
said they said it was a some wheat brand
was there so there was a huge wheat and
because wheat was there and because of
that wheat the you know the rat
formation occur so this is how uh uh
like their Theory
came and today I know you all must be
laughing what is this story all about
but at that time we cannot go back to
the time machine they do not have any
idea regarding the natural selection
today we know about natural selection
today we have an idea of uh you know uh
different species the um you know the
effect of environment genes Etc at that
time they do not have any idea of Gene
genes were discovered later on and today
we know mosis the mitosis these things
are there they didn't know about it so
they came up this idea okay that can be
one of the reason and S it is important
also so whatever you
think if you're thinking their thinking
was also important when when you come up
with an idea suppose they came up with
this idea that life came from mud life
came from you know a sweat t-shirt
sweaty t-shirt so that makes other
people realize ke is he right or wrong
then they start studying they start
going in that
direction
m' ma'am it would be been easier to
study that we will study that also we
will study that also nothing wait now
next is Lis pasture Lis pasture
demonstrated that life came only from
pre-existing life and disproved this
Theory the theory which was given by
given like spontaneous generation Auto
biogenesis this was disapproved by the
um you know the Luis paser not only the
L Pasha there was one more scientist
whose name was Lazaro
Spen and Francisco ready so there were
three different scientists Luis pasture
Lazaro Spen and Francisco ready so they
did different kind of experiment and
their ultimate motive was to realize
life came from pre-existing life life
doesn't come from a non-living thing so
this was their idea three scientists
they worked
differently
okay now moving on to the next modern
chemical theory of origin of Life modern
chemical theory of origin of life was
given by Oparin AI Oparin he was a
Russian scientist and halan Halden was a
England born Indian scientist operan
theory was published in a book origin of
life in 1938 very very very important
three marker may this question you can
easily
expect along with what along with the
experiment which we will do now okay now
they said ke life initially when life
came life came from non-living
substances then from non-living to
living this is what their uh statement
was now proposed by Oparin and halan
this states that life form from a life
was originated first first from a non
living inorganic organic molecules such
as CH4 NH3 water sugar proteins nuclic
acid Etc they gave this statement of a
biogenesis first but biogenesis later on
they said first life was formed from
non-living substance stances like
inorganic substances organic substances
and from that life came from
life okay and everyone please stop
talking what all you guys talk
about okay so let's
proceed
okay H ch ch now let's
proceed experimental evidence of chem
chemical origin of Life chemical origin
of life was given by opin and Harden
Oparin was from Russia and Harden was
from England so they gave this idea of
chemical Evolution they said life first
came from in organic substances and then
from the life itself and now this is an
experimental evidence and this
experimental evidence was super
important again I'm saying for boards it
is super important and if you really
think this chapter is difficult I'll say
no this chapter is not at all difficult
this is very easy
okay
now they created a condition like that
of a primitive Earth who did this first
of all first of
all Miller and Ur experiment this was
the Miller and Ur
experiment and Ur Miller and Ur came
forward and they said we will prove so
they gave the experiment proof
of
experimental proof
of chemical origin of
Life origin of
life right they did this experiment so
let's have a look now what they did they
took two flask and they jointed in this
way in the first flask was bigger and
another flask flask was smaller in the
first flask there was electrode which
were producing electrical discharge
because at the Primitive environment at
that particular time there were
electrical discharges and because of
those electrical thundering
activities they also want y be same way
we have to create a same environment so
they did electrode they took electrode
also right they wanted over here the
temperature should be ra very high and
how did they create that temperature
because they took another flask and in
another flask they were boiling the
water as the boiling the water the
vapors they were coming here which were
maintaining the temperature of almost
around
800 C which itself is huge just imagine
Deli temperature if it goes more than
50 C we burn like hell and it is 800
C right temperature was really high
because of this boiling water at that
particular environment environment at
that particular time environment was
reducing reducing means no oxygen was
there so here reducing
environment how did they create reducing
environment they created reducing
environment by the vacuum pump so they
took this vacuum pump and they used it
here and with this they were producing
the and reducing environment no
oxygen so everything in this uh chamber
was like that of a previous uh thing now
they introduced some gases also methane
ammonia water that in the form of this
moisture and H2 was there it was in the
ratio of 1 is 2 is to 1 where one was
your
ammonia
sorry clear they kept this setup as such
with a G gases inside with electrode
with temperature very high and they kept
this for 7
days then they came into that room
Miller and uray and they what they did
they condensed whatever substances they
were forming over here they wanted to
condense and they wanted to check what
all things are there in it what all
reaction happened because of these gases
so they used one condenser from that
condenser water was coming in and water
was going out water was not in touch
with the gases water was not in touch
with the substances which were making
over here it just that some a pipe is
here and outside some water is Flowing
just to cool down because 800 C if
something is there it's very difficult
to touch isn't it then they collect it
here with the help of a to and they
realized organic substances are there
but all organic substances they found
nucleotides were there some amino acids
were there so they were shocked how this
formation occur so they realized these
formation was because of the gases which
were prevailing at that time they were
because of the electrode they were
because of the temperature at that
particular
time is this point clear so again I'm
saying everyone you all have your notes
make this diagram super important again
up though I am standing here and this
can be asked in your paper okay
okay let's
start now let's read let's do a quick
reading now they made electrod discharge
a closed flask CH4 NH3 water water vapor
as a result some amino acid formation
was there this was asked in neat paper
though it is there in your cbsc uh in
your ncrt also so can be asked similar
experiment other observed the formation
of sugar nitrogen on basis pigments and
fat other scientists also did did this
this experiment they said okay if he
he's doing this experiment this is very
easy to set up let's do this
also their name was not there because
Miller and Ur they were Pioneer in this
and that is the reason we study their
name in our
textbook okay now first non- cellular
form of life originated three billions
years ago while RNA protein
polysaccharides Etc so life came
here okay now moving on to the next now
we have to move towards the evidence of
organic evolution now it is like we
cannot go back to that time can we go
back to that time not possible so we
looked for some evidences so these
evidences they were paleontological
evidences comparative Anatomy morphology
physiological biochemistry biog
geographical and embryological evidences
by looking at these evidences by
studying these evidences see now what we
have is inorganic substances organic
substances with time we realize ke the
number of species which exist today they
were not
same so we wanted to study what all
species were there in those million 500
millions of years back how this
Evolution happened so we started
studying the
evidences okay clear let's have a look
first paleontological evidences right
paleontological evidences now
paleontological EV es that means study
of
fossils that means study of
fossiles right to study why this is used
to study the evolutionary history or the
race history because you know early now
we have a horse a modern horse and if
you study the evolution of horse you
will realize horse was like the size of
a box with time it developed and today
we have is a modern horse with us how
with the help of a penological evidences
because we looked at the
fossils and fossils they were present in
sedimentary rocks by determining the age
of the sedimentary rocks we got to know
that this particular kind of horse used
to exist at that particular time and now
we have is a
this right now next one to study the
connecting link between the two group of
organism to study about the extinct
animals to study about the geological
period by analysing the fossils in
different sedimentary rocks two studies
showed that life forms varied over time
and certain life forms are restricted to
certain geological time spans these are
the paleontological
evidences right clear one second
okay now moving on to the next is this
comparative Anatomy seven second
evidence we have is comparative anatomy
and the morphology now listen what kind
of question comes can come can be asked
in the paper he uh write down the
evidences of evolution so first
penological evidences everything I have
given you now second we are studying
this no no we are not uh looking at it
right or
nothing now homology homo homo homo
means same or
similar what
origin origin is similar origin is
similar but function is
different function is
different
function is different now how will you
understand this let's take my example
now it is like it is
like I have a family right in my family
there are five
members one is doing one function means
someone is a teacher someone is an IT
professional someone is something
someone is something someone is
something but we have a common origin
this is termed as homolog
similarity based on the common origin if
we have a common Orin if we have a
common ancestor if we have a common
ancestor and similar basic plan of
organization embryonic development is
similar that is
homoy homo similarity loogy means to say
in the terms of origin orientation
organization embryonic development if
everything is same but function is not
same this is
homology homology gives us an idea of a
divergent evolution so it gives an idea
of divergent
evolution divergent evolution because
something is diverging from a
point d
vergent right okay so here for this
respect we have an
example we have a Thorns of bong Andia
we have a tendrils of
kukura both of them they have a common
origin epical meristem right they have a
common origin but they have a different
function Thorn's function is a
protection tenderers they help in
providing the support and you know bi
boty more than me now you know this the
thorns and the bong Thorns of the bongan
Valia and the tendril of kukur tendrils
helps in climbing it provides the
support isn't it now moving on to the
next is if you'll take all of this what
is the similarity between these there's
a man cheetah Veil and the bat what is
the similarity between these come on
tell me in the comment section come on
come on tell me in the comment section
what is the similarity between these
these
all come on come on come
on come on similarity what's the
similarity similarity is all of them
they are mammals they have a common
origin yes butterfly
butterfly yes
they
huh yes tendrils mammals yes just me
you're
right okay so here if you look at their
four limbs if you look at their four
limbs the for liim structure is same see
there will be see what is this bone
humorus radius alna there will be carpal
metacarpal everything is same humorous
radius ala humorous radius ala humorous
radius those structure is different but
but overall if I say everything is same
they have a radius they have radius alna
humorus everything is same but the
function is different humans May what is
the use for holding right what's the use
for cheah for running for the wheel
swimming for the bat climbing you know
to
support yes we all are same we belong to
each other isn't
it great we are family right so yes
absolutely right so they have a same
structure
but different
function different
function okay
now let's move on to the next
analogy now analogy what is analogy
analogy means the or origin everything
is different
so origin they do not have any origin
origin is
different
but but function is
same is
same now let's have a look it is a
similarity in organ based on the similar
function similar function right or
organs which have different origin and
dissimilar fundamental structure but
have a similar function or termed as
analogous organ are you guys sleeping no
right yes now moving on to the next is
examples up they look at this eyes of
octopus and mammal Sky look at the eyes
what is the function to see the object
but the structure is
different flippers next is flippers of
penguin and
dolphins origin is not same function is
same next is sweet potato and potato
sweet potato is a root modification
whereas a potato is a stem
modification function is same food
storage function is same that is a food
storage isn't
it okay now let's move on to the
biochemical evidences so we have some
biochemical evidences also like organism
show similar in protein genes other
biomolecules metabolism it indicate a
common ancestry we look at the organism
we look at their biomolecules we look at
the atile coenzyme we look look look at
different things and we realize yes
genes are same yes these biochemicals
are same same enzyme which is
functioning in me same enzyme
functioning in any other animal this
gives us an idea that we have a common
ancestry we have not sorry we have a
kind of
relation
okay
okay let's move on to the next one
embryological evidences embryological
evidences was given by Ernest Heckle
right just let's complete this chapter
then I'll give you a break okay I'll
give you a
break it is observed that all vertebrate
embryos have some common features that
are absent in adult some common features
features are there which are absent in
adults all artivate embryo including
human develop vestigial gilets we used
to have vestigial gillet just behind the
head but it is functional only in fishes
not found in any other individual so I
I'll show you do I have that image no I
don't have that image but if you'll
Google if you look at the embryos the
different embryos you will realize they
look alike either you take a fish one or
frog one all embryos they look alike
they will be having gill
slits are they functional in us no right
you remember Animal Kingdom in class
11th you remember class 11th may we used
to study uh key fenal gill slits are
their characteristic feature of cordate
so those fenal Gill slit they were
functional only in
fishes do we respire through gills no
right no however Carl alest one beer
rejected this proposal he noted that
embryos never pass through the adult
stage of any other animal it is just
their development stage so embryological
evidence was was given by Ernest Heckle
it was rejected by Van beer very very
very important question rejected by one
beer
11th Co now let's talk about evidences
from the biog geography
evidences
from
bio
geography evidences from biog
geography
right Darwin went to galpagos
Island what do you want me to repeat
butterfly I'll repeat that again
yes tell
me tell me tell
me tell me what do you want me to repeat
butterfly first what tell me what's your
name
okay tell me tell me tell me hey bhagan
what you all guys talk you you guys can
talk for
hours and you know it's your paper in a
few days you have your paper biology if
you're not studying then please let
other students study okay otherwise you
can please move
out okay any
doubt okay okay now adaptive radiation
so let's start this adaptive radiation
now first let's talk about the
biogeography I'll give you one thing and
then we will start writing something now
if I talk about the Darin Darin went to
Galapagos Island Galapagos Island is a
secluded um Island he went there he
realized ke U some birds are there which
are origin originally seed
eating then he realized some other birds
are also there which are very much
similar to seed eating wobblers but they
are adapted to various food some are
insect eating some are you know
vegetarian various adaptation was seen
so he said it is because of the
different environmental condition so he
called this as adaptive radiation so it
is like Original Seed eting birds were
there and Original Seed eting Birds they
were adapted to different environmental
condition some became you know insect
eating some became Cactus eating so like
this they were evolved so this he called
it as adaptive radiation right now this
is a process of evolution of different
species in a given geographical
area what is
this adaptive radiation is the process
of
evolution in
a given one geographical
area
graphical
radiating from a
point is
called adaptive
radiation
is called adaptive
radiation right in a geographical area
if they radiate into different direction
that is the adaptive radiation right so
this was one of the
evidence similar kind of trend was seen
in Australia that is a marsupial
radiation all the marsupial they belong
to a same category right right so some
became Tasmanian wall tiger cat band
Bandit an maril right so this kind of
evolution was also
seen so this gives us an idea of what
does it gives us an idea it gives us an
idea of divergent evolution isn't it
it's a divergent evolution radiating
from the point I'll explain you one more
thing wait similar Trend was seen in the
placental mammals Also earlier it was
the marsupial now I'm seeing the
placental mammals so in a geographical
area that is Australia there were
marsupial radiation
also
marsupial
radiation maral they were Evol evolving
like
this your kangaroo
one right they were evolving they
realized in the same area the placental
mammals they were also
radiating same area similar Trend was
observed similar
Trend this is termed as convergent
evolution or the parallel
Evolution right placental mammal in
Australia also exhibit adaptive
radiation in evolving into varieties of
such placental mammals which Each of
which appears to be similar to a
corresponding marial so in an area in a
particular geographical area there was a
convergent evolution what is that see if
I talk about only this what is this this
is a Divergent Evolution some Divergence
is happening but when I'm seeing in a
area in an area this evolution is also
happening and this is also happening and
they are very much similar to each other
see placental mammal if you look at the
mole they're very much similar to
marsupial mole placental May in the same
area if you look at the antier they're
very similar to the numbet if you look
at the this placental mouse marup mouse
lemmer spotted ccus flying squirrel
finger Bobcat Tasmanian diger cat wolf
Tasmanian wolf so this is termed as
convergent evolution in an area two
different things are happening and that
too similar to each other clear so this
also gives us an idea yes they were
similar to each other because they were
exposed to different environmental
condition so we can keep them under the
same category so that means kind of
relation is
there
okay
okay now moving on to the next we have
is evidence of n uh evolution by the
natural selection we all know about the
natural selection
right natural selection is the process
by which organisms that are best suited
for environment survive and reproduce
some evidences are given below let's
talk about
it
yes AA Raj grow said ma'am convergent or
diverent please explain okay yes this is
cbsc going on okay so uh convergent and
divalution good question Raj Raj I'll
tell you convergent
see first homology you remember homology
or homologous organ this show divergent
evolution now everybody Focus here now
I'll give you a a very important data
here right if I talk about
convergent sorry if I talk about
analogy it gives us an idea of
convergent evolution of how to
remember in summer
nowadays nowadays in summer what do we
like most we should have a TV and if
that TV is HD then the by it's like
party for us
and if we have AC that is also party for
us so h d a these are the things which
are which we want in summer HD
television and an AC so h means homology
divergent evolution analogy convergent
evolution done this point clear then
let's talk about the adaptive radiation
up they let's look at the adaptive
radiation
Raj adaptive
now there are group of
animals right they have a common
origin but with time they were exposed
to different environmental condition and
they are R radiating in a different
direction at a particular location this
is termed as adaptive
radiation and this gives us an idea of
divergent
evolution yes Raj this gives us an idea
of divergent
evolution that diverging from a point
adaptive radiation in an area AB listen
now same thing same divergent evolution
in the same area is happening in another
species and they are very parallel to
each other parall if you look at this
one one is very similar to one here if
you look at the two two is very similar
to two here this is these are the
marsupial and these are the mammals
Australian marsupial and placental
mammals this I called it as convergent
evolution both are converging both are
converging individually they are showing
divergent evolution but they're
converging also is this point clear
Raj yes tanu clear everyone no
doubt why you guys talk so
much
okay so let's start uh one second
and okay natural selection so natural
selection is naturally selected today we
have a neat exam with us we have a cbsc
exam with us that means someone is
checking ahuh right they both are
parallel evolution is occurring very
good very
nice okay now moving on to the next is
natural selection is something they are
checking naturally on the uh
capabilities if I say Corona with time
you know this covid came and those who
were better suited those who are having
a good immunity they were selected by
nature and those who are having the bad
immunity they were eliminated by Nature
so that can be a kind of a natural
selection isn't it so that is also kind
of a natural selection now natural
selection here we have one more example
in around 1850
1850s in 1850 that is before
industrialization before
industrialization and after
industrialization
right
so before
industrialization
bitson B
area and bitson
carbonaria were the two species of M
moth these were the two species of
moth right these were the two species of
moth used to exist similarly here
also V
area and it's in carbon
area these were the species who used to
exist
right because industrialize indust uh
industrialization was not there so this
was the tree right tree tree tree tree
tree tree so you know the tree the bark
was covered with
lyans bark was covered with lyans and
lyans you all know lyans grow only in
that area where pollution is not there
so when there was no pollution so at
that particular time bitson bit area
bitson bit area was the light colored
moth light color and these were the one
which were dark colored
moth so their number the light colored
Mo number was really very high the
reason is they used to hide on this
lyans dark color they were completely
visible that is the reason their number
was really very
less with time natural selection
came right natural selection came so
natural selection the bits and bit area
which were light in color and here what
happened was this was a
tree this was a tree so on the tree
there was there were no Likens so the
bark was
dark so the bark was really very dark
you know the bark is really dark so dark
used to hide so their number was
more and their number was
less
so in England before industrialization
there were more white winged Mo white
light color tree uh on trees then dark
winged or melanized moth after
industrialization more dark winged moth
and less White Winged Mo mods were
developed so it is like a industrialized
it is like a natural selection natural
selection okay now reason before
industrialization there were white lyans
covered the tree in that background
white winged moth survived but dark
winged moth were picked out by the
Predators right now after
industrialization the tree trunks became
dark they became dark because lyans were
not there as lyans were not there so
bark was visible Park is dark due to
Industrial smoke and suit no growth of
lyans
under this condition The White Winged
moth did not survive because of Predator
identified them easily dark winged moth
survived because of suitable dark
background is this point clear clear to
everyone
now now let's talk about theories of
evolution now what we have discussed so
far let's do a quick revision we talked
about the origin of Earth then we talked
about origin of Life various theories
then we talked about the chemical
evolution in chemical Evolution we
talked about the Miller and Ur
experiment and after that Miller and Ur
experiment we talked about the evidences
of evolution paleontological evidences
comparative anatomy and morphology
evidences we talked about the
embryological evidences we talked about
biochemical evidences we talked about
biogeographical evidences then the
evidences from the natural
selection
okay now theories of evolution in
theories now we have to come back
everything whatever we have studied now
we have to correlate everything so by
looking at this evidences some
scientists they came to this idea so
first was a lamaris lamaris in detail is
not given in your uh you know ncrt
theory of inherit of acquired character
this was a theory which was given by
John Baptista D Lamar Right theory of
inheritance of acquired characteristics
is the first theory of organic
evolution now what was this Theory all
about theory is all about if I want to
change I can change if I want my neck
should be long I can increase the length
of the neck if I want to increase my
muscle size I can do that so every
individual they have some internal vital
force and by altering that internal
vital force I can do anything whatever I
want to do what they said they said
internal vital force effect of
environment and new need if I want to
increase the length of my neck I can
increase the length of my
neck effect of environment and new needs
use and disuse of organ more I will use
one or organ or I will use one organ the
length of that organ the size of that
organ will increase continuously I'm
talking to you so that means my vocal uh
vocal sack size should increase this is
what they said but which is not true
inheritance of acquired character
whatever changes I do in my life that
will be acquired to the Next Generation
this is what they said four points you
have to remember internal vital force
effect of environment and new needs use
and disuse of organ inheritance of
acquired character this was given by
John Baptist D lar in the theory
inheritance of acquired
characters okay clear
everyone
now now see this is what they said he
said there was a giraffe so Here Giraffe
wanted to have some green grasses which
were on top of the tree so they extended
the
neck similarly so their neck size
increased so their child their kids were
having a you know a blong neck this is
what they said which you all know it's
not
true now next come the scientist Darwin
now first I'll explain the same concept
what Darwin said Darwin said giraffe
Evolution was not because of the not
because of the extension not because of
the use it was like in the environment
there were giraffe who were having long
neck there were giraffe who were having
small neck because leaves which were
near to the ground they
vanished with time those which were
having the small neck they were not able
to feed they
die they die and other who were having
the long neck they
survived and now as they survived they
were reproducing and now we have is we
have that giraffe which is is having a
long neck now let's have a look let's
read this Darin Darwinism Darin theory
is also termed as theory of natural
selection proposed jointly by the
Charles Darwin and Alfred Russel valis
he was maluski there was a theory of
population he was very much influenced
by the theory of
population so he came up with these
features you can easily correlate both
of
this
right first over production each
individual they have a capacity to
reproduce at maximum they can reach
their biotic potential they can produce
n number of Offspring struggle for
existence they all struggle so that they
can be they can you know they can
survive they always struggle variation
and heridity all are different from each
other all are not same they said
heridity they can can't transfer the
things from one generation to
another only those which are best suited
will be selected by Nature this is the
New Concept which he introduced he
introduced the concept of variation also
he introduces the concept of the natural
selection also and origin of new species
these are the points which he
mentioned
clear
clear okay so moving on to the next is
now theory of natural selection now
theory of natural selection may we have
is this Theory which is a mutation
Theory mutation Theory mutation Theory
gave some ideas regarding the darnis but
he modified that also he said variations
are very Smalls he said whatever Darin
mentioned he there are variation there
are changes they are very small and he
did not explain the reason behind the
variation that was the biggest drawback
of Darwin so he mutation Theory came and
mutation Theory explained the reasons
for variation he said mutation is one of
the Reason by which variation
come mutation theory was put forward in
1901 by Hugo devies he conducted an
experiment of ooal larana that is a
evening Prim news he believed that
Evolution take place through mutation
not by minor variation whatever Darwin
said Darwin said variations are there
changes are there he did not explain
what all variations are there what are
the reasons for it but he was able to
explain it Darian variation is minor
slow and directional he said ke whatever
changes are happening he said can be due
to the meosis but they are very slow
minor and Direction uh they are having a
particular direction due to this gradual
Evolution occur the reason behind the
evolution well this can lead to a very
slow Evolution now mutation he said ke
mutation whatever I have explained
mutation mutation is sudden random
directionless variation here speciation
is a saltation and what is a saltation
saltation is a single step large
mutation and because of that large
mutation today Evolution can happen is
the origin of evolution it's a or of
variation of
humans Okay
C
now now let's move on to the next topic
which is a hardi vug
equilibrium clear Hardy so let's see
theories of evolution May first we
talked about the lar Theory you have to
remember the complete name of Lamar the
theory acquired character Theory which
he gave then we talked about about the
points in the lar Theory then we talked
about the Darin theory different point
related to the darn Theory and then we
talked about the mutation Theory given
by the Hugo deves now we are discussing
the hardi vug equilibrium so hardy vug
equilibrium is another equilibrium this
tells he Gene
frequency gen
frequency
of randomly meeting
randomly meeting panmictic
population meting population 10 to
remain
constant 10 to
constant
if no
external
force is acting on
it he said whatever genes are now we
know the genes
are okay now we
know right
uh now we know what are the genes right
so genes frequency they always remain
constant from one generation to another
until unless some force act on it now
what all Force did he talk about it he
said there are some factors which affect
this equilibrium he said the equilibrium
that remains is like this
p + Q  + 2
PQ is equal to 1 or p + Q is equal to 1
this is what they
said
this is what they said what is P
Square p sare is the frequency of a
homozygous
dominant
G
frequency of
homozygous
dominant
dominant what is this Q
sare Gene
frequency
of
homozygous
recessive right
2pq is
the gene
frequency
of of heto
zygotes heto
zot clear now next is what is p and Q
what is p p is a liic fre
quency alic frequency it's not a gene
frequency it's an alic
frequency right and Q is alic frequency
of of dominant
Al and this is the frequency of a
recessive
Al this is also Gene frequency of a
recessive Al and the dominant right now
they say it's not equal to one whenever
there is Gene
recombination Whenever there is a
mutation Whenever there is a gene
genetic drift which is also termed as
cival right effect there's a gene flow
and there's a natural flow these are the
they said ke these are the factors which
actually affect the equilibrium now what
why we are studying this there must be
some reason why we are studying why we
are talking because these are the
reasons by which different species they
exert on they exist on this Earth's
surface that is a reason behind the
evolution these are the reason behind
the evolution this is what they say gen
recombination we all have studied meosis
recombination occur here and whenever
there's a recombination the Hardy
equilibrium that means the species who
are actually in a normal Zone that means
there is no variation they will change
they will start showing the variation
mutation Sudden Change genetic drift
Sudden Change in a population genetic
drift Al frequency change sudden gene
flow people are migrating from one place
to another if we have a population here
right they do not show any variation if
something is coming from outside that
means some genes are being introduced if
something is going out genes are being
exited they're removed next is a natural
flow when there is a natural flow is
occuring so that case also there will be
change okay
now
now okay now let's talk about this
natural selection now let's talk about
Buddies the types of natural
selection
of natural
selection types of natural selection
let's discuss this let
me increase the AC
temperature second it's really hot
here one second buddies just a
second
yeah types of natural selection let's
discuss this okay now see if if
seriously you will be able to like if
you'll focus on this you'll be able to
understand everything okay uh just after
this chapter we will complete this
chapter then I'll give you a break right
now natural selection now this is a
population can you see this is a
population and this population is full
of rat now in this population you will
see some white rats are there some
medium color rats are there and some
dark color rats are also there right can
you see right now suppose suppose
something happened and because of that
something only dark colored are selected
this is termed as directional selection
something happened some natural
selection some force is acting on it so
in that case that will be termed as a
directional selection that is a
directional selection on One Direction
We Are selecting something for example
uh you know uh suddenly when we when we
started spraying DDT on all the insect
they become they became DDT resistant
all insect they become DDT resistant so
that is a insect resistance insect
resistant DDT resistance now next one is
this can you see diversifying selection
so here either this this or that either
this or that will be selected medium
people they were not selected one
particular phenotype was not selected
either this or that stabilizing
selection stabilizing selection only the
medium individual they are selected so
this is what it
is yes any doubt any doubt come on tell
me if you have any doubt you can ask me
come on uh we are about to finish this
chapter some more uh points are there we
will disc discuss
that so here you can take an example of
a human
height you can take an example of a
human
height and here buddies you can take an
example of a CLE cell
anemia CLE Cel anemia right and here the
DDT
resistance DD resistance
now CLE cell anemia means those who are
having HBS HBS both the AL will not be
able to survive the those who are having
HBA and HBS they will survive and those
who are HB HB they are already surviving
now human height we all know medium
person they are always
selected
now let's talk about evolution of plants
so how plants evolved let's have a look
look you all know we are evolved from
the plants are evolved from the chloride
an ancestors chloride to Tropi to Ria to
sopyan and from copian the synops sits
the ferns the genos the conifers knail
pyet everything angiosperms dcot Etc
everything evolved from this now
question comes if I talk about the
Brophy brop fyes are evolved from the
chlorophytes ancestors Brites if I talk
about the lycopods lorts they evolved
from the troyes so this gives us an idea
how Evolution
happened similar trend has been seen in
case of the animals also here these are
the reptiles these are the early
reptiles which you all know they do not
exist anym if I talk about the from this
the two species they arise one is a
sorid and second is a synapsids from
from sopit copits we have Turtles we
have lizards we have the snakes we have
is taras we have is the those dinosaurs
toodon they are now do not have with us
the dinosaurs then the therapsids
they're not here with us the synapsids
were the one that ultimately give rise
to the
animals right how did we got to know
about it with the help of different
evidences of
evolution and how can we know that which
species how can we know that what's the
reason behind the evolution that we can
easily calculate with the help of the
Hardy wibur
equilibrium done
okay so now moving on to the Evol AA
there's one data regarding this 500
Millions years ago the first organism
who arise that was the invertebrates
were formed and Ive 350 jaw as fish is
evolved 320 seaweeds and few plants 350
again fish with a snout strong fins they
can move to the land and led fin kocan
was found in South Africa with that we
got to know he amphibians they evolved
from the fishes because these were the
fishes who can easily migrate to the
land right so from that the amphibians
low fil form the amphibians amphibians
into reptiles and dinosaur disappeared
in 650 Millions years ago why this data
I'm discussing it's there in
ncrt
okay
now moving on to the next evolution of
man so there is a you
know uh you know a chart regarding this
the first organism that is the humanlike
creature 15 Millions years ago was SE
life was evolved 500 Millions years ago
life I am seeing humans the first human
evidence today we know that is the drop
pacus and dram pacus drop pacus they
were more
apik more apik and RAM pacus were more
humanlike they were evolved they used to
walk like gorillas and chimpanzee drop
pacus they were apik Ram pacus was one
like this was once asked in a neat
2016 then then came the 3 to 4 billions
years ago manlike primate height up to
4T fossils of manlike bones found in
Ethiopia and Tanzania and you know what
is that that is the
Australopithecus aop
pacus that is the
Australopithecus right these were the
organism so they were bodies you won't
believe they were having the
height
one
second yeah Australopithecus they were
having the height of around 4T fossils
manlike bone Ethiopia and Tanzania made
it was seen now next come the two
millions years ago in the 2 Millions
years ago there was a Homo habilis this
was Homo
habilis habilis
Homo
habilis lived in East African glassland
hunted with stone weapons ate fruit
clear homo heis first humanlike hominid
brain capacity yes their brain capacity
you have to write down that is around
650 to 800 CC and you know what was
their brain capacity Australopithecus
that was around 400 to 600 CC
this was there now 1.5 million year ago
Homo erectus Java man they were having
the brain capacity of around 900 CC they
used to eat
meat Now 1 lakh to 40,000 years ago
homon nandal schames brain capacity was,
1400 CC lived in East and Central Asia
used to hide and protect their body
buried their dead so they were more
civilized then came the 75,000 to 10,000
years ago homo sapiens Modern Man
prehistoric CA develop few years back
only and they developed the agriculture
so let's discuss everything let's
discuss this again racus racus
Australopithecus Homo habilis
see this is what we have studied right
racus racus then Australopithecus then
Homo habilis then Homo erectus after
homoerectus neanderthals they have is
homo neanderthals neanderthals after
that we have is a homo sapiens right do
it again let's do it again first came
drakus racus after drakus racus there we
have the Australopithecus after
Australopithecus Homo habilis Homo
erectus neanderthals and the homo
sapiens sapiens come on let's revise
this again everyone let's revise this
again first the racus rap pacus ostop
pacus after aop pacus we have a Homo
habilis homoerectus mandals and Homo
sapiens
clear for everyone you have to remember
the brain
capacities done done done done so guys
so with this we have completed the
chapter which is the evolution next we
have to start the biotechnology so
before biotechnology before starting the
biotechnology let's take a break right
let's take a break for the half an
hour right let's take a break for uh
like let's take a break for 20 minutes
20 minutes are enough
minutes let me check if I we have a
timer timer timer
timer
[Music]
uh yes we will meet just after 20
minutes 20
minutes right so we'll meet just after
20 minutes by the time let's make a take
a break bye-bye we not go don't go
guys
hey buddies are you getting my
voice come on come on come on tell me
tell me tell me yes break is over come
back now we are going to start a new
chapter which is biotechnology principle
and
processes yes so marathon is still going
on we are done with the five almost 5
hours are you guys getting my voice
yes great great great H great are you
getting my voice good so we are going to
start with the full energy now another
chapter three chapters done this is a
fourth chapter which we are starting and
we are starting with the biotechnology
principle and processes in the last we
will do human health and diseases yes
everybody ready now so how was your
three chapters it went well see how
dedicated we are we whole team of PW we
organize this session because you know
your next exam is your biology and what
we want is our students should do great
in
that yes very nice very
nice hi Prisha okay good good
good three chapters done yes okay so
let's start with the biotechnology
biotechnology principle and processes we
are starting
okay so before proceeding let's first
know what actually a biotechnology is so
biotechnology is all about
modifying right earlier we used to you
we used to uh you know take care of only
natural capabilities of
microorganisms like we know how to make
CTS you know there are some bacterias
who can give us antibiotics so we used
to just focus on that because that was
their natural capability now what we are
doing is with the help of a recombinant
DNA technology we are modifying those
microorganism so that we can use them
for the products and the services let's
have a look so what is a standard
definition of biotechnology given by efb
that is the European Federation of
biotechnology European Federation of
biotechnology says when we integrate
when we use the natural capability that
means natural sign means organism sells
part of their molecular analog for our
products and services this is termed as
the biotechnology let me first switch on
the
AC one second it's really very hard and
guys I'm telling you seriously it's so
difficult to stand in front of the
screen with just warit heat one
second
okay so this was given by European
Federation of biotechnology and this
European Federation of biotechnology
says we should we use of you know the
Natural Science products and the
services for various things right for
the products for the services Etc so
that comes under this this full form is
also important can be asked in one Mark
now let's move on to the next one
principles of biotechnology among many
the two core technique that enabl the
birth of the modern biotechnology are so
overall the biotechnology is made up of
two different component without these
two component biotechnology is
handicapped first thing is the genetic
engineering so what is a genetic
engineering genetic engineering means to
alter the DNA engineering we are using
the tools so that we can modify the DNA
techniques to alter the chemistry of a
genetic material either that can be DNA
or RNA to introduce this into the host
organism and thus change the phenotype
of the host organism genetic
engineering yes we are modifying the
gene genetic
engineering yes now moving on to the
next is second most important part is
bioprocess engineering now suppose this
is an organism this is an organism and
it is a cell right right this is the
chromosome you have modified it with the
help of a biotechnology with the help of
a recombinant DNA technology you have
introduced a gene right let me use
another color that will be more visible
to you so I have introduced this white
Gene here done now I want the product I
want the gene
product but how is it possible how much
product am I going to get by only uh you
know culturing a single cell not
possible Right
we will get only a small very little
amount of product so what will I do I
will use the technique which is termed
as bioprocess Engineering in the
bioprocess engineering what we do is we
culture these
cells we culture cells we culture cells
how we give them a particular
environment we give them a particular
temperature we provide them a particular
pH we culture them according to their
requirements
and then we extract our product out of
it that all comes under the bioprocess
engineering maintenance of sterile
microbial contamination free ambients in
chemical engineering process to enable
the growth of only desired microb
eukariotic cell that to in large
quantities for the manufacturer of
biotechnology product like antibiotics
vaccine enzymes Etc this aspect is
related to Pure culturing so this is
very much different from those culture
which we do in our labor
normal laboratory but in biotechnology
lab we use bioprocess Biore reactors are
there a huge bioreactors which has a
capacity of around 1,000 liter so there
fluid is there we provide culture medium
we provide temperature so that we can
culture those microorganism any
eukariotic cell whom we have modified
where we have introduced yes the gene of
Interest okay okie doie no recombinant
DNA technology so what actually the
recombinant DNA technology is then I'll
be telling you what was the first
recombinant U you know the DNA which
which was produced recombinant DNA
technology is all about see what we do
this is a plasmid which is a extra
chromosomal one right now the first
recombinant let's explain this with the
help of a first recombinant
DNA
first
recombinate
DNA molecule so how did we produce the
first recombinant DNA molecule so first
let's understand this first recombinant
first means very first recombinant means
new combination that means this is a
normal DNA and then this normal DNA I
have introduced something like this this
is a new recombinant this is a new
recombinant DNA and this was the first
of all this was produced by Stanley
Kohan and Herbert Boer this was done by
Stanley
Kohan
and
Herbert
Boer Stanley Gohan and Herbert Boyer and
when what this started that when did he
do this in
1972 9 years after the discovery of the
one very important tool that was a recom
uh that was the rtion endon nucleus that
was discovered in
1963 and this was done in
1972 now here now listen very carefully
this is a gene of Interest so what
scientist did they took a gene of
Interest this is a gene of interest and
this Gene of Interest was the antibiotic
resistance
Gene
antibiotic
resistance Gene and this antibiotic
resistant Gene was used this was cut
from here with the help of a restriction
enzyme these are the enzyme which was
discovered again I'm saying in the
1963 almost just check it whether I'm
100% sure it is 1963 so this was cut
from this place then the gene was
isolated antibiotic resistance Gene this
was a plasmid which was taken and here
the another Gene was introduced this was
a gene which was introduced this plasmid
was taken from salmonella typhimurium
Ty muum now all of you must be thinking
M what is salmona tyum salmona tyum is a
bacteria very much similar to that of
eoli and uh yes this was introduced with
the help of a ligase it was joined and
now we have is a modified plasmid and
this modified plasmas was introduced
into the
eoli this is what they did the first
recombinant DNA molecule which was which
the produced the question comes what is
a plasmid plasmid is a extra chromosomal
DNA this is a
cell in a bacterial cell we have the
plasmids these are the plasmids extra
chromosomal they have their own
bacterial uh you know bacterial
chromosome is also there but the
circular the double standard the plasmid
which is present they basically provide
this is what this is a plasmid so this
provides some extra properties like
antibiotic resistance Etc and Etc so
they scientist they just took out this
plasmid they took out this plasmid they
inserted the gene of interest in it and
again they have introduced this modified
plasmid into the ecoli this is what they
do right so yes plasmid is like a
carrier it's like how you go from one
place to another you book a cab either
you book a ob or a Ola or any other Taxi
you use similarly this is that
taxi right
okay now moving on to the next is now
let's talk about now we have to discuss
the major discoveries
May one second no another Discovery
another major important Discovery is
this restriction end endonuclease
restriction enzyme restriction enzym so
what are these restriction enzyme why we
call this as a restriction because they
were isolated from Bia first thing they
were
isolated from
bacteria that this is not the reason we
call it restricted but scientists
realized ke whenever a
bacteria is infected with a bacteria
phase they saw whenever a bacteria phase
infect a
bacteria they release their genome
inside bacteria phase they release their
genome inside the bacteria this This Is
How They infect bacteria has this
capacity that they produce some enzyme
which is termed as the restriction
enzymes they produce re right in the
cell in the cell they will produce the
re they have this natural
capacity and what this AR will do they
will kill they will cut the DNA into
fragments so it cut the
DNA foreign DNA into fragment not the
native one foreign
DNA into
fragments this can be asked in one
marker why we call this as restriction
so it cut the DNA into the fragment and
when it cut the DNA into various
fragments then scientist realize what is
this why we have some enzyme which cut
the DN into fragment and that to its
specific places how it is possible then
scientists they extracted those enzymes
and he they called they named it as
restriction
endonuclease growth restrict the
insertion of any foreign DNA into the
host cell so they took it and today we
have the Restriction endon nucleus with
us
now why it is not cutting the own DNA
because of methylation because their own
DNA is methylated that is the
reason
okay now principle it recognize a
specific palindromic nucleotide sequence
in the DNA cut each of the two stranded
of the double helix at a specific
position in a sugar Fox phosphate back
background is say from this point many
question can be
asked right now it recognize a specific
palindromic sequence what is a
palindromic sequence palindromic
sequence is a repeat sequence repeat
sequence either you read it from this
side three prime to five prime or 5 Prim
to three prime it gives us same
information for example let's take g a a
t t c c t t a a g now everyone read it
they GA AA GA AA same so this is a
palindromic sequence so they recognize
the pelic sequence very nice malum
another example it he was there in my
class so I remember it name right
Madam Madam yes any other example you
have Madam
madm clear so these are the palindromic
sequences now they cut each of the two
strands of a double helix so it if
restriction enzyme I will add over here
now this restriction enzyme will cut
here and it will cut here also
so both the Strand at cut at the both
the Strand second most important point
you have to note down at specific point
at their sugar phosphate backbone can be
asked in a one marker where does it cut
it cut at sugar phosphate
backbone clear now used in genetic
engineering for the recombinant DNA
molecules also called as molecular
because it cuts the molecule molecular
Caesar discovered in 1963 as discussed
earlier 72 May first recombinant DNA
molecule was formed all thanks to this
1963 because we discovered this
restriction
endonucleases now let's talk about the
fact I'll discuss this later first types
it has two type exonucleases
nucleotide from the
end now suppose this is a DNA I'll take
a Caesar and I'll cut it like
this cut it like this from the end so
this is termed as Exon nucleus if it cut
in between this is endon nucleus remove
nucleotide from the end of DNA make cut
at the specific position within the DNA
hind 2 was the first dition endon
nucleus which was
discovered done clear everyone okay now
splicing produce overhanging stretching
called as sticky ends which facilitate
the action of DNA liase now let's
understand this what am I talking about
here okay this is a DNA and this is
another DNA I want to attach both of
them see what happens is this is a
vector DNA Vector plasma DNA right and
here only linear fragment is shown not
the circular one just think now it is
having a sequence of GA TTC this is a
palindromic sequence now what will
happen the enzyme will come and enzyme
will cut it if I add enzyme enzyme will
come here we are talking about one
enzyme which is the Eco R1 that is
another one so Eco R1 will come and it
will cut
here it will cut here in between the G
and a where does it cut sugar phosphate
backbone sugar phosphate backbone
what I will get is see here we have a
double standard and then a overhanging
sticky ends overhanging sequence now
this overhanging sequence can easily
find the something which is
complimentary to it isn't it if they
will find in the medium some a a TS
there they can easily go and easily bind
so this is the characteristic feature we
always go with a sticky and type of
those which produce sticky and type of
restriction enzyme we press prefer to
use that we do not use the one which
produces the blunt end blunt end means
cut straight no we always use this
similarly the same type of thetion
enzyme will be used in the DNA isolation
so here same will be used same type of
sticky EDS will be produced now they are
complimentary to each other they can
fall in love with each other and what we
can get is a recombinant DNA so sticky
end one is you
used yes so always when you will be
doing biotechnology experiment in your
laboratory make sure at that particular
time you should use the same restriction
endon nucleus one while isolating the
DNA and second for the
vector okay
now let's talk about now tools of
biotechnology First Tool we have already
discussed that is the restriction endon
nucleus polymerase enzymes for
replication we require some liases we
require some Vector we require some host
organism where we want to clone is
clear now next uh let's talk about
vectors one example I have already given
you what is that that is a plasmid let's
talk about other example now first one
cloning Vector is a DNA segment that
replicate independent of the chromosome
and can be transferred between the host
what is the cloning Vector cloning
vectors are like Vehicles they will
carry your DNA whatever you want to give
them they will carry that and they will
transfer to a particular location they
are like a
Vehicles similarly here the examples are
given as plasmids and bacteriophage not
only the plasmid and bacterio we have an
example of the
back we have an example of yak
we have an example of TI
plasmid we have an example of
retrovirus
fade F mid we have an example of for
cosmids these are the various examples C
bacterio phase because their High copy
number per cell have a high copy number
of the genome within the bacterial cell
the bacterial FES they are also
used clear now one more
thing we talked about the hind two so
there are some other examples Also let's
talk about
them we have restriction uh other
restriction enzymes like Eco
R1 we have an example of hind
2 we have an example of hind
3 we have an example of bam
H1 bam
H1 pvu one we have an example of
pst1 too many examples are there but how
their naming was done let's have a look
if I talk about
E1 what is e what is e buddies e is
esta
e come from the
first genus first letter
esteria two comes from Ki two words from
Ki one word from genus two from Ki me
the species R come from The Strain R
strain one comes from the sequence of
isolation
sequence in which it is
isolated okay
clear so like this we have a various
example hemophilus influenza the uh what
was this this Amo liquifan is there so
many examples are there
aluan now vectors features of cloning
vectors there are two different features
of cloning Vector
yes cloning site so they should have a
cloning site they should have a cloning
site I'll show
you cloning site guys can you see can
you spot here any cloning site anyone
come on Can you spot some cloning sites
here in this plasmid this is a vector
this is an example this is artificially
synthesized uh vector by Boliver Rodrigo
who ask can you tell
me
rope not
rope cloning sites where can we
clone yes this is PBR 322 come
on no no no no
rope guys can you
see if restriction enzyme will come here
so here only the DNA will come and
insert no Sami
no if DNA will come over here these are
the cloning site if e R1 I'm using e R1
will come and cut here and DNA will come
at this position if I use clav one clav
one come and cut here I will insert the
DNA this location pv1 will cut here the
BAM H1 will cut
here isn't
it okay
now so few or single recognition site
for restriction enzymes are used these
are the cloning
sites is this
clear M Class 11th
ma
okay I'll teach you
mathematics we have classes of
mathematics also you can follow
them if I'll teach you mathematics then
you you will hate
mathematics okay isika now vors of
cloning genes in a plants and animals
for example plasmids of agrobacterium
tum retrovirus if you are using plants
if you have to do transf if you have to
do the transfer in Plants the DNA
transfer in Plants you will use the ti
plasmid of retr uh agrobacterium tuation
but if you have to use a animal if you
have to use a human make if you have to
do this in human or animal
anything then in that case you will use
the
retrovirus now next one origin of
replication or should have origin of
replication what is the origin of
replication origin of replication is
that place where the replication start
Ori
okay next is selectable mark Mar marker
so selectable markers are those marker
which helps in identifying the
transformants and non-
transformant transformants and non-
transformant so let's complete
this right
so now here let's have a
look now suppose now now listen very
carefully now suppose I have inserted a
gene over here which Gene is affected
ampicilin resistant so that means
transformant will not be ampicilin
resistant transformant will not be
ampicilin resistant if I'll use a bam H1
over here right tetracyclin resistance
Gene will be affected that means our
transformant our new synthesized
recombinant DNA will not be tetracycline
resistant is this point clear yes so
these are the selectable markers so
selectable markers how can we select on
the basis of the
first
selectable
markers selectable markers are important
in selection between the recombinant and
non-
recombinant and non
recombinant recombinant and non-
recomment now listen very carefully
if if p v
U1 we are
used PV U1 we have used if we have used
pv1 so pv1 if we have used then
meline resistance G being
disrupted this is disrupted if this is
disrupted then your transformant or the
recombinant
will not
be ampicilline
resistant
now what are these recombinant and wrong
recombinant means new combination that
means I have inserted DNA non-
recombinant means I have not inserted
the
DNA right recombinate I have inserted
the DNA I have not inserted the DNA this
is the difference between these two
okay clear now moving on to the next
similarly there's another way also by
producing colored colony
by
producing colored
Colony colored
Colony suppose here there is a enzyme
there is a
gene which code for
beta Galo
cides
beta galacto so let's say not
here let's say
here I have a gene Gene which code for
beta galactosidase
enzyme beta
galactosidase
enzyme beta galois enzy okay now listen
very carefully very very very
carefully
if if Sal one can you see Sal one enzyme
used enzyme
used
then
recombinant will not be able to
produce will not be able to
produce
beta
galactosides beta
galactosides right
now if I add chromogenic
substrate chromogenic
substrate no beta galto side is so White
colony White
colony
White
colony clear now suppose beta galoes is
there this beta gyas is there now when
beta gidas is there chromogenic
substrate when I add any substrate color
producing which is specific to Beta
galactosides
substrate I'll add with the beta
galoes
with beta galosy is produce a Blue
Colony up by looking at them now it's
like now it is like the major thing
is listen very
carefully now
listen I have a a solution I have a
solution right in that I have added
plasmid I have ADD added restriction
endon nucleus and I have added my Gene
of Interest also in all the plasmid my
DNA will not go and insert if my DNA
will insert that will be a recombinant
plasmid if my DNA will not insert that
will be a non-recombinant plasmid how
will I recognize whether this is a
recombinant plaset or non-recombinant
plaset first what will I do is in that
culture medium in that thing what will I
do I will add the chromogenic substrate
if they will produce the color so that
means they are non-recombinant if they
will not they will uh not produce the
color so that means the beta
galactosidase Gene is affected because
my Gene my Gene has been inserted here
at the salvan
position right is this point clear to
all of you yes come on tell
me come on come on tell
me come on
very
nice arnest AA this Ernest Hackle was
the one who introduced the term ecology
he's not a father he's not a
father humbold is a father he's not a
father okay just do not be confused
between Ernest Heckle he was the first
one who introduced the word
ecology this is a class 12th buddies one
shot going on for the board examination
here I'm not I'm sorry I'm not here I'm
teaching hemic cardates and any other
thing
clear
[Music]
Survival let's not focus here let's come
back okay now let's come back so these
are the two ways by which we can
recognize one by the selectable marker
and second by producing the chromogenic
substrate hope this points are clear
okay now moving on to the next
is competent hold first now let's talk
about the process of recombinant DNA
technology what is the actual process of
recombinant DNA technology let's have a
look now first thing what we are going
to do is isolation of genetic material
first we will isolate the genetic
material now listen very carefully I
have a cell it is having a DNA it is
having other substances also but I have
to isolate only DNA so for this what
will I do is I will use various enzymes
right if I'm using plant
cell plant cell to break the plant cell
I will use
cellules I will use cellules if I'm
using let's say
fungus fungus cell I will
use uh uh
kitenin if I'm using bacterial
cell bacterial cell I will use lysine
clear right I don't want my proteins
should be there because what I want is
only DNA protein will be digested by
protein
proteas I don't want RNA should be
there I will digest the RNA by
rnas what I will get is only DNA what I
will get is only DNA isn't it this is
what we want
next is I will get 2.2 M
DNA if I talk about human body 2.2 M
long DNA is there but I want only a
specific sequence so in that case I will
use enzyme which is restriction
endonuclease suppose
one because I know at this particular
location my Gene is there and beside
this Gene I have this restriction enzyme
position so I will use that restriction
enzyme now the next thing is I will
isolate and separate the DNA fragment
how am I going to isolate and separate
the DNA fragment I'm going to do that
with the help of a gel
electroforesis gel
electroforesis now listen again very
carefully what was I having I was having
2.2 m
DNA I isolated this in two
fragments how can I recognize that this
one is mine this is the one which I am
looking for how can I do that I will do
that with the help of a gel
electroforesis now what actually a gel
electroforesis is let's have a
look
gel
electroforesis
what is gel electroforesis gel
electroforesis is the process of
separation process
of
separation of DNA
fragments
DNA
fragments on the basis of
charge and
size what kind of charge is there what
kind of size is there on that basis I
will isolate them gel
electroforesis now what will I do see
gel
electroforesis now first thing is I will
use a agros
gel
I have this agrose
gel egg Rose gel now this egg Rose
gel we have a it's isolated from a wheat
agros wheat and from that we prepare a
gel right it is solid normally it's
available in the laboratory and it is
solid and we have to add a buffer and
accordingly we can set it we set this in
a this in this particular way that here
there are
Wells Wells we create Wells with the
help of a com just like that a normal
comb we use so for this we have another
comb so that create a well
well now what we do is we with the help
of a micro
pipet we insert our DNA
here we will insert our DNA here right
we will keep inserting the the DNA right
we will keep everything whatever we have
in a buffer
solution this is a buffer
solution
buffer inside there is a buffer and this
is
Electro for
ftic
unit
electrophoric unit right now next is we
are going to attach
this next is we are going to attach this
to
electricity e I'm labeling as
electricity right electricity is
attached you all know what is the charge
of
DNA what is the charge of
DNA DNA is negatively charged how how
can I say it is negatively charged
because of
phosphate because of phosphate it has
phosphate because of phosphate it is
negatively charged and as it is having
phosphate no stone gives histones to we
have removed now some hisone we have
already removed you remember we added
prot
proteos yes for the
digestion
no
DNA is negatively charged so here the
positive terminal is attached here
negative terminal is attached in this
way now DNA being the negatively charged
DNA will
move DNA will
move DNA will move okay now as it will
be visible it will be quite evident
suppose our fragment is like this this
is a one which we uh suppose this is
this is a uh this is the gel right run
is there everything is there now what we
are going to do is we step number two is
we will take
gel whole gel
and place it
in
UV
transilluminator UV trans
illuminator
ultraviolet transilluminator right we
will add a you know here we add a Dye
also we add while this making the this
we add dye also that is ethidium
bromide ethidium bromide
etbr so as you will place under the UV
trans
Illuminator orange deep
orange bands will be
visible
deep orange bands will be visible and if
you look at these bands if you look at
those bands what will you
see that your DNA is there right you
will recognize that our fragment is
there let's see it will be visible now
next step is Step number four
illusion we will
cut
specific
DNA
fragment we will cut DNA
fragment or DNA uh you know the
gel we will cut the gel
now
specific cut
specific
gel
where
required DNA fragment is
present required DNA fragment is
present done so this is termed as gel
electr fores and these are the
illusion now moving on to the next is
now done now we got our
DNA we got our DNA a single fragment I
got now without single fragment I cannot
proceed with the whole experiment is it
is that possible to proceed with that
experiment no right so what we are going
to do is we will amplify the gene of
Interest we will amplify the gene of
Interest
now for
amplification
of gene of
interest for amplification Gene of
Interest we use a machine which is
termed as PC
R what we use is we use a machine which
is a
PCR which
is
polymerase
Chain
Reaction polymerase Chain Reaction
polymerase chain reaction was discovered
by car
mulus now
now this polymerase Chain Reaction
amplify the DNA if I have one DNA
fragment now this polymer G one they
will amplify
it and the rate of
amplification
amplification is like 2 ra to power
n where n is the number of
Cycles number of Cycles it is a number
of Cycles clear number of Cycles if you
run 30 Cycles then that means 2 to^ 30
This Is How They will further amplify in
this way they will amplify done clear
now here what we use is a append off
tube so we have a append off tube like
this
append off tube right in this endof tube
we add some
substances we add the
ntps we add these are the required
substances we add
dntp we will add the gene of
interest interest which we want to
amplify right we will add mg2+
ion we will add tar
polymerase given in your
ncrt T polymerase is that polymer
polymerase enzymes they are used for the
making the copy of a DNA clear so this T
polymerase is the one which is isolated
from thermos
aquaticus thermas
aquaticus
isolated from thermos
aquaticus which is found in Spring hot
spring found in Hot
Springs right because they are found in
hot spring and if you increase a
temperature also of this machine nothing
will happen to this polymerase so they
are thero stable what they are is they
are thero stable T polymerase added
clear dntps we have also added okay
clear everyone we will add
oligonucleotide primers also some common
oligo
nucleotide
primers these are the materials you have
to collect before starting the machine
of a polymerase Chain Reaction now let's
talk about the
steps
steps of
PCR there are three steps in which your
PCR machine works so first step is the
denaturation in the denaturation step
temperature increases
to 95 around 95 C so it is like you
have the end off you have added
everything now you will place that in
the PCR machine so in the first step it
will increase the temperature that is a
denaturation
clear yes Arya clear Arya Mishra yes yes
yes yes great great great okay we will
increase the temperature to 92 2 to 95
C it depends ver be it depends on the CG
content right how many C and G are there
so it depend on
that now this is a DNA
strand which are having which are
hydrogen bonded to each other five Prime
to three
Prime 3 Prime to five
Prime right as you will increase the
temperature now what will happen there
will be
separation
the
types
here this is five Prime this is 3 Prime
five Prime 3 Prime they are separated
separated no love at all temperature is
increased step number two if you'll say
m it is 92 cus written you can use the
word 92 also it depends actually I'm
telling you for the CG
content yeah second one
analing second step is
analing now what is this unhealing
unhealing means to
stick unhealing means to stick now what
will happen here these are the two
strands right five Prime to 3 Prime
right three prime to five Prime right
now what will happen olon nucleotide
primer they will come and they will
attach over
here 5 Prime 3
Prime they will come and they will
attach over here analing of
oligonucletide
primer small nucleotide primer five
Prime to 3 Prime they will provide
overhanging three prime o group so
here temperature comes down 50 to 55
C degree celsius the temperature will
increase clear and because of this they
will unal second step analing is clear
moving on to the third step step number
three step number three is
extension or
polymerization extension or
polymerization clear now what will
happen let's draw this
again
now same same I have drawn again okay
now what will happen buddies now the
polymerase which polymerase the tar
polymerase will come and T polymerase
will keep on adding the oligonucleotide
in this
direction right oligonucleotide so it is
like I'm writing here T
polymerase will
add
oligonucleotide primer sorry
dnps d n TPS in the presence of
magnesium ion that's it and here the
temperature is what here the temperature
is
almost here the temperature is almost
what around
72 C
now the temperature will increase so in
one cycle what we will get is complete
synthesis see it will be now completely
synthesized completely synthesized isn't
it done done done done completely
synthesized now one strand is converted
into two strand one cycle one multip by
two we'll get
twos is this point clear to everyone so
this is a
PCR moving on to the next is insertion
of DN D into the host cell there are
various Ways by which we can insert the
DNA into the host cell let's talk about
it okay insertion of DNA into the host
cell into
host
cell insertion of the DNA into the host
cell how can we insert the DNA into the
host cell let's have a look DNA can be
inserted into the host cell by different
ways one of the treatment is calcium
chloride guys have you heard of it come
on tell me have you heard of it the
calcium carbonate treatment the um
electric treatment which we use do you
are are you guys aware of
it come on come on come on then I'll
explain
you so I'll write
down
calcium
CA CO3
treatment
right now what we do is we treat the
cell right we take the
cell plus foreign DNA which we have to
insert
right both of them right both of them
and we will add calcium
chloride and because of the calcium
chloride because once we add the calcium
chloride calcium chloride increases the
absorption
of DNA by host
cell host cell see actually uh DNA
cannot go directly because DNA is what
you know lipid DNA is
hydrophilic we all know right this DNA
is what DNA is hydrophilic
and if I talk about the
membrane cell
membrane cell membrane is
hydrophobic so they cannot you know then
they cannot fall in love with each other
so how can we make them fall in love
with each other first add calcium
carbonate let's talk about the step
number two or the second second method
that is a heat shock this is the most
torturous method I feel
heat
shock method so in a heat shock method
what we do is we first of all heat the
mixture we
heat we then place it
on
ice then again we
Heat this is the one which we do heat
shock isn't it torturous just imagine
you facing this
situation so here what we do
is okay so here buddies what we do is
because of this this create transient
Poe
transient
force on cell and when they create
transient Poe on Cell easy absorption
can
occur is this point clear to all of
you so heat doesn't mean that we are
giving 800 cus it is very normal means
42 C then ice and again 42
C clear now there are other ways Also
let's talk about
them other
ways
biolistic
biolistic biolistic is also termed as
Gene
gun
so here this is used in the case of
plants suppose we have to do
transformation in Plants this is for
transformation in
Plants transformation in Plants right in
this case what we will use is we will
use gold or
tungsten
qued
bullets right and on that we add DNA
also they have DNA
also and then we bombard it on the plant
cell it is possible to do this on the
plant cell right plant cell
yes this is bombarded now on the next
method micro
injection small injection let's take a
DNA micro
injection let's insert the DNA with the
help of a injection this I'm not
explaining in detail now the last one is
the disarmed
pathogen is hared
Vector or pathogen for example
when we have to we can use retrovirus
disarmed again I'm saying
retrovirus when we have to use this in
case of plants oh
sorry
animals TI plasmid you know TI plasmid
cause Crown Gall disease in plant but
disarmed one when we use we can do the
transformation in case of plants right
but make sure it should be dis
harmed yes clear to all my
buddies okay so let's move
further now next next let's look at the
next Point insertion is done obtaining
the foreign Gene product obtaining the
foreign Gene product good aush CH now
let's have a look for obtaining a gene
product what we use we use these
bioreactors there are two type of bi bio
reactor this is a simple stirred tank
bioreactor and the second is a spared
tank bioreactor SED tank bioreactor is
like there will be a stirer there will
be a foam breaker there will be imperor
who keeps on impelling we add culture
brow we add our cell we have to culture
we maintain the temperature also Steam
for sterilization we maintain the pH
also everything we maintain and at
Thousand level capacity we can easily
culture
on the another hand we have the sped
tank bio reactors also both have a same
function but they are of different types
clear there are two type of culture
system
culture can be done in two different
ways one is a continuous
culture continuous culture and second is
a discontinuous
culture in the continuous one continuous
one what we do is continuous see there
are two different ways
uh we will add some
yes so what we will do is it's like we
will add something right we will CL it's
just like a cooker right it's just like
a discontinuous we have a cooker we've
added all the vegetables now we will
close the cooker we will open only
cooker once when our food is
prepared now another one in the
discontinuous one one what we do uh in
the another one sorry what we use is we
keep on adding the vegetables from
outside we keep on adding the you know
the culture medium from outside and we
will keep on obtaining the product from
Lower
Side done clear okay so these are the
two ways okay guys is this clear maximum
level and then once we will get the cell
lots of cells we can easily isolate them
with the help of a process which is
Downstream
processing so Downstream
processing so continuous means
continuously we are adding substances
from outside and From Below we are
extracting the product so there are
chances of contamination at that time
discontinuous means once we have closed
the cooker once we have closed this
thing now we cannot add anything from
outside yes great so next isolation of
product can be done by Downstream
processing so Downstream processing may
involve the ultra centrifugation uh
various ways
of in fact chromatography is also one of
the ways by which we can isolate the
desired
product okay buddies so so so so with
this we have completed your this chapter
also what is this that is a
biotechnology principle and
processes
right six hours okay four chapters down
good good good now we have to move on to
the next chapter that is a biot
technology and its
application right can we start this
chapter bi technology and its
applications come on tell
me
yes biotechnology application is
comparative ly uh you can say a smaller
chapter it's not that big one it's a
small as compared to the uh you know the
other
chapters so let's do this biot
technology
application so you know the
biotechnology biotechnology is we are
modifying it we are using genetic
engineering and we are using
bioprocesses yes then previously other
chapters whatever is there now
application of biotechnology there are
various applications of biotechnology
one is Therapeutics diagnostic
genetically modified crop for
agriculture processed food bior
remediation waste material removal and
the energy
production these are the different
ways right
okay three critical areas of the
research in biotechnology are see
biotechnology what we are doing is we
are modifying something right we are
modifying something here it provide the
best Catalyst in the form of improved
organism usually a microbes or the pure
enzyme what see biotechnology may we are
modifying any organism so what we need
is that organism providing the best
catalyst is that thing on which we can
work in the form of improved organism
that improved organism usually a microb
or a pure enzyme that thing is required
creating a optimal condition through
engineering for a catalyst to act
creating particular environmental
condition that comes under the
bioprocessing if you remember the
previous chapter Downstream processing
technology to purify the protein or
organic compound the first thing is we
will modify something or whatever is
there whatever is already available we
will use them then we will culture it as
given in the second Point third thing is
Downstream processing means we will
isolate the product
whatever organic compounds are there we
will isolate them now biotechnology
application in agriculture there are
various uh you know applications are
there
see with increasing population like we
have read in the chapter number two of
zoology which is reproductive Health
there was a major issue and that major
issue was related to the
population increasing you know
population in millions it was difficult
to feed those number of individuals so
what we did we tried to increase the
agriculture right by that only we can
provide them food so we started using
some chemicals we started using some
chemicals like insecticide and
pesticides and we when we started using
those insecticide and pesticide what
happened production increased and
because of that insecticide and
pesticide they had some residual effects
also though this lead to the Green
Revolution also which later we realized
that these pesticides are not good for
our body second we moved on to the
organic agriculture organic agriculture
organic agriculture now aays we are
moving towards organic foods organic
pses organic vegetables where the no
where zero pesticides zero insecticides
are
used we moving but overall production is
less in this case now next is
genetically engineered cobbed based
agriculture now this is the one which we
are targeting today that is the
genetically engineered cred based
agriculture now what this genetically
engineered crop-based agriculture is
let's have a look we have made the crops
more tolerant to abiotic stress now
let's have a look either it is a drought
or it is a cold it is a salt or a heat
nothing can happen to our plant because
our plant are
resistant next reduced reli Reliance on
the chemical pesticide
we don't want pesticides who wants
pesticide we don't want pesticides help
to reduce post Harvest loss when we are
storing those food in bulk nothing can
happen to them next increased efficiency
of mineral usage by plants more and more
plants are extracting nutrients from the
soil even when they are at dwarf prod
you know when when they are small and
high they're producing fruit how it is
possible bi technology
only
enhanced nutritional value for example
today we have produced golden rice
golden rice means doesn't means it is
golden it's made up of gold it doesn't
mean that golden rice means it is yellow
color rice which is rich in vitamin A
okay so with the help of all these
things today all biotechnology we have
made these things possible so everybody
my cbsc aspirant keep these points in
your
mind okay
now
what we have prepared so far let's talk
about it have you how many of you have
heard of B
cotton come
on how many of you heard of BT
cotton today we have prepared a cotton
plant whose name is BT cotton we have
modified it we have modified a cotton
how we have modified a cotton let's have
a look there's a
bacteria
whose name was bassilus
tranis bassilus
tranis
ganis basil tranis what's the name
bassilus
tranis bassilus Tanis produce a protein
what do they do is they produce
protein and the name of that protein is
cry
protein name of that protein is cry
protein right they produce
it because
because they are having a gene which is
a cry
gene they have a gene whose name is cry
cry not that Rona cry this is name is
cry only so they produce a protein which
is is a cry protein and whenever insect
feed on
it
insect
feed on
it they die that means not bacteria the
insect
die why because it cause perforation in
gut it cause perforation in
gut right same problem was there in the
cotton cotton infestation cotton people
the uh you know Farmers they were facing
some problem in Cotton they say either
it is
lepidopteran or it is colop
Terin
or it is
dip we are tired of all
three they cause huge
infestation yes they cause huge
infestation leibo Teran comes your
butterfly Ms Etc in the colop Teran we
have is a beetle in the dipin we have is
a flies and
mosquitoes
okay
lepidopteran call of Teran and
dptr clear
cotton now scientist thought let's take
a use of this bassilus through gianis
then what scientist did scientist
isolated
Crye
Cene and they inserted into the
cotton right Ken into the cotton now the
cotton cotton becomes BT
cotton
it becomes py cotton now lepido Teran if
you'll come we will kill you lepido
Teran if cotan will come we will kill
you kopan if any on of uh you know if
dipan will come they will kill the
dipan so these Crye has some
name Cry 1
AC and Cry 2 2
AB yes these are the name of Gene when
the scientist they go deep into this
they realized Cry 1 AC and Cry 2 AB they
are effective against cotton
ball cotton
ballom which cause huge
loss which cause huge loss as far as
because India is one of the greater
greatest producer user of the cotton now
cry
1ab cry
1ab is used to
control cotton
budw corn borer
sorry quter corn
Boral cter corn borer cryan AC AB cotton
bwom cryan AB cotton corn borer so this
is a what B cotton today we have with us
not only the B cotton today we have a b
tomato B potato B bringel BT soy bean BT
chicken pea Pig pigeon pea all of them
today we have with us so this is the BT
cotton
now moving on to the next is neod
resistant tobacco plant yes guys so
today we have created nematode resistant
tobacco or plant also so there is a
nematode whose name is mogy in
cognita
mogy
incognita it is a
nematode it's a
nematode it cause huge infestation as
far as your tobacco is considered
tobacco
infestation right tobacco infestation so
scientists they were very worried are
how to solve this problem what to do
what not to do so they used one
technique which is RNA
interference
RNA
interference they use a technique which
is I interference RNA I that is RNA
interference so RNA interference is all
about prevention of the
infestation right RNA interference is a
Cellular
Defense Cellular
Defense in you carotic
organisms organ
isms now let's have a quick look how
this has been
done now what scientists
did okay they took a
DNA right
DNA
of
mogy
incognit and this DNA was vital this was
vital for them like if something will
happen to this Gene in their body they
will not be able to survive so they took
this they insert this into the plant
which plant obviously this one tobacco
plant tobacco
plant they inserted this into the
tobacco plant which technique did they
use definitely the ti
plasmid
now here they used a mechanism what they
did he normally if I talk about a DNA
only one strand replicate here both the
strands they replicated and they produce
the RNA sense Strand and anti- sense
strand this is the sense
RNA both strands they produce the
RNA this is the anti sense
RNA
anti sense RNA as DNA was complimentary
to each other so they will also be
complimentary to each other so what will
happen both will form double standard
RNA double standed
RNA then it forms small small mate was
being
cut right some other protein they also
joined them
and what they form is risk
complex risk
complex what is
this RNA induced silencing
complex RNA induced silencing complex
risk complex
clear now this risk right is there in a
plant now once nematode will come and
nematode will try to feed on this now
this risk
will
silence the vital
DNA of
mogy incognita
when
the
neod feed on
plant feed on plant is this point
clear yes or no come on tell
me still we have a long way to
go
come on come on tell
me okay not only this buddies we have
also created some other things what are
those we have also
created flavor saver variety of
tomato
where we have
silenced where we have silenced
poly
galao
urones
enzyme poly galacto urase enzyme we have
silence the poly galao urase enzyme and
this this particular enzyme is
responsible for
softening and if this enzyme is not
there there will no softening so this
helps in increasing the shelf life of
tomato clear flavor saver variety of
tomato now moving on to the next is what
we have created is golden rice
golden rice so golden rice is that Rice
which is rich in vitamin
A right where we have introduced Gene
of gene of beta
carotene which is a precursor of vitamin
A and that helps in curing the night
blindness
okay here
everyone yes or no come on tell
me yes okay now let's move towards the
application in medicine in medicines
also we have lot of applications the
first is uh only one thing is there in
your syllabus the first one is insulin
yes so we have created insulin Also
let's have a look so we have created
recombinate
insulin insulin so what is the function
of insulin what does insulin do in our
body insulin helps in reducing the blood
glucose
level right insulin reduces the blood
glucose level many people they suffer
from diabetes melittis not insipidus
diabetes Melius people they do not have
you know you know they they have a high
blood sugar level so they take insulin
from
outside is that clear so initially this
insulin was taken from a slaughtered
pigs cattles Etc but today we have
prepared recombinant insulin with us
which was prepared in 1983 by a company
named
Elly right by
Elly
in
see insulin in our body is produced in
the form of a pro- insulin this is a
pro-
insulin right it is having different
chains this is a a chain
this is a b chain right a chain and B
chain let's label
this so this is a a
chain this is a c chain white in color
and pink one is a b chain these are the
different
chains right this is a pro insulin this
is how it is produced in our body so how
do the remain in this particular you
know this one because they are having
dulfi bonds like this because of the
dulfi bond because of dulfi bond they
remain like this now when this Pro
insulin is converted into an mature
insulin what we have
is this and this pink
one right and dulfi Bonds are
there
right a chain is made up of this one is
made up of 21 amino acid and this one is
made up of 30 amino acids it's a
polypeptide chain C now what scientist
did scientist took a CH
Gene a CH
Gene inserted into a
vector whose Vector name was
PBR
322 we have inserted
this Vector will transfer this into the
eal equoli may we transferred it and now
we have a we have
isolated
a
polypeptide so they did it
separately similarly scientists took B
chain
gene they isolated and they took this
and they inserted this into the vector
which is PBR
322 then they inserted into another eoli
cultured that eoli and then they
isolated
isolated B
polypeptide
and when they did
that later on they combined both of them
and today we have is recombinant insulin
with us what do we have is the
recombinant insulin with us so we have
created recombinant insulin here
here
okay
yes now next is gene therapy
y gene therapy gene therapy now this is
another application of biotechnology in
gene what is this gene therapy that
means we are therapizing the gene that
means we are replacing the faulty Gene
with a new Gene suppose in an human
suppose in a one particular person that
a one gene is not working what we will
do we will replace the faulty Gene so
gene therapy means What gene therapy
means sorry replace
the faulty
Gene faulty
gene
into oh sorry
with New
Gen New Gen so what we have done so far
see gene
therapy so there was a person if there
was a girl she was just a six year old
he was suffering from
skid skid
patient skid patient what is a skid skid
is
severe
combined immuno
deficiency severe combined immuno
deficiency skid patient right these
patient their immune system or their
immune is compromised they do not have a
yes aish so they have a immuno
compromised clear why because they are
not able to produce
adene no adenosine deaminase
enzyme
adenosine dmas
enzyme adenosine Damas enzyme is not
there when Ada is not there in them
because ad gen is
absent Ada Gene is absent and when I'm
saying Ada Gene is absent no enzyme and
this enzyme has a role and what is that
role so this help in
maturation of
WBC clear unti yes okay now what we have
done is we took out wbcs of the
patient so we took
out WBC of
patient
right we
inserted ad
Gene ad Gene in them we inserted ad Gene
in
them how with the help of
retrovirus disarmed retrovirus we took
and we have inserted this into it now
the next thing is reintroduction
of reintroduction
of
WBC into patient body now patient body
will start secreting ad
enzyme they will start secreting the ad
enzyme now ad enzyme is there but this
WBC has some life so one has to go
through this procedure again and again
so there are various therapies by which
we can treat one is a gene therapy it's
not a complete
treatment but Q means to say one has to
go through this again and again if this
could have been done at the embryo level
that would have been a permanent cure
but this is not a
permanent right buddies everybody is
this point
clear
okay okay so let's move on to the next
molecular
Diagnostics molecular
diagnostic yes so hope preparation is at
full
swing
right now moving on to the next is
moleular diagnostic molecular diagnostic
these are the you know we have
biotechnologies these are the ways of of
biotechnology and those biotechnology
things helps in the diagnosis of various
diseases either it is you know your
cancer cancer detection can be possible
that I'll show you how even when there
is any genetic disorder that is also
detected with the help of this in a
conventional method when we have is a
blood test uh urine test tool test in
that case the uh you know the disease
can be detected when symptoms are there
in the blood and already symptoms are
there but these are the ways by which
pre sympto symptomatic that means before
symptom also we can easily detect
whether person is suffering from any
disease or not even cancer can be
detected even whether person is HIV
positive or not that can also be
detected any genetic disorder is there
or not that can also be detected by this
that I'll show you so here the molecular
diagnostic three different procedure are
there one is a
PCR
okay so one is a
PCR PCR how does a PCR function that
I've discussed with you isn't it
polymerase chain reaction that is used
for
amplification the first thing is with
this we can identify any genetic
disorder
identify
any genetic disorder very much possible
right any change in the gene sequence
any change is there in the gene sequence
we can easily detect them isn't it yes
now the next thing is HIV even when
there is low concentration of pathogen
can be easily
detected low concentration
of
pathogen can also be
detected
be detected for example you remember uh
covid test rtpcr was used so that is
also
same yes rooster extension HIV yes HIV
can also be detected asish rooster yes
that can also be
detected now next thing is mutation can
be
detected
mutation can can be
in
cancer
suspected
patients cancer suspected patient
PCR clear because whenever any change is
there yes rooster I'm teaching for the
boards it's for boards Marathon
on
now now next one second one is auto
radiography second
Point
Auto
radio
graphy Auto radiography now what is a
auto radiography in Auto radiography we
use radio labeled probe that is a sing
standard DNA or RNA so what we use is we
use radio
labeled single
stranded
probe and this can be a DNA or RNA
always remember students they come to me
and they say ma'am it is only DNA no it
can be a DNA and RNA now just imagine
buddies if your DNA is Radio
labeled
right if it is Dian is Radio labeled it
can easily bind to
complimentary can bind
to
complimentary
DNA right it can go go and B to the
compliment DNA then it will show the
radioactivity
radioactivity visible and it if doesn't
bind so that means if mutation is
there it doesn't bind that means some
mutation is there in our DNA that is the
reason it is not able to
bind so what is the use use is any
disease can be detected if this is
because of mutation in the DNA is this
point clear now moving on to the last
one that is the
Elisa third
one third
one is
Elisa what is Elisa Elisa is
enzyme
linked
immuno
sorbent
saay enzyme linked immunosorbent essay
Eliza enzyme linked immunosorbent
essay
okay okay now what is this enzyme linked
immunosorbent essay now here this is
based on antigen antibody
reaction
antibody
reaction now suppose suppose in
someone's body any suppose an any
antigen is there right let's say in X
body some HIV positive antigen virus is
there anything any bacteria is there
something is there some antigen is there
now what will happen we will add we will
take a sample blood sample we will add
antibodies and those antibodies they
will bind to the antigen they will go
and they will bind to the antigen clear
as they will bind to the antigen so
antigen antibody complex will be there
extra we will wash it then we will use
another antibodies and that antibody
will be radio labeled antibody will come
and antibody will bind to the antibody
again so there will be antibody antibody
and antigen complex that antibody will
start eliminating radioactivity as as
they will radiate the radioactivity that
means the positive that means that
particular antigen is
there done clear so that is Elisa it is
based on antigen antibody
reaction so moving on to the next is
transgenic animal biotechnology because
of the biotechnology today we have
created transgenic animals also now
there are animals whose genome has been
altered by introduction of a foreign
Gene by manipulation that is a
transgenic animal so there's a
difference cloning is something else
this is a
transgenic right yes Rose
huh now transgenic rat rabbit pigs sheep
cows fish over
95% of transgenic animals are the
mice okay so why we have created mice
let's have a
look
okay yeah we were here here okay let's
see have a look trenic animals today we
have created so that we can study the
normal physiology and development
suppose I want to study a gene right and
I have introduced suppose some X Gene is
there in human body and I want to study
that Gene how does that Gene function
how does it is transcribe and translate
I will insert that Gene into a rise and
I can easily study it into a mice I
cannot study into a human body very
difficult but majorly it is done in case
of a mice nice to study the contribution
of gene in development of disease clear
next is biological product today human
protein alpha 1 antipin used to treat
micma product treatment of Phile Ketone
Uria and cystic fibrosis also we have
created see all thanks to biotechnology
1997 Rosie the first transgenic
cow I'm saying the transgenic cow I'm
not saying the cloned cloned is
something else this is transgenic so
that means we have we have inserted a
gene from outside we have uh this is the
transited cow which produces milk which
is rich in protein that is 2.4 G per
liter and that is Alpha lactal albumine
and it's nutritionally more balanced
product for human babies than a natural
cow milk definitely there is no
alternative to a mother's milk but this
milk is better for babies as compared to
a normal milk I'm not saying the
mother's milk mother's milk is best and
then we have is this one vaccine safety
you all know vaccine trials and
everything happens on mice and other
animals chemical safing whatever
chemicals whatever you know the face
product whatever Cosmetics we use they
are always tried and tested on
animals
okay now
ethical issues problem of unpredictable
result genetic modification may cause
unpredictable result when such organism
are introduced into the ecosystem
because they're natural Predators they
are absent that is a reason Indian
government has set up an organization
which is a GAC genetic engineering
approval committee which makes decision
regarding at what extent modification
can be done make decision about the
validity of the GM research and the
safety of GM organism for public
services clear now
yes problems of patent unpredictable
result may be observed by introduction
of these organism in
ecosystem many indigenous varieties are
claimed by the mnc's as their own
invention that is also one of the
problem here comes an example of a
Basmati you all know Indian literature
is full of Basmati because of their
Aroma we are using Basmati from ages but
what this country did let's have a look
now there's an American company American
company patented the Basmati now what
they did is they took just a Indian
variety normal Indian variety basmati
rice and they crossed it with the semi
dwarf varieties and they said K this
belongs to us which was a biggest issue
so now it has been rectified similarly
other medicine usage are also there such
as neem as a directa indicia the
turmeric use which we are using from the
a ages and their antibacterial
properties biopiracy what is biopiracy
if this this can be asked one marker
Buddies the use of Bio Resources by MNC
and other organization without proper
authorization suppose you have
discovered something either it is a
process or anything and
buddies without proper authorization
from the countries then this is is
termed as biopiracy Indian Parliament
has recently introduced a second
amendment of The Indian patent Bill to
deal with such
issues yes so soon if you will patent
something you will get you know that
thingy no one can use it until unless
you give them author authoritie should
have that
Authority or they should give you some
compensatory payment okay now butes we
have to start another chapter which is a
human health and diseases so before
starting this chapter let's take a break
small break I need uh let's take a break
of
for 20 minutes right we'll be back in a
moment and then we will start this
chapter this chapter is little bit big
by the time be here I'll be back in a
moment okay let's take a 20 minutes
break I will start the timers now uh we
can start early also I will let you guys
know so let's start let's take a break
for some time I actually need
it
okay no still one chapter is left which
is human health and diseases we will do
that okay just be here buddies don't go
anywhere
so hello hello hello guys am I
audible hello hello hello am I Audible
and visible is everything fine please
let me
know so we are going to start the last
chapter that is a human health and
diseases this chapter is bit L
lengthy am I audible
yes one second
check hello hello hello hello
hello hello hello
hello hello guys am I audible please let
me know everything is fine hello hello
hello yes good good good good yes okay
so we are going to start the chapter
which is human health and diseases the
last chapter bit lengthy I won't say
it's much lengthy it is bit leny but we
will also complete the chapter we will
take another 2 hours or so and in that
we will complete this okay so get ready
all of you with your notes you all
should have your notes The Notebook with
you the pen and pencil because right now
this chapter is also about the diagram
so yes the content is there along with
the diagrams are also there like
antibody diagram the life cycle of HIV
that is also important okay come on
share with your friends and call
everyone class has been started after
after the break so let's
start now what is health health is
defined as the state of complete
physical mental and social well-being
this is a general definition given by
the wh you should not only be uh you
know there should not be any disease so
along with the disease you should not be
uh you know mentally uh unhealthy your
your thinking should be good you should
be all positive because nowadays uh you
all know we are more aware of the you
know mental
disorders we should also think about
what uh actually goes in our mind either
we are positive towards other or we are
very negative or what we think that also
matters now so we should be mentally
healthy and as well as the people who
arounds you they should be good they
should be helpful now health is being
affected by the genetic disorder there
are various disorder by which health is
affected like lifestyle also affects it
whatever you eat that also affect it
wide range of organisms like bacteria
fungus virus protozoa helth also affects
our
life isn't it
yes okay if you have any doubt guys you
can ask in the comment section keep
asking I looking at the comment sections
also okay now let's talk about the types
of diseases we classify diseases into
this category the first one is a
communicate or the communicable diseases
these are the infectious diseases which
spread from one person to another and
the second one is a non-communicable
diseases which doesn't spread from one
person to another now one communicable
or non-communicable diseases are those
diseases which develop after birth so
they're not congenital these are the
acquired one which we acquire when we
are Expos when we are exposed to
different uh you know bacteria fungus
pathogen we develop these diseases
sometime we spread those diseases from
one person to another sometime we not do
not they're caused by the virus bacteria
fungus protozoa and
helmin right they are caused by the
deficiency of nutrient hormone
degeneration of body organs allergy uh
cancer Etc comes under this category if
I talk about the congenital congenital
are those which are present from
birth present from birth
present from birth right now these are
genetic disorders genetic disorders are
the one which are present from birth now
anatomical or physiological
abnormalities present from birth can be
caused by single demodulation for
example hemophilia color blindness Phile
Kone UA sickle cell anemia chromosomal
libration like down syndrome ROM of
chromosome number 21 the Turner syndrome
clein filter syndrome environmental
factors like hair clip and the cleft
pallet so they come under this category
yes
okay any doubt why are you guys
fighting yes definitely nobama I can
repeat that again you mean to say this
point so here those diseases are those
these are the diseases which doesn't
which are congenital that means these
are the one which are present from birth
right caused by the single demodulation
that means any changes in the chromosome
suppose there's a triome of chromosome
number 21 what do we call that that is
uh Down syndrome Turner syndrome EXO
color blindness the you know hemophilia
Phile ketonuria sickle cell anemia comes
under this category and then we have is
disol okay okay no no Bama clear okay
okay so let's start further now diseases
now diseases in your chapter is there
some diseases are in detail some are not
detailed so I have made a chart of it
and with the help of a chart let's
understand everything first let's talk
about typhoid so
typhoid ctive agent is salmona Ty muum
what is that that is the
salbon one
second
okay so that is the salmonella triim
muum so salmonella trium this is the
inhabitant of the small intestine how
does it spread whenever we use outside
food during especially during the you
know the rainy season when the moisture
is high temperature is high at that
particular time typhoid cases comes now
how does it enter it generally enter
through the small intestine through the
food water contaminated with bacteria
and migrate to other organs through the
blood they can cause perforation in the
small intestine due to which person
feels pain lot of pain right the fever
here goes very high a person feel high
fever chills right so classic case you
all know the Mary Malon which who was a
cook by profession he was having this
problem he was continuously cooking and
he was spreading the disease also so the
symptom is sustained high fever 39 to
40 cus weakness stomach pain
constipation headache loss of appetite
intestinal perforation and it also keys
to
death clear one of the most important
question which can be asked from this
topic is the uh you know
uh the test the Vidal test yes Vidal
test it measure the utenation of
antibodies against ho antigen of the
sanilla tyy this is if vial test we are
talking about that means we are talking
about the Sala tyum or the Ty typhoid
okay okay okie dokie so let's start so
this is a typhoid now let's move on to
the next one next disease we have is
pneumonia pneumonia so the pneumonia
basically it affects the alali of the
lung so person is not able to breathe
properly here the costive agent is
streptococus neumonia hemophilus influen
both of them you have to learn because
given your ncrt Alvi it affects the Alvi
of the lungs what is this bacterial yes
this is a bacterial disorder now
inhaling the droplet aerosole released
by The Infected person by sharing
glasses utensil of affected person if
one person is affected affecting and
another person can also have this if
they share the utensils needles
Etc here what happens is these are the
alval alval they are filled with fluid
due to to which the oxygen the gases
transport area reduces person feel
suffocated they're not able to breathe
properly so Alvi filled with fluid
leading to prop uh problems related to
respiration here fever chills scff and
headache severe cases the nails and the
skin turns blue lips
finger grayish to bluish in color why
because of lack of oxygen because of
less oxygen isn't it now can be detected
by the blood test x-ray plus pulse
oximetry and the sputum test next is
dentry dentry by the shagala species it
affects the intestine whenever we
consume outside food so we can suffer
from uh dentry now your exams are near
here your apping for your board
examination then you'll be going for
your neat
examination so make sure you oid outside
food for at least this period of time
now contaminated food you know the
temperature also if I talk about if
you're from the north India temperature
is going high so please take care of
yourself right now also like it goes to
30 C here even in the month of March
which is really high now pain in the
abdomen diarrhea IND digestion nausea
vomiting blood in the loose watery sto
loses and the examination of stool one
can detect dentry Shela species now next
is
plague Yia Pesce now plague whenever
plague comes in our mind we say it is
because of
rat it is because of yenia pestis they
spread by the fleas rat
fleas and where do they live they live
in our blood and lymph now fever
headache weakness and this was a reason
for Black Death just like that of a
Corona pandemic here that was also also
a pandemic the black death now bacterium
fluid from the lymph node and the blood
of the sputum gives us an idea whether
person is suffering from this or
not dpia corny bacterium dpia mucus
membrane of nose throat tonsils direct
contact with infected person th throat
fever enlarged lymph node
test done next is whooping calf oh Peru
say pela pertusis respiratory tract it
affect it spread from one person to
another if one person is affected then
another person can also get it if you
cuff in front of him now next is severe
cuffing characteristics loud woofing
cuff nose and the throat test and the
blood test can gives us the whooping
cuff
yeah pusis bellaa pusis moving on to the
next is
tuberculosis Micco bacterium
tuberculosis is lungs it affects the
lungs pum test even in the X-ray we can
detect whether the person is suffering
from you will find some patches there
right cuff Blood also comes out so if
you have cuff it is considered here um
if you have cuff more than one week one
should go to the doctor right so yes the
treatment is there cuff blood comes in
sputum chest pain loss of weight mon
test at the blood test syphilis syphilis
to already we have done right in STDs so
syphilis tripona padam goria neria gonor
all these are the bacteria these are the
sexual contact detail is being given
this will be important for the another
chapter
also okay now let's talk about the viral
diseases these were the bacterial
diseases
tuberculosis there was syphilis there
was goria there was whooping cuff there
were a lot of diseases right now let's
talk about the viral disease the viral
diseases first comes is the common cold
so common cold is that disease which we
all suffer from every now and then and
you know this is because of the Rhino
virus how does it spread definitely
droplet infection if one person is
suffering other person can also suffer
by sharing pen Etc by living next to
them so that this is how it spread we do
not take any medicine for that because
after two to two to 3 days maximum 3 to
4 days it get cured by themselves
droplet resulting from the Cuffs sneezes
infected person are either inhaled
directly transmitted through the
contaminated object such as pens book
cup door knob computer table computer
keyboard mouse Etc it affects the mucous
membrane of respiratory tract
so many students they ask me this
question ma what is the difference
between a pneumonia and a common cold
common cold affects the mucous membrane
here but the pneumonia affects the
alali clear so there will be swelling
here due to which person is not able to
breathe whereas in pneumonia lungs are
affected now here infect the nose and
the respiratory passage not the lungs
nasal congestion discharge sore throat
Hess headache tiredness usually last for
3 to 7 Days self
diagnosable right very common and
whenever in on our house if someone is
having common cold we get that very
common common C very common Rhino
virus
okay now small poox this is the one
which is completely eradicated small
poox virus it's a virus disease caused
by the viola virus by contact droplet
formite skin rashes which forms the
pusle which causes scab and this is how
they spread some fluid come out and they
spread from one person to to another
blister fluid they take out and the skin
scrapping they take out by doing the
Laboratory test whether the small pox
virus is there or not we can get to know
it is positive for them or not small pox
completely eradicated from India next is
chicken pox very zuster virus do not be
confused this is a verola virus this is
a very Sola zuster virus by contact it
spread skin Source open and the emit
fluid flood test measles measles is the
rubiola virus by droplet from the nose
and throat fever inflammation of the
nosal membrane loss of appetite red
watery eyes and the skin rash blood test
polio you all know this is the one which
spread uh which affects the nerve cell
due to
which the there there's a inflammation
of nervous system it causes the
paralysis of limb inflammation of
nervous system muscle shrinkage limb
paralysis fenial swab dangi is the arbo
virus fighting of mosquito here many
time question comes from this topic what
is a costive age how does it spread
spread through Adis egypti Adis
egypti plasmodium vaa that spread
through anop but this is Adis egypti
please remember everyone this is Adis
egypti okay next is mile conjuctivitis
high fever backache nausea vomiting with
the help of Eliza this can be detected
Dy arbo virus ad it is Egypt Egypt
please remember everyone clear a is egyp
many times this has been asked in one
Mark okay now protozoan disease first we
have is a malaria malaria we will be
discussing in detail we have malaria in
detail let's talk about amasis amasis is
because of the anba hisoa anba hisoa
causes problem here in the stomach it
affects the mucus membrane so person
feel lot of pain so how does it spread
by eating the outside food Ana hisoa it
remain the large intestine so sometime
it yes our when our food is infested
with the uh you know the house fly they
are the carrier of antoa hyola so they
contaminate our food and water due to
which we fail constipated abdominal pain
cramp uh and SP stool with mucus and the
blood blood and stool
test
next ascariasis
ascaris ascaris swm intestinal parasite
here eggs of parasite are excreted along
with the feces infected person which
contaminate soil water vegetables and
fruits so
ascaris is a neod right it's a round
worm escalus ascaris lumbricoides so
when one person is suffering from it in
the body sexual reproduction occur and
in the intestine they produce eggs the
egg they go out from the body with the
help of a feis and when the seage water
it goes to the you know agriculture land
it can affect the fruits and a vegetable
it cause infestation there and once we
consume our fruits and vegetable without
proper washing them again we can get the
escaras infection now internal be
leading they can cause muscular pain
fever and IIA blockage of intestinal
passage stool test fasis ferial warm
elephantiasis first of agent is weria
bankrupty weria
malayi now bite of mosquito clex
mosquito previously it was Adis Egyptian
dingi here it is clex mosquito everybody
will remember this now ferial worms live
in lymphatic vessels chronic in
inflammation of the organ in which they
live for many years lims and genital
organ may be
deformed ICT fasis test so here what
happens is limb the you know scotle sack
they swallow so they become huge in size
that is the reason we call this disease
as U elephantiasis elephant type
diseases because the lymphs they become
huge in size and uh they actually block
the lymph vessel so that is the reason
it
happens
okay now the last one fungal disease
ring worm dadad KU what is this ring
worm the Ring Worm it causes some
abration like thing here and this is
because of the fungus ring it says Ring
Worm but it is not because of the worm
it looks like some scab is there some
reddish scab that cause eing fluid comes
out so that is because of the three
different species of a fungus
microsporum tropen
epidermophyton microsporum troyen
epidermophyton three all three you have
to remember given in ncrt so how does it
spread because if one person is affected
if you use their towel if you'll use
their brushes so yes it can spread from
one person to
another now from soil or by using the
towel clothes com heat moisture help
fungi to grow more which means make them
thrive in the skin folds such as those
area in the groin and in between the
toes so because of those areas in
between the toe toes there are moisture
so they develop more at those areas now
symptoms appearance of dry scaly leion
on the various body parts such as Skin
nail scalp lesions are accompanied by
the intense eating by looking at the
skin and with the use of antifungal
powders we can
easily get rid of the such problem okay
now now let's talk about as I've
discussed with you we have to discuss
the malaria in detail so let's start the
malaria let's start reading about the
malaria let's not start the
malaria yes all three name you have to
learn now
malaria malaria is caused by you know
given over here plasmodium so there are
various species of plasmodium one is
plasmodium VX malaria
felip perum and plasmodium
ovil these are the different species
right they causes different type of
malaria turchan malaria different
malarias are there so they cause cause
that now life cycle plasmodium require
two holes to complete the life cycle one
is termed as humans and second is
musk in the human they reproduce by the
asexual ual
method and in the mosquito they develop
by the sexual
reproduction sexual and
asexual clear so primary host for the
anop is the what primary host is what
primary host is a mosquito secondary
host is the human where they reproduce
by the asexual method so let's have a
look life cycle
very easy peasy can be asked again in a
three marker
guys infected person Andes musquito
bites the human whenever infected
mosquito they bite the human the
infected mosquito Andes will carry the
sporo it will carry the sporo and sporo
zoids will enter into the human right
plasmodium enter the human infectious
form sporozoite and reached via blood
now this is going to circulate all these
sporo oid will circulate in blood for
half an hour 1 second they will
circulate in blood for half an hour and
after that half an hour it can migrate
to other structures specifically the
liver then they go to the liver and they
multiply asexually in the liver cell in
the liver they cause exoerythrocytic
shogi not given again then they go to
the blood again they attack the red
blood cell when they attack the red
blood cell they feed on the RBC
hemoglobin they release some toxins
which are termed as
hemoo and these hemoo is the one which
is responsible for fever so hemoo is a
toxic substance which causes the
fever which causes the fever decrease
result in due to which chill high fever
reoccurring every 3 to 4 days so
characteristic features is after 24
hours you will get the fever after 36
hours you will get the fever depending
on which disease you are which type of
malaria you are suffering
from
now life cycle in the mosquito now what
happens
is sexual stages see what happens is
when this sporo Zoid first it migrate to
the blood then from the blood it goes to
the liver liver may it will undergo the
chisoon asexual reproduction they will
affect the liver cell then then they
will migrate to the blood in the blood
they show different stages Signet ring
stage amii boid stage and in between
that they release hemozoin also and
because of hemoo we get fever and chills
clear hope this point is clear till now
now moving on to the next if I talk
about now what happens in the blood so
in the blood they will form gy female
Gite and male Gite female Gite will be
bigger and the female male Gite will be
smaller now section ual stage gamy
develop in human RBC now what will
happen another female anop who was not
having any kind of sporozoite any
disease now they will come and they will
pick up the Gite they will feed on blood
and along with the blood they will get a
treat
gyes and now what will happen the
parasite will enter the mosquito body
done now what will happen as parasite
enter the mosquito body gamy will be
converted into
gamuts
Gite will be converted into the
gametes gyes will be converted into the
gamits male gametocytes will form male
gamut female gamy will form the female
gamut clear now fertilization occur now
there will be development in the
mosquito so those gamut female gamut and
male gamut they will fertiliz together
what we will get is a zygote and then
they develop and what they form is a
sporo zoids now multiply to form
sporozoite which is an infective stage
which goes to the salivary gland it
remain there now anop which was not
having any problem now she is having
sporozoite that two in the salivary
glands that two in the salivary glands
and if it is
there
so done
okay so so with this we have completed
the disease part now we are moving to
the next part that is the
immunity okay okay now immunity what is
immunity immunity is the ability of a
hor to fight with the disease causing
organism I have a capacity I have that
immunity that I can fight against this
disease that disease that pathogen Etc
that will be my immunity
conferred by the immune system we have a
proper immune system in our body just
like that D system we have respiratory
system we have a proper immune system
where lot of cells are there lot of
structures are there which are important
for fighting against the different
pathogen present in the
environment okay okay let's
proceed now with this chart now we will
learn each and every line everyone
please Focus over
here uh
okay immunity immunity is what it is the
ability of a host to fight the disease
causing organism this is immunity now
immunity is of two type when this
immunity is present from
birth this is termed as the non-specific
innate
immunity it consists of four typ when a
child is born child will be having skin
and mucosa which will not allow the
pathogen to enter into the body that
comes under the physical barrier of a
baby child will be secreting saliva tear
gastric juices that will come under the
physiological barrier that will not
allow the pathogen to enter next thing
is they will be having some cells like
pmnl neutrophils are there
polymorphonuclear lucites then monoy NK
cells macras are there which are
normally present and they cause
non-specific immunity they're not
specific but whatever for foreign things
will come they will kill them it's not
specific but they will definitely kill
them now cyto keines cyto keines may we
have an example of interfer
interferons okay we have is a
interferons
so acquired immunity specific acquired
immunity is that immunity which we
develop with our
lifetime
develop
with exposure
to
pathogen
in our
lives right now acquired immunity is the
immunity which is specific which is not
casual it is specific it is specific
characterized by memory it shows a
diversity
our body produce lots of antibodies and
it shows a discrimination between self
and nonself these are the four points
you have to
remember
between self and La self specificity
diversity the characterized by memory
discrimination between the self and
nonself these are the four features
which are present in
this acquired immunity is of two type
active immunity and passive immunity now
what are these active and passive
immunity active immunity is that
immunity where our body is producing
antibodies so here what do I mean by
this
body
producing anti
bodies if some pathogen is coming and
body is producing antibodies that comes
under the active immunity passive
immunities that means antibodies we are
taking from
outside from
outside clear now active immunity active
immunity is further of two type natural
active immunity and artificial active
immunity natural now here suppose
pathogen comes you went outside you had
golapa right it was open it was not
hygienically prepared so pathogen will
enter in your body your body will start
forming the
antibodies natural active
immunity now the next one is artificial
active immunity you took vaccine
shot Corona vaccine Co vaccine which one
did you took so you did you take any
vaccine right so I'm talking about those
vaccines so vaccines are what vaccines
are attenuated healed K killed pathogens
so we are taking vaccines vaccines means
pathogen healed killed disarmed pathogen
we are taking from outside and then our
body is producing antibodies against uh
that and creating um you know memories
for that that comes under this
category
now next one is passive immunity is
further of two type natural passive
immunity mother feeds the baby and when
mother feeds the baby mother passes the
IG IGA is the one which is present in
the
chrum mother's milk if I talk about the
IG G is the one which can cross the
placenta
artificial
immunity taking PATH taking antibodies
directly from outside
artificial passive immunity pre-formed
antibodies we take right for example ATS
antias C or snake
venom right at the time of whenever we
are bitten by a snake so in that case
direct these are
available
now based on the type of lymphocytes are
involved there are two type of
immunity
one cell mediated
immunity cell mediated
immunity and the second one is humoral
immunity cell mediated immunity and
humoral immunity now cell mediated
immunity is that immunity where the T
lymphocytes are
involved the lymphocytes are
involved
right cell mediated these are those
immunity where whenever see here what
happens is T lymy they further
proliferate when Whenever there is a
pathogen they proliferate how do they
proliferate they proliferate into T
helper cell t cytotoxic or t killer
cell and T suppressor
cell helper will help so what is this
this is a
helper right this is a
cytotoxic or killer killer kill oh my
God this will be
suppressor they will differentiate and
they will kill the pathogen they will
kill the pathogen So This Is How They
divide one very important thing is when
we do any grafting suppose uh liver
transplantation kidney transplantation
sometime the tissue they are not able to
graft properly our body you know start
producing antibodies against it in that
case which antibodies involved the cell
mediated immunity involved in graft
rejection graft
rejection
clear moving on to the next is humoral
immunity humoral immunity they are also
termed
as antibody mediated
immunity mediated
immunity now in this antibody mediated
immunity humoral immunity and antibody
mediated immunity in this immunity what
we we have is B
lymphocytes whenever this
osy whenever this you know and Immunity
arise in that body what happens is B
lymphocytes plasma B cells plasma B
cells produces
antibodies right and the next one they
produce is the memory cell
if you'll come for the next time I will
kill you in a short duration of time
this is the
difference clear memory and the plasma B
cells okay now as I have discussed with
you antibodies are there so this is how
antibody look like again I'm saying you
cbsc aspirant get ready this question
can be asked draw the structure of an
antibody very very very
important
this is how a antibody a typical
antibody look like typical all
antibodies they do not look
same here you will see chains are there
can you see this this one two heavy
chains are there so it is having a
structure of H2 two light chains are
there light chain light chains are there
right because of Association of heavy
chains and the light chain they form
antigen binding site which comes and
which binds to the antigen they're
attached to each other by some bonds
which you can see they are termed as
disulfide Bond so you should know the
exact location of these dulfi
Bond clear everybody clear now antigen
they come and they will bind over here
and this one they react to them how do
they react to them they cause
opsonization they Cause neutralization
they basically attach to them that's a
you know very uh difficult part they go
and they attach to them so how does they
attach so let's have a
look
so
antibodies antibody
functions in this way First Step they
cause
agglutination
tination that means they will go and
they will bind to the
antigens second is
opsonization they will cover
it and they will start engulfing It
Whatever toxin they
produce neutralization they will
neutralize it these are the different
steps by which these work these
antibodies they work clear is this point
clear so they work in this way they
agglutinate it they go and they bind to
the antigen whenever they see any
foreign body pathogen in our body they
go and they will bind to it second thing
is they will cause opsonization they
will just cover it and they will engulf
it they will call the macras to come and
engulf it next is neutralize whatever
toxin that antigen has produced they're
going to neutralize those toxins
also okay
now these are the antibodies function
how many types of antibodies are there
let's have a look
types
of
antibodies there are following type
they're also termed as imog globulins so
G IG
a
IGM IG d
i g
e
g right clear now
first G this is the one which can cross
the
placenta this is the one which can cross
placenta right a is the one a present in
chrom
present in mother's milk m m means mu mu
M1 this is the first first which reach
to the site of
infection so it is like my
buddies whenever any pathogen comes in
our body the first immunoglobin who uh
you know the number increases in blood
that is
IGM IG d d IG D IG D is a one which
activate B
cell b cells or B
lymphocytic bodies clear to all my
students yes come
on come on come on come
on okay now what we are left with now
let's talk about the
allergies allergies are exaggerated
response to of a immune system to
certain antigen present in the
environment there are lots of allergens
present in an environment which are not
pathogenic to us for example pollin they
will not cause any harm but our body
they start producing antibodies against
so that is the
allergy substance to which allergy is
produced are termed as allergen so
allergen can be anything they can be any
food some people are allergic to
mushrooms some people are allergic to
almond some are allergic to uh you know
the lemon so they can be any
Allergan
clear the antibodies prod used to these
are IG type as I've told you how will
you remember IG e e means
allergy but it's a sorry Anushka Anushka
it's an English Channel so I cannot talk
in Hindi
okay okay it's an English Channel so I
cannot talk in how can I talk in IND you
you know the what's the name of this
channel PW English physics whilea
English H know let's talk in English it
will be of two benefits will be there
you'll be good you'll be good at your
English paper and you'll be doing good
in biology also is that
[Laughter]
it so we have a shire also here oh my
God we have a sh then gorov you should
write something for
us like these people they are
continuously spamming continuously I can
see it's it's a video who's uh I am live
from last 8 hours 7 7 8 hours or
something right almost 7 7 and a half
hours I'm here I'm continuously looking
at the chat and the these people are
just talking to each other these people
are like this there's some setting going
on hi good evening otaku how are you
good
evening yeah okay no no it's
okay yes yes G sh there should be a ID
right but it should be in English and it
should be decent if it it is not decent
that I'll not uh say anything I'll not
speak hi good evening how are
[Laughter]
you you must be Googling to get a uh
good no it's okay Anushka it's okay
Anushka
it's good
now what is
this
okay okay I guess our Sher is busy in
Googling so better we should focus on
your studies
H H okay no no no it's no it's not fine
please huh do not spam here better to go
somewhere and
uh yeah
okay oh good if you belong to harana I
also belong to harana now allergy is due
to release of chemicals like histamine
and serotonin from mast cell and what is
histamine histamine is a
vasodilator
vasodilator so vasod Vaso means blood
vessel dilator mean to dilate the blood
blood vessel serotonin is Vaso
constrictor right for determination and
cause of allergy the patient is exposed
or injected to various small doses of
possible allergy and with that we can
get to know
okay okay now let's move further aut
autoimmunity now autoimmunity sometime
due to genetic and other unknown reason
the body start attacking our own body
cell considering that it a path pathogen
so they cause some diseases which is
autoimmune diseases one example is given
over here that is a uh uh
arthritis clear which is a rtid
arthritis so in the joints we have
sinovial membrane so our body start
producing antibodies against that
membrane so that becomes affected and
that there's an inflammation due to
which we fail we feel pain right while
uh you know moving our hands and the
joints if you're in eth standard if you
will be in 10th standard then you can
attm the
session
okay now moving on to the next immune
system in our body so like I have told
you B cells are there t cells are there
now let's talk about the whole system
what all things are the part of this
let's have a look now human immune
system consist of lymphoid organ tissues
cells and some molecules like antibodies
organs are there lipoid organs are there
in our body let's talk about the
lymphoid organs we have tissues also
cells so we have already discussed now
what are the lymphoid organs these are
the organs where original maturation
proliferation of
lymphocytes lymphocytes are your B and T
lymphocytes the primary lymphoid organs
are the bone marrow and the thymus so
primary lymphoid organ are those organ
where there is maturation and
proliferation of
lymphocytoid and the T lymy these are
your bone marrow and the
thymus right now after maturation the B
lymphocytoid organ and secondary
lymphoid organs are those organ where
there is interaction
of interaction
of
antigen
with
antibodies clear here the examples are
spleen lymph node tonsil spare patches
of small intestine and appendix so you
should know again I'm saying the
difference between these two the primary
lymphoid organ and the secondary
lymphoid organ primary lymphoid organ
are your bone Maro thymus secondary
lymphoid organs are your pairs patches
appendix malt G
Etc
okay
now secondary lymphoid organ provide the
site of interaction of
lymphocytic which undergo proliferation
to become eector cell so at the
secondary one there's an U this one
right interaction bone marrow is a main
lymphoid one where the all blood cell
including the lympho are produced please
remember this line either you are a cbsc
aspirant or no neat aspirant please
remember this bone marrow is a place
where either it is WBC RBC everything
formation occur in the bone marrow clear
thymus is quite large at Birth but once
we get old their size reduces thymus and
this is a place where the T lymphocytes
mature formation of T
lymphocysts all the cells of formation
occur in the bone marrow but their
maturation T lymy maturation occur in
the
thymus now bone marrow and thymus
provide micro environment for the
development maturation of T lymphocytes
spleen has a reservoir of erthrocytes
now another super important one marker
mucosa Associated lymphoid tissue
located within the lining of wheresoever
mucosa is there either it is in a
digestive tract it is there in the
respiratory tract urinogenital tract it
contribute 50% of the lymphoid tissues
in our body very very very
important primary lymphoid organ
secondary lymphoid organ difference can
be asked in your paper clear now primary
lymphoid organ bone maryus here we have
others and The Malt is the one mucosa
associate lymphoid tissue is the one
where which is which constitute almost
50%
okay let's stop shiring beta stop stop
do doing this now we have to start the
topic eights okay let me bring some
water okay I need a water let me bring
some water I don't have water where's my
bottle let me bring some water I'll be
back okay it's not a break I'm just
coming we have to start the topic of
AIDS
yes we are back
I'm back okay so let's start AIDS what
is AIDS AIDS is
acquired
immuno
deficiency
syndrome acquired immun deficiency
syndrome what is the causitive agent
it's the
HIV it is the HIV human imuno deficiency
virus human imuno deficiency virus
HIV right the first case came in
1981 first
case and in the time period of 25 years
25 million people they suffer from this
this is because of a virus the firsta uh
disease come over here so let's talk
about AIDS so how does AIDS spread
eights spread by the you all know we
have done that chapter it's spread by
sexual contact
spread by
sexual
contact surgical
instruments same surgical
instruments
unsterilized sharing of
needles right so like this way and it
also spread from the
uh you
know mother to
fetus mother to
fetus it also spread by blood
transfusion blood
transfusion here this is eight acquired
imuno deficiency syndrome so this is
caused by virus now let's study how this
virus spread with the help of this chart
now we will learn everything clear now
HIV so what happens is if you look at
this virus can you see this virus so
this virus is a retro virus we call this
as a retrovirus why do we call this as a
retrovirus because this is having
RNA as genome and along with that they
are having two single stranded RNA they
have two single stranded RNA along with
that they are having reverse
transcriptase
enzyme reverse
transcriptase they have
proteas protees enzyme and they have
integr
enzyme these are the three enzymes which
are present in them they are having two
single standard RNA they have enzyme
like uh reverse transcriptase they have
a proteas or integr
clear this is a virus and on the virus
body spikes are present GP glycoprotein
gp1 120 and GP
41 so they are having this
GP 120 and this one is made up of
glycoprotein 41
they are having two capsid made up of
protein two
capsids they have one second two single
standard
RNA right single stranded RNA two two
and enzymes are also there three enzymes
I've already written there so these are
the three enzymes which they have
clear is this clear now with the help of
this GP
120 they whenever they ENT in our body
they bind to a cell animal
cell so this cell is a
macras
macras on the macras body the CD4
receptors are present CD4 what are these
CD4 four receptors so on the CD4
receptors they will come and they will
bind right with the help of gp1 120
receptors it's not shown over here but
detail I am showing you clear they will
come and they will bind over here now
this is a nucleus sorry this is a cell
now what will happen they will they will
release the RNA into the cell now what
will they do the viral D this will they
will release the viral RNA now viral RNA
will be having the integr
enzyme clear now what will happen this
RNA will form the DNA with the help of
integr enzyme they will go and
incorporate into the nucleus or the
Genome of the cell they will introduce
now what will happen they will use the
machinery and they will prepare a copy
of it multiple virus copies will be
produced now this macrophase it will be
termed as a factory of HIV
Factory of
HIV this is a factory of HIV now what
will do it will go and it will infect
the cell it will reduce the T helper
cell number which is more than 1200 and
in HIV patient it goes less than 200 now
what will happen to
patient patient will suffer from
Toxoplasma infection will suffer from a
common code tuberculosis and whatnot
because person is imuno compromised
people do not die because of
AIDS sorry the HIV people die because of
other disease because it's a syndrome
it's a collection of disease so other
diseases they will also come there will
be cancer development because cancer can
also be because of the virus I'll show
you there are onco viruses also that can
cause V that can cause cancer so that
can also occur in
them you know and the first HIV case
that I've discussed over there was like
in 1981 so there were group of
homosexuals and they were sitting and
they were using some drug so there was a
some party going on and they were using
some drug and that drug was they were in
inserting intravenously and they were
using the same syringe and after some
time all of them they were detected with
the same diseases they were having some
cancer they were they developed the
tuberculosis so doctors they were
worried why this happened so everybody
thought maybe it was because
of uh you know of the less uh you know
the immune system was not that uh one
like not that you know functional so
they realized doctor said this but the
major reason behind the compromised
immune system was this
virus
okay now so how can we uh red how can we
uh remove this we have a um uh viral uh
retroviral drugs available in the market
Andro retro drugs are there which
increase the longivity of a person but
complete eradication is again not
possible now let's talk about the next
disease which is a cancer then we have
to do drugs and that's it we are done
yes now let's do cancer right cancer
cancer is normal
cell converted into a cancer
cell right normal cell has a capacity
that it
show
growth and
apoptosis apoptosis apoptosis is
programmed cell death some these cells
every cells they have some program
programming they divide and after some
time they die whereas the cancer cells
no
apoptosis epop
Tois these are the one which respond to
growth
factors respond to
factors they are the one who do do not
respond to growth
factor do not respond to growth factors
they do not respond okay they will not
respond to the growth factors so they
will keep on dividing so they divide
rapidly so they show controlled
division controlled
division they do not show controlled
division so there is uncontrolled
division uncontrolled
division these are the cancer cells
cancer cells this is a property the
difference between a normal cell and the
cancer cell now these cancer cell please
have a look as they show uncontrolled
division right because some changes
occur in a normal cell due to which that
cell gets converted into a cancer cell
so this occur because of the various
things now let's talk about the factors
by which it is converted so there are
first thing let's talk about the
radiations so because of the radiation
this changes
occur these radiation can be your
ionizing radiation and non ionizing
radiation ionizing
radiation or non ionizing
radiation right ionizing radiation your
xrays non other rays are also there now
let's talk about UV rays are also one of
them so now what all things there can be
viral onogen sorry enco
virus enco virus are there the
smoke whatever like we smoke right so
that is also one of the Reason by which
the cancer can happen so this these are
the reasons behind it now what does
these things causes now these two
can lead to this particular
conversion they lead to gain of
function gain of function in proto onco
Gene due to which they're converted into
onoin
they can lead to loss of
function loss of
function
in tumor suppressor
Gene tumor suppressor Gene due to which
there will be no tumor suppression if
there is no tumor suppression just
imagine guys if there is no tumor
suppression so there will be development
of a tumor isn't it yes guys so ionizing
radiation non ionizing radiation these
all are the one which causes this
problem right now let's talk about
ionizing yeah ionizing me you can take
an example of xrays gamma rays Etc this
to you know now you have already done
chemistry gamma
rays here here you have is a UV R so
they causes such problem
now normal cell converted into a cancer
cell so now let's talk about their
types types of
cancer they are of two type one is
benig benig
tumor pagal tumor that is
localized localized means it is present
at a particular location it is present
at a particular location so it is
localized second thing is
malignant malignant means now the
cells are
spreading
from spreading
from one organ to
another
to
another right now in the benan state it
becomes very easy to eradicate but in
malignancy stage it's very difficult to
eradicate because it has affected other
organs so what all properties does a
cancer cell show because it is migrated
so here they will
show
angiogenesis they show
angiogenesis angiogenesis means means
blood vessel
formation so that they can
get lot of
nutrient and do not show contact
inhibition
inhibition they do not show contact
inhibition so that means contact
inhibition is that
way by which one cell affect another so
how can we detect it this can be
detected by you know the bone marrow
test biopsy histopathogical
studies here I'm
writing
detected
by
biopsy
hiso
pathological
studies and bone
marrow suppose blood test also with the
help of blood test also when it is
related to the cancer blood cancer
because in blood cancer the wbc's number
increases Beyond a limit so blood
test and and detected
or
treatment various therapies are there
one is
surgery if it is localized easy to
remove
ionizing
sorry
immunotherapy is is there radiotherapy
is
there radiotherapy is there and Alpha
interferons also we are working in this
direction hope a good revision is
happening Alpha
interferon
immunotherapy right radiotherapy
Etc right radiations
also right so Alpha interference these
evoke are immune system and they evoke
our immune system so that our body they
can start producing antibodies against
the cancer
cells
okay
so let's move further now let's talk
about the
drugs another topic of this chapter is
drug okay let's talk about of this
chapter drugs now what are drugs drugs
are those those things which we take
externally normally these drugs they are
available in market for curing various
diseases so there are two categories of
this drugs one category of this drug is
psychotropic and second one is
psychodelic psychodelic is the one which
causes
hallucination altered thought
hallucination ation and some
psychotropic drugs are those drugs which
basically uh basically which are
sedative which will give you calm effect
sometime painkillers Etc so they will be
having this effect
sedative effect in some cases They Are
depressants
also depressant also so these are the
categories so here in the in this
category we have is
we have is uh you know what's the
name
tranquilizer tranquilizers come this
category tranquilizers are like benzo
dipine and uh your barbiturates they
come under this category they we have is
this uh
stimulants then we have is this
ofid opioids they come under this
category rest all they come under the
psychodelic drugs yeah psychotropic are
the sedative drugs you will be uh you
know it will give you a calmness effect
you will be calmed and the depressant it
has very bad impact in our body clear we
are talking about it now first is is
opioids now we are discussing one by one
first let's talk about opioids opioids
come under like I've told you
psychotropic drug psychotropic drugs are
those drugs which affects our body and
this gives a you know a sedative effect
a calmness effect and here The receptors
are present on the center nervous system
and gastrointestinal tract of opioids
they are taken from the poppy plant that
is a pomn ferum very important
right and this is extracted from the
latex latex of puppy plant now they are
taken by snotting and by injection here
the examples are morphine heroin smack
di atile Morphin so these are basically
used uh at earlier time when there were
there was a war war so people used to
take it you know when these people they
were in injured so at that time it was
used but nowadays people they've started
us using it they produce they think that
it produce a calmness effect it gives
them a good uh you know a Euphoria kind
of thing so they take it which is not
really which is very bad for our body it
is effective sedative
painkiller but I am saying that it is a
drug which because people they are not
using it as a painkiller now it is
undergo surgery it is used at that time
it is a depressant slow down the body
function it is orderless white bitter
crystalline compound this is a
opioids receptors are present in central
nervous system and the gastrointestinal
tract next is cannabinoids canabo
monoids receptors they are present in
brain now these are the one so it
activates our body you will be activated
once the person will take it they will
be activated activated means that this
increases the cardiovascular activity so
overall these are these are amongst
those drugs which are uh you know um
which are made mainly used by the sports
person right in fluoresence FL tops
leaves raisins of the cannabis plants
Canabis sativa inhalation by Oral
ingestion charas hashish ganja marijuana
comes under this category effects on
cardiovascular system of the body and
being abused by the sports
person yeah now
stimulants stimulants are the one which
stimulate our body so this also comes
under the category of psychotropic drugs
again I'm saying this is isolated from
the arthro xylm Coca coca plant coca
arthro zym coca here have you heard of
cocaine coca now if I talk about the
energy drinks you take in energy drinks
I won't take the name this is there so
it gives you that stimulant effect so
one should not take it because
dependency increases so it is taken by
snotting cocaine coca alkaloid commonly
called Coke or crack it interfere with
the transport of neurotransmitter
dopamine potent stimulant action of
Center n a system producing sense of
euphoria increased energy excessive
dosage can cause hallucinations
hallucinations is altered thought right
stimulants they stimulate it again I'm
saying do not be dependent you guys are
uh appearing for the board examination
and many student they feel can we feel
sleepy or let's take this energy drink
XYZ whatever you want whatever you take
they're not good for the body they are
seriously not good for the body it
dependency increases with
time now first is next is hallucinogens
hallucinogens we have a category atropa
badona and
datura so have been used hundred of
years in folk medicines regions
ceremonies and rituals all over the
globe so you know about the datura even
in the Puja whenever we worship we use
datura also so that is also a
hallucinogens that cause hallucinations
other drugs synthetic drugs available in
the market like barbituate and benzo
dipine barbituate and benzoin comes
under the category of the
tranquilizers tranquilizers they are
given to patient who suffer from the
mental illness for their calmness but
people now they have started using it
amphetamine they also comes under this
category they help patient cope up with
a mental illness like depression and
insomnia right clear and also guys when
uh here morphine is written do you know
uh when whenever we take cuff medicines
so we feel sleepy and it's on the back
side of a cuff syrup it is written one
should not drive after taking the cuff
syrup because that contains morphine so
it gives a calm effect it can uh induce
sleep also that is a reason
okay okay now let's talk about the
alcohol these are the problems related
to adolesence M next problem we have is
a alcohol alcohol what is the AL what is
what does alcohol do it increases the
body activity or it lowers the body
activity so what do you feel like after
taking
alcohol one should not take if you see
people when they take alcohol do they
become active or they
depress they become inactive so it
produces that you know sedative calmness
calmness effect it's a depressant yes it
slowers the body uh activities it
because it lowers the blood sugar level
so person thinking capacity is AFF Ed
blood May there will be less sugar going
alcohol drinking affect the cerebelum
part of the brain so control and
coordination is badly affected you know
the people they just they whenever they
take alcohol they just roam around they
do not have a body control when they're
not able to speak properly this is
because the cerebelum is
affected okay next yes it affects the
liver also excess alcohol in the yes it
affects the major organ which it affects
is the liver that you all know
so what happens in the liver is this
alcohol when someone takes it goes to
stomach from the stomach it will be
absorbed it will go directly to the
liver liver mate will be converted into
the fat so first stage will be the fatty
liver first stage will be the fatty
liver and it can affect the liver
because it can deposited uh the fat can
deposit into the liver cells and the
bile duct that can lead to the fatty
liver this is a first stage if people
take more like lot of alcohol this can
lead to the liver therosis liver sosis
means fibrous tissue formation and that
is a irreversible change in the liver if
someone is having fatty liver fatty
liver can be reversed right by removing
uh alcohol from their diet now next
thing is if liver fibrous tissue
formation occur liver curosis that is
not
curable
clear
now okay next is it can lead to loss of
memory cause the inflammation of wall of
stomach chronic cases ulcers can develop
overall body resistance against disease
that means our immune system is also
badly affected okay if someone at your
place anyone who takes alcohol this is
not good for the body in fact the those
drugs which I have discussed they are
also not good for the body and now let's
talk about the
smoking so smoking means tobacco so
tobacco can be taken in any form CH tell
me smoking or the tobacco when we talk
about the tobacco tobacco here nicotine
is present so it is a stimulant or it
suppress the
body tell
me tobacco it stimulates the body or it
suppress the
body
yes it's sub yes it stimulates the body
it can be taken in the form of smoked
chewed and snuff it contain large number
of chemical which is nicotine nicotine
stimulate adrenal gland to release
adrenaline yes it causes the adrenal
gland to release adrenaline and non-
adrenaline when adrenaline and non-
adrenaline is there there will be brush
you know BP increases blood pressure
increases the respiratory weight
increases heartbeat
increases yes absolutely right so
smoking is associated with increased
incidence of cancer of lungs urinary
bladder throat bronchitis empyema
coronary heart disease gastric ulcers
see look at the
diseases look at the
diseases
yes so guys with with this we have
completed your whole
syllabus so it's more than 8 hours we
are live and you're continuously with me
good job did a great job with this we
have completed all the chapters starting
from Human reproduction to reproductive
Health then we talked about Evolution
biotechnology human health and diseases
we have discussed
everything if you haven't seen the
session from the starting do watch it
before your paper it will be a great
help great revision for you
guys so can we wind up the session
here hope you're not tired you're full
of energy all the all the best for your
examination have a nice day bye-bye guys
good night take care yes thank you so
much
guys